<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

<string name="cvsem1sub3">Mathematics-I</string>
    <string name="Math1cv">\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> CALCULUS (SINGLE VARIBALE)</font></b>\n\n\n

              <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1A: CALCULUS: (12 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

INTERVALS, CONVERGENCE OF SEQUENCES AND SERIES OF REAL NUMBERS, LIMIT AND CONTINUITY OF FUNCTIONS, DIFFERENTIABILITY OF FUNCTIONS, ROLLE THEOREM, MEAN VALUE THEOREMS, TAYLORS AND MACLAURIN THEOREMS WITH REMAINDERS; INDETERMINATE FORMS AND L HOSPITAL RULE; MAXIMA AND MINIMA, RIEMANN INTEGRATION, FUNDAMENTAL THEOREM OF CALCULUS.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1B: CALCULUS: (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EVOLUTES AND INVOLUTES; EVALUATION OF DEFINITE AND IMPROPER INTEGRALS; BETA AND GAMMA FUNCTIONS AND THEIR PROPERTIES; APPLICATIONS OF DEFINITE INTEGRALS TO EVALUATE SURFACE AREAS AND VOLUMES OF REVOLUTIONS.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1C: SERIES: (PREREQUISITE 2B) (8 LECTURES)\n\n\n</font></b>

POWER SERIES, TAYLOR SERIES. SERIES FOR EXPONENTIAL, TRIGONOMETRIC AND LOGARITHMIC FUNCTIONS; FOURIER SERIES: HALF RANGE SINE AND COSINE SERIES, PARSEVAL THEOREM\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXTBOOKS/REFERENCES:\n\n\n</font></b>

~G.B. THOMAS AND R.L. FINNEY, CALCULUS AND ANALYTIC GEOMETRY, 9TH EDITION, PEARSON, REPRINT, 2002.\n\n\n

~ VEERARAJAN T., ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS FOR FIRST YEAR, TATA MCGRAW-HILL, NEW DELHI, 2008.\n\n\n

~ RAMANA B.V., HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, TATA MCGRAW HILL NEW DELHI, 11TH REPRINT, 2010.\n\n\n

~N.P. BALI AND MANISH GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, REPRINT, 2010.\n\n\n

~B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 35TH EDITION, 2000.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MATRICES AND LINEAR ALGEBRA\n\n\n</font></b>

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2A: MATRICES (IN CASE VECTOR SPACES IS NOT TO BE TAUGHT) (14 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

ALGEBRA OF MATRICES, INVERSE AND RANK OF A MATRIX, RANK-NULLITY THEOREM; SYSTEM OF LINEAR EQUATIONS; SYMMETRIC, SKEW-SYMMETRIC AND ORTHOGONAL MATRICES; DETERMINANTS; EIGENVALUES AND EIGENVECTORS; DIAGONALIZATION OF MATRICES; CAYLEY-HAMILTON THEOREM, ORTHOGONAL TRANSFORMATION AND QUADRATIC TO CANONICAL FORMS.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2B: MATRICES (IN CASE VECTOR SPACES IS TO BE TAUGHT) (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

MATRICES, VECTORS: ADDITION AND SCALAR MULTIPLICATION, MATRIX MULTIPLICATION; LINEAR SYSTEMS OF EQUATIONS, LINEAR INDEPENDENCE, RANK OF A MATRIX, DETERMINANTS, CRAMER\'S RULE, INVERSE OF A MATRIX, GAUSS ELIMINATION AND GAUSS-JORDAN ELIMINATION.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2C: VECTOR SPACES (PREREQUISITE 4B) (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

VECTOR SPACE, LINEAR DEPENDENCE OF VECTORS, BASIS, DIMENSION; LINEAR TRANSFORMATIONS (MAPS), RANGE AND KERNEL OF A LINEAR MAP, RANK AND NULLITY, INVERSE OF A LINEAR TRANSFORMATION, RANK- NULLITY THEOREM, COMPOSITION OF LINEAR MAPS, MATRIX ASSOCIATED WITH A LINEAR MAP.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2D: VECTOR SPACES (PREREQUISITE 4B-C) (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EIGENVALUES, EIGENVECTORS, SYMMETRIC, SKEW-SYMMETRIC AND ORTHOGONAL MATRICES, EIGENBASES. DIAGONALIZATION; INNER PRODUCT SPACES, GRAM-SCHMIDT ORTHOGONALIZATION.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXTBOOKS/REFERENCES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~ D. POOLE, LINEAR ALGEBRA: A MODERN INTRODUCTION, 2ND EDITION, BROOKS/COLE, 2005.\n\n\n

~ V. KRISHNAMURTHY, V.P. MAINRA AND J.L. ARORA, AN INTRODUCTION TO LINEAR ALGEBRA, AFFILIATED EAST-WEST PRESS, REPRINT 2005.\n\n\n

~ ERWIN KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, 9TH EDITION, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n

~ VEERARAJAN T., ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS FOR FIRST YEAR, TATA MCGRAW-HILL, NEW DELHI, 2008.\n\n\n

~N.P. BALI AND MANISH GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, REPRINT, 2010.\n\n\n

~B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 35TH EDITION, 2000\n\n\n

    </string>

<string name="cvsem1sub4">Physics</string>
<string name="cvphy">


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:3 T:1 P:3 Credit:5.5</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>DETAIL CONTENT PRE-REQUISITION: HIGH-SCHOOL EDUCATION\n\n\n</b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: (08 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

TRANSFORMATION OF SCALARS AND VECTORS UNDER ROTATION TRANSFORMATION; FORCES IN NATURE; NEWTON\'S LAWS AND ITS COMPLETENESS IN DESCRIBING PARTICLE MOTION; FORM INVARIANCE OF NEWTON\'S SECOND LAW; SOLVING NEWTON\'S EQUATIONS OF MOTION IN POLAR COORDINATES; PROBLEMS INCLUDING CONSTRAINTS AND FRICTION; EXTENSION TO CYLINDRICAL AND SPHERICAL COORDINATES.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: (07 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

POTENTIAL ENERGY FUNCTION; F = GRAD V, EQUIPOTENTIAL SURFACES AND MEANING OF GRADIENT; CONSERVATIVE AND NON-CONSERVATIVE FORCES, CURL OF A FORCE FIELD; CENTRAL FORCES; CONSERVATION OF ANGULAR MOMENTUM; ENERGY EQUATION AND ENERGY DIAGRAMS; ELLIPTICAL, PARABOLOIC AND HYPERBOLIOC ORBITS; KEPLER PROBLEM; APPLICATION: STELLITE MANOEUVRES.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: (05 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

NON-INERTIAL FRAMES OF REFERENCE. ROTATING COORDINATE SYSTEM: FIVE-TERM ACCELERATION FORMULA. CENTRIPETAL AND CORIOLIS ACCELERATIONS; APPLICATIONS: WEATHER SYSTEMS, FOUCAULT PENDULUM.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: (06 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

HARMONIC OSCILLATOR; DAMPED HARMONIC MOTION - OVER-DAMPED, CRITICALLY DAMPED AND LIGHTLY-DAMPED OSCILLATORS; FORCED OSCILLATIONS AND RESONANCE.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 5:(05 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

DEFINITION AND MOTION OF A RIGID BODY IN THE PLANE. ROTATION IN THE PLANE; KINEMATICS IN A COORDINATE SYSTEM ROTATING AND TRANSLATING IN THE PLANE; ANGULAR MOMENTUM ABOUT A POINT OF A RIGID BODY IN PLANAR MOTION. EULER LAW\'S OF MOTION THEIR INDEPENDENCE FROM NEWTON\'S LAWS, AND THEIR NECESSITY IN DESCRIBING RIGID BODY MOTION; EXAMPLES.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6: (07 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

INTRODUCTION TO THREE-DIMENSIONAL RIGID BODY MOTION — (A) ANGULAR VELOCITY VECTOR, AND ITS RATE OF CHANGE AND (B) MOMENT OF INERTIA TENSOR; THREE-DIMENSIONAL MOTION OF A RIGID BODY WHEREIN ALL POINT MOVE IN A COPLANAR MANNER: e.g. ROD EXECUTING CONICAL MOTION WITH CENTER OF MASS FIXED —ONLY NEED TO SHOW THAT THIS MOTION LOOKS TWO-DIMENSIONAL BUT IS THREE-DIMENSIONAL AND TWO -DIMENSIONSAL FORMULATION FAILS.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED REFERENCE BOOKS:</font></b>\n\n\n

~ ENGINEERING MECHANICS, 2ND ED. - MK HARBOLA\n\n\n

~ INTRODUCTION TO MECHANICS - MK VERMA\n\n\n

- AN INTRODUCTION TO MECHANICS-D KLEPPNER &amp;

KOLENKOW ~ PRINCIPLES OF MECHANICS - JL SYNGE &amp; BA GRIFFITHS\n\n\n

~ MECHANICS - JP DEN HARTOG\n\n\n

~ ENGINEERING MECHANICS - DYNAMICS, 7TH ED. - JL

MERIAM\n\n\n

~ MECHANICAL VIBRATION - JP DEN HARTOG.\n\n\n

~ THEORY OF VIBRATION WITH APPLICATIONS - WT THOMSON.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>List of Experiments:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Measurements of length (or diameter) using vernier caliper, screw gauge, and travelling microscope.\n\n\n

2. To determine the Height of an object using a Sextant.\n\n\n

3. To determine the Moment of Inertia of a Flywheel.\n\n\n

4. To verify that fundamental frequency of vibration of a steel bar clamped at one end is inversely proportional to the square of its length and measure the Young\'s modulus of bar.\n\n\n
5. To determine g by Bar Pendulum.\n\n\n

6. To determine g and velocity for a freely falling body using Digital Timing Technique.\n\n\n

7. To compare the moment of inertia of a solid sphere and hollow sphere or solid disc of same mass with the torsional pendulum.\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem2sub2">Mathematics-II(Differential Equations)</string>
<string name="M2cv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Mathematics -II (Differential Equations) L:3 T:1 P:0 Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3A: FIRST ORDER ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EXACT, LINEAR AND BERNOULLI EQUATIONS, EULER EQUATIONS, EQUATIONS NOT OF FIRST DEGREE: EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR P, EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR Y, EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR X AND CLAIRAUT TYPE.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3B: ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS OF HIGHER ORDERS (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

SECOND ORDER LINEAR DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS WITH VARIABLE COEFFICIENTS, METHOD OF VARIATION OF PARAMETERS,

CAUCHY-EULER EQUATION; POWER SERIES SOLUTIONS; LEGENDRE POLYNOMIALS, BESSEL FUNCTIONS OF THE FIRST KIND AND THEIR PROPERTIES.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXTBOOKS/REFERENCES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~ ERWIN KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, 9TH EDITION, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n

~W. E. BOYCE AND R. C. DIPRIMA, ELEMENTARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS AND BOUNDARY VALUE PROBLEMS, 9TH EDITION, WILEY INDIA, 2009.\n\n\n
~S. L. ROSS, DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, 3RD ED., WILEY INDIA, 1984.\n\n\n

~E. A. CODDINGTON, AN INTRODUCTION TO ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, PRENTICE HALL INDIA, 1995.\n\n\n

~E. L. INCE, ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, DOVER PUBLICATIONS, 1958.\n\n\n

~G.F. SIMMONS AND S.G. KRANTZ, DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, TATA MCGRAW HILL, 2007.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS>\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3C: PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS - FIRST ORDER (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

FIRST ORDER PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, SOLUTIONS OF FIRST ORDER LINEAR AND NON-LINEAR PDES.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 3D: PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS - HIGHER ORDER (10 LECTURES)\n\n\n</font></b>

SOLUTION TO HOMOGENOUS AND NON-HOMOGENOUS LINEAR PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS SECOND AND HIGHER ORDER BY COMPLIMENTARY FUNCTION AND PARTICULAR INTEGRAL METHOD. FLOWS, VIBRATIONS AND DIFFUSIONS, SECOND-ORDER LINEAR EQUATIONS AND THEIR CLASSIFICATION, INITIAL AND BOUNDARY CONDITIONS (WITH AN INFORMAL DESCRIPTION OF WELL-POSED PROBLEMS), D ALEMBERT SOLUTION OF THE WAVE EQUATION; DUHAMEL PRINCIPLE FOR ONE DIMENSIONAL WAVE EQUATION. SEPARATION OF VARIABLES METHOD TO SIMPLE PROBLEMS IN CARTESIAN COORDINATES. THE LAPLACIAN IN PLANE, CYLINDRICAL AND SPHERICAL POLAR COORDINATES, SOLUTIONS WITH BESSEL FUNCTIONS AND LEGENDRE FUNCTIONS. ONE DIMENSIONAL DIFFUSION EQUATION AND ITS SOLUTION BY SEPARATION OF VARIABLES. BOUNDARY-VALUE PROBLEMS: SOLUTION OF BOUNDARY-VALUE PROBLEMS FOR VARIOUS LINEAR PDES IN VARIOUS GEOMETRIES.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXTBOOKS/REFERENCES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~S. J. FARLOW, PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS FOR SCIENTISTS AND ENGINEERS, DOVER PUBLICATIONS, 1993.\n\n\n

~R. HABERMAN, ELEMENTARY APPLIED PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS WITH FOURIER SERIES\n\n\n

~ AND BOUNDARY VALUE PROBLEM, 4TH ED., PRENTICE HALL, 1998.\n\n\n

~IAN SNEDDON, ELEMENTS OF PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, MCGRAW HILL, 1964.\n\n\n

~ MANISH GOYAL AND N.P. BALI, TRANSFORMS AND PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, UNIVERSITY SCIENCE PRESS, SECOND EDITION, 2010.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>COMPLEX VARIABLES\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4A: COMPLEX VARIABLE - DIFFERENTIATION (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

DIFFERENTIATION, CAUCHY-RIEMANN EQUATIONS, ANALYTIC FUNCTIONS, HARMONIC FUNCTIONS, FINDING HARMONIC CONJUGATE; ELEMENTARY ANALYTIC FUNCTIONS (EXPONENTIAL, TRIGONOMETRIC, LOGARITHM) AND THEIR PROPERTIES; CONFORMAL MAPPINGS, MOBIUS TRANSFORMATIONS AND THEIR PROPERTIES.\n\n\n

 MODULE 4B: COMPLEX VARIABLE - INTEGRATION (8 LECTURES)

CONTOUR INTEGRALS, CAUCHY-GOURSAT THEOREM (WITHOUT PROOF), CAUCHY INTEGRAL FORMULA (WITHOUT PROOF), LIOUVILLE THEOREM AND MAXIMUM-MODULUS THEOREM(WITHOUT PROOF); TAYLOR\'S SERIES, ZEROS OF ANALYTIC FUNCTIONS, SINGULARITIES, LAURENT SERIES; RESIDUES, CAUCHY RESIDUE THEOREM (WITHOUT PROOF), EVALUATION OF DEFINITE INTEGRAL INVOLVING SINE AND COSINE, EVALUATION OF CERTAIN IMPROPER INTEGRALS USING THE BROMWICH CONTOUR.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4C: APPLICATIONS OF COMPLEX INTEGRATION BY RESIDUES: (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EVALUATION OF DEFINITE INTEGRAL INVOLVING SINE AND COSINE. EVALUATION OF CERTAIN IMPROPER INTEGRALS USING THE BROMWICH CONTOUR.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXTBOOKS/REFERENCES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~ ERWIN KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, 9TH EDITION, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n

~J. W. BROWN AND R. V. CHURCHILL, COMPLEX VARIABLES AND APPLICATIONS, 7TH ED., MC- GRAW HILL, 2004.\n\n\n

~ VEERARAJAN T., ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS FOR FIRST YEAR, TATA MCGRAW-HILL, NEW DELHI, 2008.\n\n\n

~N.P. BALI AND MANISH GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, REPRINT, 2010.\n\n\n

~B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 35TH EDITION, 2000.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>NUMERICAL METHODS\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5A: NUMERICAL METHODS-1 (12 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

SOLUTION OF POLYNOMIAL AND TRANSCENDENTAL EQUATIONS - BISECTION METHOD, NEWTON-RAPHSON METHOD AND REGULA-FALSI METHOD. FINITE DIFFERENCES, RELATION BETWEEN OPERATORS, INTERPOLATION USING NEWTON FORWARD AND BACKWARD DIFFERENCE FORMULAE. INTERPOLATION WITH UNEQUAL INTERVALS: NEWTON DIVIDED DIFFERENCE AND LAGRANGES FORMULAE. NUMERICAL DIFFERENTIATION, NUMERICAL INTEGRATION: TRAPEZOIDAL RULE AND SIMPSON 1/3RD AND 3/8 RULES.\n\n\n

 MODULE 5B: NUMERICAL METHODS - 2 (10 LECTURES)

ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS: TAYLOR SERIES, EULER AND MODIFIED EULER METHODS. RUNGE- KUTTA METHOD OF FOURTH ORDER FOR SOLVING FIRST AND SECOND ORDER EQUATIONS. MILNE AND ADAM\'S PREDICATOR-CORRECTOR METHODS. PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS: FINITE DIFFERENCE SOLUTION TWO DIMENSIONAL LAPLACE EQUATION AND POISSION EQUATION, IMPLICIT AND EXPLICIT METHODS FOR ONE DIMENSIONAL HEAT EQUATION (BENDER-SCHMIDT AND CRANK-NICHOLSON METHODS), FINITE DIFFERENCE EXPLICIT METHOD FOR WAVE EQUATION.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXTBOOKS/REFERENCES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~P. KANDASAMY, K. THILAGAVATHY, K. GUNAVATHI, NUMERICAL METHODS, S. CHAND and COMPANY, 2ND EDITION, REPRINT 2012.\n\n\n

~S.S. SASTRY, INTRODUCTORY METHODS OF NUMERICAL ANALYSIS, PHI, 4TH EDITION, 2005.\n\n\n

~ ERWIN KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, 9TH EDITION, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n

~ B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 35TH EDITION, 2010.\n\n\n
</string>


<string name="cvsem3sub1">Basic Electronics</string>
<string name="BEcv">\n\n\n

 The objective of this Course is to provide the students with an introductory and broad treatment of the field of Electronics Engineering to facilitate better understanding of the devices, instruments and sensors used in Civil Engineering applications. Lab should be taken concurrently. This course emphasizes more on the laboratory/practical use of the knowledge gained from the course lectures.\n\n\n

    <b>What Will I Learn?\n\n\n</b>

a) Know broadly the concepts and functionalities of the electronic devices, tools and instruments\n\n\n

b) Understand use, general specifications and deployabilities of the electronic devices, and assemblies\n\n\n

c) Confidence in handling and usage of electronic devices, tools and instruments in engineering applications\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus (All modules to provide only broad overview)\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module1:</font></b>\n\n\n

Diodes and Applications covering, Semiconductor Diode - Ideal versus Practical, Resistance Levels, Diode Equivalent Circuits, Load Line Analysis; Diode as a Switch, Diode as a Rectifier, Half Wave and Full Wave Rectifiers with and without Filters; Breakdown Mechanisms, Zener Diode - Operation and Applications; Opto-Electronic Devices - LEDs, Photo Diode and Applications; Silicon Controlled Rectifier (SCR) - Operation, Construction, Characteristics, Ratings, Applications;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n

Transistor Characteristics covering, Bipolar Junction Transistor (BJT) - Construction, Operation, Amplifying Action, Common Base, Common Emitter and Common Collector Configurations, Operating Point, Voltage Divider Bias Configuration; Field Effect Transistor (FET) - Construction, Characteristics of Junction FET, Depletion and Enhancement type Metal Oxide Semiconductor (MOS) FETS, Introduction to CMOS circuits;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n

Transistor Amplifiers and Oscillators covering, Classification, Small Signal Amplifiers - Basic Features, Common Emitter Amplifier, Coupling and Bypass Capacitors, Distortion, AC Equivalent Circuit; Feedback Amplifiers - Principle, Advantages of Negative Feedback, Topologies, Current Series and Voltage Series Feedback Amplifiers; Oscillators - Classification, RC Phase Shift, Wien Bridge, High Frequency LC and Non-Sinusoidal type Oscillators;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n

Operational Amplifiers and Applications covering, Introduction to Op-Amp, Differential Amplifier Configurations, CMRR, PSRR, Slew Rate; Block Diagram, Pin Configuration of 741 Op-Amp, Characteristics of Ideal OpAmp, Concept of Virtual Ground;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practicals:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n

Laboratory Sessions covering, Identification, Specifications, Testing of R, L, C Components (Colour Codes), Potentiometers, Switches (SPDT, DPDT and DIP), Bread Boards and Printed Circuit Boards (PCBs); Identification, Specifications, Testing of Active Devices - Diodes, BJTs, JFETS, MOSFETs, Power Transistors, SCRs and LEDs;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n

Study and Operation of Digital Multi Meter, Function / Signal Generator, Regulated Power Supply (RPS), Cathode Ray Oscilloscopes; Amplitude, Phase and Frequency of Sinusoidal Signals using Lissajous Patterns on CRO; (CRO);\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n

Experimental Verification of PN Junction Diode Characteristics in A) Forward Bias B) Reverse Bias, Zener Diode Characteristics and Zener Diode as Voltage Regulator, Input and Output Characteristics of BJT in Common Emitter (CE) Configuration, Drain and Transfer Characteristics of JFET in Common Source (CS) Configuration;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n

Study of Half Wave and Full Wave Rectification, Regulation with Filters, Gain and Bandwidth of BJT Common Emitter (CE) Amplifier, Gain and Bandwidth of JFET Common Source (CS) Amplifier, Gain and Bandwidth of BJT Current Series and Voltage Series Feedback Amplifiers, Oscillation Frequency of BJT based RC Phase Shift, Hartley and Colpitts Oscillators;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n

Op-Amp Applications - Adder, Subtractor, Voltage Follower and Comparator; Op-Amp Applications - Differentiator and Integrator, Square Wave and Triangular Wave Generation, Applications of 555 Timer - Astable and Monostable Multivibrators;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n

Truth Tables and Functionality of Logic Gates - NOT, OR, AND, NOR, NAND, XOR and XNOR Integrated Circuits (ICs); Truth Tables and Functionality of Flip-Flops - SR, JK and D Flip-Flop ICs; Serial-In-Serial-Out and Serial-In-Parallel-Out Shift operations using 4-bit/8-bit Shift Register ICs; Functionality of Up-Down / Decade Counter ICs; (15 Sessions)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. David. A. Bell (2003), Laboratory Manual for Electronic Devices and Circuits, Prentice Hall, India\n\n\n

2. Santiram Kal (2002), Basic Electronics- Devices, Circuits and IT Fundamentals, Prentice Hall, India 3. Thomas L. Floyd and R. P. Jain (2009), Digital Fundamentals by Pearson Education, 4. Paul B. Zbar, A.P. Malvino and M.A. Miller (2009), Basic Electronics - A Text-Lab. Manual, TMH 5. R.T. Paynter (2009), Introductory Electronic Devices and Circuits, Conventional Flow Version, Pearson\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem3sub2">Biology For Engineers</string>


    <string name="cvsem3sub3">Computer-Aided Civil Engineering Drawing</string>
<string name="cadcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Drawing 1L:0T:2P 2 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>The students will be able to</b>\n\n\n

a) Develop Parametric design and the conventions of formal engineering drawing\n\n\n

b) Produce and interpret 2D and 3D drawings\n\n\n

c) Communicate a design idea/concept graphically/ visually d) Examine a design critically and with understanding of CAD

- The student learn to interpret drawings, and to produce designs using a combination of 2D and 3D software.\n\n\n

e) Get a Detailed study of an engineering artifact\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus (No. of lectures shown within brackets)</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n

INTRODUCTION; Introduction to concept of drawings, Interpretation of typical drawings, Planning drawings to show information concisely and comprehensively; optimal layout of drawings and Scales; Introduction to computer aided drawing, co-ordinate systems, reference planes. Commands: Initial settings, Drawing aids, Drawing basic entities, Modify commands, Layers, Text and Dimensioning, Blocks. Drawing presentation norms and standards. (2)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n

SYMBOLS AND SIGN CONVENTIONS: Materials, Architectural, Structural, Electrical and Plumbing symbols. Rebar drawings and structural steel fabrication and connections drawing symbols, welding symbols; dimensioning standards (2)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n

MASONRY BONDS: English Bond and Flemish Bond - Corner wall and Cross walls - One brick wall and one and half brick wall (1)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n

BUILDING DRAWING: Terms, Elements of planning building drawing, Methods of making line drawing and detailed drawing. Site plan, floor plan, elevation and section drawing of small residential buildings. Foundation plan. Roof drainage plans. Depicting joinery, standard fittings and fixtures, finishes. Use of Notes to improve clarity (7)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n

PICTORIAL VIEW: Principles of isometrics and perspective drawing. Perspective view of building. Fundamentals of Building Information Modelling (BIM) (3)

 Total 15 sessions\n\n\n

<b>It may be advisable to conduct Theory sessions along with

    Lab demonstrations.</b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>List of Drawing Experiments:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Buildings with load bearing walls including details of doors and windows. 09\n\n\n

2. Taking standard drawings of a typical two storeyed building including all MEP, joinery, rebars, finishing and other details and writing out a description of the Facility in about 500-700 words. 06\n\n\n

3. RCC framed structures 09\n\n\n

4. Reinforcement drawings for typical slabs, beams, columns and spread footings. 09\n\n\n

5. Industrial buildings - North light roof structures - Trusses 06\n\n\n

6. Perspective view of one and two storey buildings 06\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Total L: 15+ P: 45=60</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Subhash C Sharma and Gurucharan Singh (2005), "Civil Engineering Drawing", Standard Publishers \n\n\n2. Ajeet Singh (2002), "Working with AUTOCAD 2000 with

updates on AUTOCAD 2001", Tata- Mc Graw-Hill Company

Limited, New Delhi\n\n\n 3. Sham Tickoo Swapna D (2009), "AUTOCAD for Engineers and Designers", Pearson Education,\n\n\n

4. Venugopal (2007), "Engineering Drawing and Graphics + AUTOCAD", New Age International Pvt. Ltd.,\n\n\n

5. Balagopal and Prabhu (1987), "Building Drawing and Detailing", Spades publishing KDR building, Calicut,\n\n\n

6. (Corresponding set of) CAD Software Theory and User Manuals.\n\n\n

7. Malik R.S., Meo, G.S. (2009) Civil Engineering Drawing, Computech Publication Ltd New Asian.\n\n\n

8. Sikka, V.B. (2013), A Course in Civil Engineering Drawing, S.K.Kataria and Sons,\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Goals and Outcomes:\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b>The course should enable the students to</b>\n\n\n

i) To develop graphical skills for communicating concepts, ideas and designs of engineering products graphically/ visually as well as understand another person\'s designs, ii) and to get exposure to national standards relating to technical drawings using Computer Aided Design and Drafting practice\n\n\n

iii) Develop Parametric design and the conventions of formal engineering drawing\n\n\n

iv) Produce and interpret 2D and 3D drawings\n\n\n

v) Examine a design critically and with understanding of CAD - The student learn to interpret drawings, and to produce designs using a combination of 2D and 3D software.\n\n\n

vi) Do a detailed study of an engineering artefact\n\n\n

vii) Develop drawings for conventional structures using practical norms.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem3sub4">Engineering Mechanics</string>


    <string name="cvsem3sub5">Surveying and Geomatics</string>
<string name="SAGcv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>2L:0T:2P

        3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>Course Objectives With the successful completion of the course, the student should have the capability to:\n\n\n</b>
    a) describe the function of surveying in civil engineering construction,\n\n\n
    b) Work with survey observations, and perform calculations,\n\n\n
    c) Customary units of measure. Identify the sources of measurement errors and mistakes; understand the difference between accuracy and precision as it relates to distance, differential leveling, and angular measurements,\n\n\n
    d) Be familiar with the principals of recording accurate, orderly, complete, and logical field notes from surveying operations, whether recorded manually or with automatic data collection methods,\n\n\n
    e) Identify and calculate the errors in measurements and to develop corrected values for differential level circuits, horizontal distances and angles for open or closed-loop traverses,\n\n\n
    f) Operate an automatic level to perform differential and profile leveling; properly record notes; mathematically reduce and check levelling measurements,\n\n\n
    g) Effectively communicate with team members during field activities; identify appropriate safety procedures for personal protection; properly handle and use measurement instruments. Be able to identify hazardous environments and take measures to insure one\'s personal and team safety,\n\n\n
    h) Measure horizontal, vertical, and zenith angles with a transit, theodolite, total station or survey grade GNSS instruments,\n\n\n
    i) Calculate azimuths, latitudes and departures, error of closure; adjust latitudes and departures and determine coordinates for a closed traverse,\n\n\n
    j) Perform traverse calculations; determine latitudes, departures, and coordinates of control points and balancing errors in a traverse. Use appropriate software for calculations and mapping,\n\n\n
    k) Operate a total station to measure distance, angles, and to calculate differences in elevation. Reduce data for application in a geographic information system,\n\n\n
    l) Work as a team member on a surveying party to achieve a common goal of accurate and timely project completion,\n\n\n
    m) Calculate, design and layout horizontal and vertical curves, Understand, interpret, and prepare plan, profile, and cross-section drawings, Work with cross-sections and topographic maps to calculate areas, volumes, and earthwork quantities.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Proposed Syllabus:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Introduction to Surveying (8 hours):</font></b>\n\n\n Principles, Linear, angular and graphical methods, Survey stations, Survey lines-ranging, Bearing of survey lines, Levelling: Plane table surveying, Principles of levellingbooking and reducing levels; differential, reciprocal leveling, profile levelling and cross sectioning. Digital and Auto Level, Errors in levelling; contouring: Characteristics, methods, uses; areas and volumes. Triangulation and Trilateration (6 Hours): Theodolite survey: Instruments, Measurement of horizontal and vertical angle; Horizontal and vertical control-methods-triangulation network- Signals. Baseline choices instruments and accessories - extension of base lines corrections - Satellite station - reduction to centre - Intervisibility of height and distances - Trigonometric leveling - Axis single corrections.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Curves (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Elements of simple and compound curves - Method of setting out- Elements of Reverse curve - Transition curve length of curve - Elements of transition curve - Vertical curves\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Modern Field Survey Systems (8 Hours):</font></b>\n\n\n Principle of Electronic Distance Measurement, Modulation, Types of EDM instruments, Distomat, Total Station - Parts of a Total Station - Accessories -Advantages and Applications, Field Procedure for total station survey, Errors in Total Station Survey; Global Positioning Systems- Segments, GPS measurements, errors and biases, Surveying with GPS, Co-ordinate transformation, accuracy considerations.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Photogrammetry Surveying (8 Hours): Introduction, Basic concepts, perspective geometry of aerial photograph, relief and tilt displacements, terrestrial photogrammetry, flight planning, Stereoscopy, ground control extension for photographic mapping- aerial triangulation, radial triangulation, methods; photographic mapping- mapping using paper prints, mapping using stereoplotting instruments, mosaics, map substitutes.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Remote Sensing (9 Hours): </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction -Electromagnetic Spectrum, interaction of electromagnetic

radiation with the atmosphere and earth surface, remote sensing data acquisition: platforms and sensors; visual image interpretation; digital image processing.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>


1 Madhu, N, Sathikumar, R and Satheesh Gobi, Advanced Surveying: Total Station, GIS and Remote Sensing, Pearson India, 2006.\n\n\n

2 Manoj, K. Arora and Badjatia, Geomatics Engineering, Nem Chand &amp; Bros, 2011\n\n\n

3 Bhavikatti, S.S., Surveying and Levelling, Vol. I and II, I.K. International, 2010\n\n\n

4 Chandra, A.M., Higher Surveying, Third Edition, New Age International (P) Limited, 2002.\n\n\n

5 Anji Reddy, M., Remote sensing and Geographical information system, B.S. Publications, 2001.\n\n\n

6 Arora, K.R., Surveying, Vol-I, II and III, Standard Book House, 2015.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="cvsem3sub7">Humanities-I(Effective Technical Communication)</string>
<string name="ETCcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Effective Technical Communication

3L:0T:0P 3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n

Information Design and Development- Different kinds of technical documents, Information development life cycle, Organization structures, factors affecting information and document design, Strategies for organization, Information design and writing for print and for online media.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n

Technical Writing, Grammar and Editing- Technical writing process, forms of discourse, Writing drafts and revising, Collaborative writing, creating indexes, technical writing style and language. Basics of grammar, study of advanced grammar, editing strategies to achieve appropriate technical style. Introduction to advanced technical communication, Usability, Hunan factors, Managing technical communication projects, time estimation, Single sourcing, Localization.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n

Self Development and Assessment- Self assessment, Awareness, Perception and Attitudes, Values and belief, Personal goal setting, career planning, Self-esteem. Managing Time; Personal memory, Rapid reading, Taking notes; Complex problem solving; Creativity\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n

Communication and Technical Writing- Public speaking, Group discussion, Oral; presentation, Interviews, Graphic presentation, Presentation aids, Personality Development. Writing reports, project proposals, brochures, newsletters, technical articles, manuals, official notes, business letters, memos, progress reports, minutes of meetings, event report.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n

Ethics- Business ethics, Etiquettes in social and office settings, Email etiquettes, Telephone Etiquettes, Engineering ethics, Managing time, Role and responsibility of engineer, Work culture in jobs, Personal memory, Rapid reading, Taking notes, Complex problem solving, Creativity.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>
    \n\n\n

1. David F. Beer and David McMurrey, Guide to writing as an Engineer, John Willey. New York, 2004\n\n\n

2. Diane Hacker, Pocket Style Manual, Bedford Publication, New York, 2003. (ISBN 0312406843)\n\n\n

3. Shiv Khera, You Can Win, Macmillan Books, New York, 2003.\n\n\n

4. Raman Sharma, Technical Communications, Oxford Publication, London, 2004.\n\n\n

5. Dale Jungk, Applied Writing for Technicians, McGraw Hill, New York, 2004. (ISBN: 07828357-4)\n\n\n

6. Sharma, R. and Mohan, K. Business Correspondence and Report Writing, TMH New Delhi 2002.\n\n\n

7. Xebec, Presentation Book, TMH New Delhi, 2000. (ISBN 0402213)\n\n\n
</string>
    <string name="cvsem3sub8">Introduction To Civil Engineering</string>
<string name="CvCV">\n\n\n


      <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Introduction to Civil Engineering

          2L:1T:0P 2 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

When the students enter the college to pursue a degree in Civil Engineering and as well pursue a career in Civil Engineering after graduation, they need to understand the breadth and depth available in this field for possible engagement. When many alternative disciplines of engineering appear to offer apparently more glamourous avenues for advancement, the Civil Engineering student should realize the solid foundations available in this mother of all engineering disciplines. The students should understand the enormous possibilities available for creative and innovative works in this all pervasive field of engineering.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus</font></b>\n\n\n

What is Civil Engineering/ Infrastructure, History of Civil Engineering, Overview of ancient and modern civil engineering marvels, current national planning for civil engineering/ infrastructure projects, scope of work involved in various branches of Civil Engineering - Architecture and Town planning, Surveying and Geomatics, Structural Engineering, Construction Management, Construction materials, Hydrology and Water Resources Engineering, Hydraulic Engineering, Environmental Engineering and Sustainability, Pavement Engineering and construction, Traffic and Transportation Engineering and Management, Geotechnical Engineering, Ocean Engineering, Building Energy Efficiency, Basics of Contract Management, Professional Ethics, Avenues for entrepreneurial working, Creativity and Innovativeness in Civil Engineering, Modules\n\n\n

1. Basic Understanding: What is Civil Engineering/ Infrastructure? Basics of Engineering and Civil Engineering; Broad disciplines of Civil Engineering; Importance of Civil Engineering, Possible scopes for a career\n\n\n

2. History of Civil engineering: Early constructions and developments over time; Ancient monuments and Modern marvels; Development of various materials of construction and methods of construction; Works of Eminent civil engineers\n\n\n

3. Overview of National Planning for Construction and Infrastructure Development; Position of construction industry vis-à-vis other industries, five year plan outlays for construction; current budgets for infrastructure works;\n\n\n

    4. Fundamentals of Architecture and Town Planning: Aesthetics in Civil Engineering, Examples of great architecture, fundamentals of architectural design and town planning; Building Systems (HVAC, Acoustics, Lighting, etc.); LEED ratings; Development of Smart cities\n\n\n

5. Fundamentals of Building Materials: Stones, bricks, mortars, Plain, Reinforced and Prestressed Concrete, Construction Chemicals; Structural Steel, High Tensile Steel, Carbon Composites; Plastics in Construction; 3D printing; Recycling of Construction and Demolition wastes\n\n\n

6. Basics of Construction Management and Contracts Management: Temporary Structures in Construction; Construction Methods for various types of Structures; Major Construction equipment; Automation and Robotics in Construction; Modern Project management Systems; Advent of Lean Construction; Importance of Contracts Management\n\n\n

7. Environmental Engineering and Sustainability: Water treatment systems; Effluent treatment systems; Solid waste management; Sustainability in Construction;\n\n\n

8. Geotechnical Engineering: Basics of soil mechanics, rock mechanics and geology; various types of foundations; basics of rock mechanics and tunnelling\n\n\n

9. Hydraulics, Hydrology and Water Resources Engineering: Fundamentals of fluid flow, basics of water supply systems; Underground Structures; Underground Structures Multi-purpose reservoir projects\n\n\n

10. Ocean Engineering: Basics of Wave and Current Systems; Sediment transport systems; Ports and Harbours and other marine structures\n\n\n

11. Power Plant Structures: Chimneys, Natural and Induced Draught Colling towers, coal handling systems, ash handling systems; nuclear containment structures; hydro power projects\n\n\n

12. Structural Engineering: Types of buildings; tall structures; various types of bridges; Water retaining structures; Other structural systems; Experimental Stress Analysis; Wind tunnel studies;\n\n\n

13. Surveying and Geomatics: Traditional surveying techniques, Total Stations, Development of Digital Terrain Models; GPS, LIDAR;\n\n\n

 14. Traffic and Transportation Engineering: Investments in transport infrastructure development in India for different modes of transport; Developments and challenges in integrated transport development in India: road, rail, port and harbour and airport sector; PPP in transport sector; Intelligent Transport Systems; Urban Public and Freight Transportation; Road Safety under heterogeneous traffic; Sustainable and resilient pavement materials, design, construction and management; Case studies and examples.\n\n\n

15. Repairs and Rehabilitation of Structures: Basics of corrosion phenomena and other structural distress mechanisms; some simple systems of rehabilitation of structures; Non-Destructive testing systems; Use of carbon fibre wrapping and carbon composites in repairs.\n\n\n

16. Computational Methods, IT, IoT in Civil Engineering: Typical software used in Civil Engineering- Finite Element Method, Computational Fluid Dynamics; Computational Geotechnical Methods; highway design (MX), Building Information Modelling; Highlighting typical available software systems (SAP, STAAD, ABAQUS, MATLAB, ETAB, NASTRAN, NISA, MIKE 21, MODFLOW, REVIT, TEKLA, AUTOCAD,…GEOSTUDIO, EDUSHAKE, MSP, PRIMAVERA, ArcGIS, VisSIM, …)\n\n\n

17. Industrial lectures: Case studies of large civil engineering projects by industry professionals, covering comprehensive planning to commissioning;\n\n\n

18. Basics of Professionalism: Professional Ethics, Entrepreneurial possibilities in Civil Engineering, Possibilities for creative AND innovative working, Technical writing Skills enhancement; Facilities Management; Quality AND HSE Systems in Construction\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>ORGANISATION OF COURSE (2-1-0)</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>S.No Module [No. of Lectures within brackets]~ Tutorials</b>
    \n\n\n

1 Basic Understanding (1) Develop a matrix of various disciplines and possible roles for engineers in each\n\n\n

2 History of Civil engineering (1) Identify 10 ancient monuments and ten modern marvels and list the uniqueness of each\n\n\n

3 Overview of National planning for Construction and Infrastructure Development (1) Develop a Strategic Plan for Civil Engineering works for next ten years based on past investments and identify one typical on-going mega project in each area\n\n\n

 4 Architecture and Town Planning (1) Identify ten best civil engineering projects with high aesthetic appeal with one possible factor for each; List down the possible systems required for a typical Smart City\n\n\n

5 Building Materials (2) Identify three top new materials and their potential in construction; Visit a Concrete Lab and make a report\n\n\n

6 Construction Management, Contracts management (2) Identify 5 typical construction methods and list their advantages/ positive features\n\n\n

7 Environmental Engineering and Sustainability (2) Environmental Engineering and Sustainability: Sustainability principles, Sustainable built environment, water treatment systems, good practices of wastewater management. examples of Solid and hazardous waste management, Air pollution and control\n\n\n

8 Geotechnical Engineering (2) List top five tunnel projects in India and their features; collect and study geotechnical investigation report of any one Metro Rail (underground) project; Visit a construction site and make a site visit report\n\n\n

9 Hydraulics, Hydrology and Water Resources Engineering (1) Identify three river interlinking projects and their features; visit a Hydraulics Lab and make a report\n\n\n

10 Ocean Engineering, Ports and Harbours (1) Identify 5 typical ports in India and list the structures available in them; Visit a related/similar facility, if possible in nearby place and make a report\n\n\n

11 Power Plant Structures (1) Collect the typical layout for a large thermal power plant and a large hydro power plant and identify all the structures and systems falling in them.\n\n\n

12 Structural Engineering (3) Identify 5 unique features for typical buildings, bridges, tall structures and large span structures; Visit Structures Testing Lab/facility and make a report\n\n\n

13 Surveying and Geomatics (1) Collect visual representations prepared by a Total Station and LIDAR and compare; Study typical Google street map and Google Earth Map and study how each can facilitate the other\n\n\n

 14 Traffic and transportation (1) Investments in transport infrastructure; Developments and challenges; Intelligent Transport Systems; Smart Cities, Urban Transport; Road Safety; Sustainable and resilient highway design principles; Plan a sustainable transport system for a city; Identify key features/components in the planning and design of a green field highway/airport/port/railway and the cost - economics.\n\n\n

15 Repairs and rehabilitation of Structures (1) Collect the history of a major rehabilitation project and list the interesting features\n\n\n

16 Computational Methods, IT, IoT in Civil Engineering (2) Visit an AutoCad lab and prepare a report; Identify ten interesting software systems used in Civil Engg and their key features\n\n\n

17 Industrial lectures (2) For each case study list the interesting features\n\n\n

18 Basics of Professionalism (3) List 5 cases of violation of professional ethics and list preventive measures; Identify 5 interesting projects and their positive features; Write 400 word reports on one ancient monument and a modern marvel of civil engineering\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>
    \n\n\n

1. Patil, B.S. (1974), Legal Aspects of Building and Engineering Contract\n\n\n 2. The National Building Code, BIS, (2017)\n\n\n

3. RERA Act, (2017)\n\n\n

4. Meena Rao (2006), Fundamental concepts in Law of Contract, 3rd Edn. Professional Offset\n\n\n

5. Chandiramani, Neelima (2000), The Law of Contract: An Outline, 2nd Edn. Avinash Publications Mumbai\n\n\n

6. Avtarsingh (2002), Law of Contract, Eastern Book Co.\n\n\n

7. Dutt (1994), Indian Contract Act, Eastern Law House\n\n\n

8. Anson W.R.(1979), Law of Contract, Oxford University Press\n\n\n

    9. Kwatra G.K. (2005), The Arbitration and Conciliation of Law in India with case law on UNCITRAL Model Law on Arbitration, Indian Council of Arbitration\n\n\n

10. Avtarsingh (2005), Law of Arbitration and Conciliation, Eastern Book Co.\n\n\n

11. Wadhera (2004), Intellectual Property Rights, Universal Law Publishing Co.\n\n\n

12. P. S. Narayan (2000), Intellectual Property Rights, Gogia Law Agency\n\n\n

13. T. Ramappa (2010), Intellectual Property Rights Law in India, Asia Law House\n\n\n

14. Bare text (2005), Right to Information Act\n\n\n

15. O.P. Malhotra, Law of Industrial Disputes, N.M. Tripathi Publishers\n\n\n

16. K.M. Desai (1946), The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act\n\n\n

17. Rustamji R.F., Introduction to the Law of Industrial Disputes, Asia Publishing House\n\n\n

18. Vee, Charles and Skitmore, Martin (2003) Professional Ethics in the Construction Industry, Engineering Construction and Architectural management, Vol. 10, Iss. 2, pp 117-127, MCB UP Ltd\n\n\n

19. American Society of Civil Engineers (2011) ASCE Code of Ethics - Principles Study and Application\n\n\n

20. Ethics in Engineering- M.W.Martin and R.Schinzinger, McGraw-Hill\n\n\n

21. Engineering Ethics, National Institute for Engineering Ethics, USA\n\n\n

22. www.ieindia.org\n\n\n

23. Engineering ethics: concepts and cases - C. E. Harris, M.S. Pritchard, M.J.Rabins\n\n\n

24. Resisting Bureaucratic Corruption: Alacrity Housing Chennai (Teaching Case Study) -S. Ramakrishna Velamuri -CEIBS\n\n\n

    25. CONSTRUCTION CONTRACTS, http://www.jnormanstark .com/contract.htm\n\n\n

26. Internet and Business Handbook, Chap 4, CONTRACTS LAW,

http://www.laderapress.com/laderapress/contractslaw1

.html\n\n\n 27. Contract and Agreements, http://www.tco.ac.ir/law

/English/agreements/General/Contract%20Law/C.html\n\n\n

28. Contracts, http://206.127.69.152/jgretch/crj/211/ch7.ppt \n\n\n29. Business and Personal Law. Chapter 7. How Contracts

Arise, http://yucaipahigh.com/schristensen/lawweb/lawch7.ppt\n\n\n

30. Types of Contracts, http://cmsu2.cmsu.edu/public /classes/rahm/meiners.con.ppt\n\n\n

31. IV. TYPES OF CONTRACTS AND IMPORTANT PROVISIONS,

http://www.worldbank.org/html/opr/consult/guidetxt/types .html\n\n\n

32. Contract Types/Pricing Arrangements Guideline- 1.4.G (11/04/02), http://www.sandia.gov/policy/14g.pdf\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="cvsem3sub9">Internship</string>
<string name="incv">

</string>


    <string name="cvsem4sub1">Mechanical Engineering</string>
<string name="MEcv">\n\n\n
    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Basic Concepts- Basic concepts - concept of continuum, macroscopic approach, Thermodynamic systems - closed, open and isolated. Property, state, path and process, quasistatic

process, work, modes of work. Zeroth law of thermodynamics, concept of temperature and heat. Concept of ideal and real gases.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n First Law of Thermodynamics- Concepts of Internal Energy, Specific Heat Capacities, Enthalpy. Energy Balance for Closed and Open Systems, Energy Balance for Steady-Flow Systems. Steady-Flow Engineering Devices. Energy Balance for Unsteady- Flow\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: </font></b>\n\n\nSecond Law of Thermodynamics- Thermal energy reservoirs, heat engines energy conversion, Kelvin\'s and Clausius statements of second law, the Carnot cycle, the Carnot Theorem,

the thermodynamic temperature scale, the Carnot heat engine, efficiency, the Carnot refrigerator and heat pump, COP. Clausius inequality, concept of entropy, principle of increase of entropy availability, the increase of entropy principle, perpetual-motion machines, reversible and irreversible processes, Entropy change of pure substances, isentropic processes, property diagrams involving entropy, entropy change of liquids and solids, the entropy change of ideal gases, reversible steady-flow work, minimizing the compressor work, isentropic efficiencies of steady-flow devices, and entropy balance. Energy a measure of work potential, including work potential of energy, reversible work and irreversibility, second-law efficiency, energy change of a system, energy transfer by heat, work, and mass, the decrease of energy principle and energy destruction, energy balance: closed systems and control volumes energy balance.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Properties Of Pure Substance- Properties of pure substances. Thermodynamic

properties of pure substances in solid, liquid and vapour phases. Phase rule, P-V, P-T, T-V, T-S, H-S

diagrams, PVT surfaces. Thermodynamic properties of steam. Calculations of work done and heat

    transfer in non-flow and flow processes.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Power Cycles- Vapour and combined power cycles, including the Carnot vapor cycle,

Rankine cycle: the ideal cycle for vapor power, the ideal reheat and regenerative and the secondlaw

analysis of vapour power cycles. Gas power cycles, including basic considerations in the

analysis of power cycles, the Carnot cycle and its value in engineering, an overview of reciprocating

engines, air standard assumptions, gasoline engine Otto cycle, diesel engine cycle, gas-turbine

Brayton cycle, and the second-law analysis of gas power cycles.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: </font></b>\n\n\nIdeal and Real Gases and Thermodynamic Relations- Gas mixtures - properties ideal and

real gases. Equation of state, Avogadro\'s Law, Vander Waal\'s equation of state, Compressibility

factor, compressibility chart. Dalton\'s law of partial pressure. Exact differentials, T-D relations,

Maxwell\'s relations. Clausius Clapeyron equations, Joule Thomson coefficient.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n Psychrometry and psychrometric charts, property calculations of air vapour mixtures.

Psychrometric process - Sensible heat exchange processes. Latent heat exchange processes.

Adiabatic mixing, evaporative cooling. Use of standard thermodynamic tables, Mollier diagram,

Psychometric chart and Refrigerant property tables. Refrigeration cycles, including refrigerators

and heat pumps, the ideal reversed Carnot vapour-compression refrigeration cycle, actual vaporcompression

    refrigeration cycles, heat pump systems, gas refrigeration cycles, and absorption

refrigeration systems.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Nag. P.K., "Engineering Thermodynamics", Tata McGraw-Hill, New Delhi.\n\n\n

2. Cengel, Thermodynamics - An Engineering Approach Tata McGraw Hill, New

Delhi. Sonntag, R. E., Borgnakke, C., &amp; Wylen, G. J. V. Fundamentals of thermodynamics:

Wiley.\n\n\n

3. Moran, M. J., Shapiro, H. N., Boettner, D. D., &amp; Bailey, M. Fundamentals of Engineering\n\n\n

4. Thermodynamics: John Wiley &amp; Sons.\n\n\n

5. Jones, J. B., &amp; Dugan, R. E. Engineering thermodynamics: Prentice Hall.\n\n\n

6. Potter, M. C., &amp; Somerton, C. W. Schaum\'s Outline of Thermodynamics for

Engineers, McGraw-Hill.\n\n\n</string>

    <string name="cvsem4sub2">Engineering Geology</string>
<string name="EGcv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Engineering Geology 2L:0T:2P 3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

The objective of this Course is to focus on the core activities of engineering geologists - site

characterization and geologic hazard identification and mitigation. Through lectures, labs, and case

study examination student will learn to couple geologic expertise with the engineering properties

of rock and unconsolidated materials in the characterization of geologic sites for civil work projects

and the quantification of processes such as rock slides, soil-slope stability, settlement, and

liquefaction.\n\n\n

Engineering geology is an applied geology discipline that involves the collection, analysis, and

interpretation of geological data and information required for the safe development of civil works.

Engineering geology also includes the assessment and mitigation of geologic hazards such

earthquakes, landslides, flooding, the assessment of timber harvesting impacts; and groundwater

remediation and resource evaluation. Engineering geologists are applied geoscientists with an

awareness of engineering principles and practice-they are not engineers.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\n Introduction-Branches of geology useful to civil engineering, scope of geological studies

in various civil engineering projects.\n\n\n Department dealing with this subject in India and their scope

of work- GSI, Granite Dimension Stone Cell, NIRM.\n\n\n Mineralogy-Mineral, Origin and composition.

 Physical properties of minerals, susceptibility of minerals to alteration, basic of optical mineralogy,

SEM, XRD., Rock forming minerals, megascopic identification of common primary &amp; secondary

minerals.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Petrology-Rock forming processes.\n\n\n Specific gravity of rocks. \n\n\nTernary diagram. Igneous

petrology- Volcanic Phenomenon and different materials ejected by volcanoes.\n\n\n Types of volcanic

eruption. Concept of Hot spring and Geysers. Characteristics of different types of magma. Division

of rock on the basis of depth of formation, and their characteristics. \n\n\nChemical and Mineralogical

Composition. Texture and its types. Various forms of rocks. \n\n\n IUGS Classification of phaneritic and

volcanic rock.. Field Classification chart. Structures.\n\n\n Classification of Igneous rocks on the basis of

Chemical composition. Detailed study of Acidic Igneous rocks like Granite, Rhyolite or Tuff, Felsite,

Pegmatite, Hornfels. Metamorphic Aureole, Kaolinization. Landform as Tors. \n\n\nEngineering aspect to

granite. Basic Igneous rocks Like Gabbro, Dolerite, Basalt. Engineering aspect to Basalt.\n\n\n

Sedimentary petrology- mode of formation, Mineralogical Composition. Texture and its types,

Structures, Gradation of Clastic rocks. Classification of sedimentary rocks and their characteristics.\n\n\n

Detailed study of Conglomerate, Breccia, Sandstone, Mudstone and Shale, Limestone Metamorphic

petrology- Agents and types of metamorphism, metamorphic grades, Mineralogical composition,

structures &amp; textures in metamorphic rocks.\n\n\n Important Distinguishing features of rocks as Rock

 cleavage, Schistosity, Foliation. Classification. Detailed study of Gneiss, Schist, Slate with

engineering consideration.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module3:</font></b>\n\n\n Physical Geology-Weathering. Erosion and Denudation. Factors affecting weathering

and product of weathering. Engineering consideration.\n\n\n Superficial deposits and its geotechnical

importance: Water fall and Gorges, River meandering, Alluvium, Glacial deposits, Laterite

(engineering aspects), Desert Landform, Loess, Residual deposits of Clay with flints, Solifluction

deposits, mudflows, Coastal deposits.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Strength Behavior of Rocks-Stress and Strain in rocks. Concept of Rock Deformation &amp;

Tectonics. Dip and Strike. Outcrop and width of outcrop.\n\n\n Inliers and Outliers. Main types of

discontinuities according to size. Fold-Types and nomenclature, Criteria for their recognition in

field. Faults: Classification, recognition in field, effects on outcrops.\n\n\n Joints &amp; Unconformity; Types,

Stresses responsible, geotechnical importance. Importance of structural elements in engineering

operations.\n\n\n Consequences of failure as land sliding, Earthquake and Subsidence. Strength of

Igneous rock structures.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Geological Hazards- Rock Instability and Slope movement: Concept of sliding blocks.

Different controlling factors. Instability in vertical rock structures and measures to prevent collapse.

Types of landslide.\n\n\n Prevention by surface drainage, slope reinforcement by Rock bolting and Rock

anchoring, retaining wall, Slope treatment. Case study on black clay. Ground water: Factors

 controlling water bearing capacity of rock.\n\n\n Pervious &amp; impervious rocks and ground water.

Lowering of water table and Subsidence. Earthquake: Magnitude and intensity of earthquake.

Seismic sea waves. Revelation from Seismic Records of structure of earth.\n\n\n Case Study on Elevation

and Subsidence in Himalayan region in India. Seismic Zone in India.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: </font></b>\n\n\nRock masses as construction material: Definition of Rock masses, Main features

constituting rock mass. Main features that affects the quality of rock engineering and design.\n\n\n Basic

element and structures of rock those are relevant in civil engineering areas. Main types of works

connected to rocks and rock masses. Important variables influencing rock properties and behavior

such as Fresh rock Influence from some minerals.\n\n\n Effect of alteration and weathering.

Measurement of velocity of sound in rock. Classification of Rock material strength. Core logging

Rock Quality Designation. Rock mass description.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n Geology of dam and reservoir site- Required geological consideration for selecting dam

and reservoir site. Failure of Reservoir.\n\n\n Favorable &amp; unfavorable conditions in different types of

rocks in presence of various structural features, precautions to be taken to counteract unsuitable

conditions, significance of discontinuities on the dam site and treatment giving to such structures.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8:</font></b>\n\n\nRock Mechanics- Sub surface 9nvestigations in rocks and engineering characteristics or

rocks masses; Structural geology of rocks.\n\n\n Classification of rocks, Field &amp; laboratory tests on rocks,

 Stress deformation of rocks, Failure theories and sheer strength of rocks, Bearing capacity of rocks.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practicals:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Study of physical properties of minerals.\n\n\n

2. Study of different group of minerals.\n\n\n

3. Study of Crystal and Crystal system.\n\n\n

4. Identification of minerals: Silica group: Quartz, Amethyst, Opal; Feldspar group: Orthoclase,

Plagioclase; Cryptocrystalline group: Jasper; Carbonate group: Calcite; Element group:

Graphite; Pyroxene group: Talc; Mica group: Muscovite; Amphibole group: Asbestos,

Olivine, Hornblende, Magnetite, Hematite, Corundum, Kyanite, Garnet, Galena, Gypsum.\n\n\n

5. Identification of rocks (Igneous Petrology): Acidic Igneous rock: Granite and its varieties,

Syenite, Rhyolite, Pumice, Obsidian, Scoria, Pegmatite, Volcanic Tuff. Basic rock: Gabbro,

Dolerite, Basalt and its varieties, Trachyte.\n\n\n

6. Identification of rocks (Sedimentary Petrology): Conglomerate, Breccia, Sandstone and its

varieties, Laterite, Limestone and its varieties, Shales and its varieties.\n\n\n

7. Identification of rocks (Metamorphic Petrolody): Marble, slate, Gneiss and its varieties,

Schist and its varieties. Quartzite, Phyllite.\n\n\n

8. Study of topographical features from Geological maps. Identification of symbols in maps.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Engineering and General Geology, Parbin Singh, 8th Edition (2010), S K Kataria &amp; Sons.\n\n\n

    2. Text Book of Engineering Geology, N. Chenna Kesavulu, 2nd Edition (2009), Macmillan

Publishers India.\n\n\n

3. Geology for Geotechnical Engineers, J.C.Harvey, Cambridge University Press (1982).\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem4sub3"> Disaster Preparedness And Planning</string>
<string name="DPPcv">\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Disaster Preparedness &amp; Planning Management

      1L:1T:0P 2 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

The overall aim of this course is to provide broad understanding about the basic concepts of

Disaster Management with preparedness as a Civil Engineer. Further, the course introduces the

various natural hazards that can pose risk to property, lives, and livestock, etc. and understanding

of the social responsibility as an engineer towards preparedness as well as mitigating the damages.\n\n\n

    <b>The objectives of the course are</b>\n\n\n i) To Understand basic concepts in Disaster Management\n\n\n ii) To

Understand Definitions and Terminologies used in Disaster Management \n\n\niii) To

Understand Types and Categories of Disasters\n\n\n iv). To Understand the Challenges posed by Disasters\n\n\n

vi) To understand Impacts of Disasters Key Skills\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction - Concepts and definitions: disaster, hazard, vulnerability, risks- severity,

frequency and details, capacity, impact, prevention, mitigation).\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\nDisasters - Disasters classification; natural disasters (floods, draught, cyclones, volcanoes,

earthquakes, tsunami, landslides, coastal erosion, soil erosion, forest fires etc.); manmade disasters

(industrial pollution, artificial flooding in urban areas, nuclear radiation, chemical spills,

transportation accidents, terrorist strikes, etc.); hazard and vulnerability profile of India, mountain

and coastal areas, ecological fragility.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 3: </font></b>\n\n\n Disaster Impacts - Disaster impacts (environmental, physical, social, ecological,

economic, political, etc.); health, psycho-social issues; demographic aspects (gender, age, special

needs); hazard locations; global and national disaster trends; climate change and urban disasters.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Disaster Risk Reduction (DRR) - Disaster management cycle its phases; prevention,

mitigation, preparedness, relief and recovery; structural and non-structural measures; risk analysis,

vulnerability and capacity assessment; early warning systems, Postdisaster environmental response

(water, sanitation, food safety, waste management, disease control, security, communications);

Roles and responsibilities of government, community, local institutions, NGOs and other

stakeholders; Policies and legislation for disaster risk reduction, DRR programmes in India and the

activities of National Disaster Management Authority.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Disasters, Environment and Development - Factors affecting vulnerability such as impact

of developmental projects and environmental modifications (including of dams, landuse changes,

urbanization etc.), sustainable and environmental friendly recovery; reconstruction and

development methods.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. http://ndma.gov.in/ (Home page of National Disaster Management Authority)\n\n\n

2. http://www.ndmindia.nic.in/ (National Disaster management in India, Ministry of Home

 Affairs).\n\n\n

3. Pradeep Sahni, 2004, Disaster Risk Reduction in South Asia, Prentice Hall.\n\n\n

4. Singh B.K., 2008, Handbook of Disaster Management: Techniques &amp; Guidelines, Rajat

Publication.\n\n\n

5. Ghosh G.K., 2006, Disaster Management, APH Publishing Corporation\n\n\n

6. Disaster Medical Systems Guidelines. Emergency Medical Services Authority, State of


California, EMSA no.214, June 2003\n\n\n

7. Inter Agency Standing Committee (IASC) (Feb. 2007). IASC Guidelines on Mental Health and

Psychosocial Support in Emergency Settings. Geneva: IASC\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem4sub4">Introduction to Fluid Mechanics</string>
<string name="FMcv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>3L:0T:2P 4 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

The objective of this course is to introduce the concepts of fluid mechanics useful in Civil

Engineering applications.\n\n\n The course provides a first level exposure to the students to fluid

statics, kinematics and dynamics.\n\n\n Measurement of pressure, computations of hydrostatic forces

on structural components and the concepts of Buoyancy all find useful applications in many

engineering problems.\n\n\n A training to analyse engineering problems involving fluids such as

those dealing with pipe flow, open channel flow, jets, turbines and pumps, dams and spillways,

culverts, river and groundwater flow - with a mechanistic perspective is essential for the civil

engineering students.\n\n\n The topics included in this course are aimed to prepare a student to build

a good fundamental background useful in the application-intensive courses covering hydraulics,

hydraulic machinery and hydrology in later semesters.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n

Basic Concepts and Definitions - Distinction between a fluid and a solid;

Density, Specific weight, Specific gravity, Kinematic and dynamic viscosity; variation of viscosity

with temperature, Newton law of viscosity, vapour pressure, boiling point, cavitation; surface

tension, capillarity, Bulk modulus of elasticity, compressibility.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n

Fluid Statics - Fluid Pressure: Pressure at a point, Pascals law, pressure variation with

 temperature, density and altitude. Piezometer, U-Tube Manometer, Single Column Manometer,

U-Tube Differential Manometer, Micromanometers. pressure gauges, Hydrostatic pressure

and force: horizontal, vertical and inclined surfaces. Buoyancy and stability of floating bodies.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n

Fluid Kinematics-Classification of fluid flow: steady and unsteady flow; uniform and

non-uniform flow; laminar and turbulent flow; rotational and irrotational flow; compressible

and incompressible flow; ideal and real fluid flow; one, two and three dimensional flows;

Stream line, path line, streak line and stream tube; stream function, velocity potential function.

One-, two- and three-dimensional continuity equations in Cartesian coordinates\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n

Fluid Dynamics-Surface and body forces; Equations of motion - Euler\'s equation;

Bernoulli\'s equation - derivation; Energy Principle; Practical applications of Bernoulli\'s equation

: venturimeter, orifice meter and pitot tube; Momentum principle; Forces exerted by fluid flow

on pipe bend; Vortex Flow - Free and Forced;

Dimensional Analysis and Dynamic Similitude - Definitions of Reynolds Number, Froude

Number, Mach Number, Weber Number and Euler Number; Buck ingham\'s t-Theorem.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n

Laminar Flow-Laminar flow through :circular pipes, annulus and parallel plates. Stoke\'s

law, Measurement of viscosity\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n

Dimensional Analysis and Hydraulic Similitude: Dimensional homogeneity, Rayleigh

method, Buckingham\'s Pi method and other methods. Dimensionless groups. Similitude, Model

studies, Types of models. Application of dimensional analysis and model

Studies to fluid flow problem. Dynamic Similitude-Definitions of ReynoldsNumber, Froude

Number, MachNumber, Weber Number and EulerNumber.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n

Flow through Pipes: Loss of head through pipes, Darcy-Wiesbatch equation, minor

losses, total energy equation, hydraulic gradient line, Pipes in series, equivalent pipes, pipes in

parallel, flow through laterals, flows in dead end pipes, siphon, power transmission through

pipes, nozzles. Analysis of pipe networks: Hardy Cross method, water hammer in pipes and

control measures, branching of pipes, three reservoir problem\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 8:</font></b>\n\n\n

Turbulent Flow- Reynolds experiment, Transition from laminar to turbulent flow.

Definition of turbulence, scale and intensity, Causes of turbulence, instability, mechanism of

turbulence and effect of turbulent flow in pipes. Reynolds stresses, semi-empirical theories of

turbulence, Prandtl\'s mixing length theory, universal velocity distribution equation.

Resistance to flow of fluid in smooth and rough pipes, Moody\'s diagram\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Lab Experiments</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Measurement of viscosity\n\n\n

2. Study of Pressure Measuring Devices\n\n\n

3. Stability of Floating Body\n\n\n

4. Hydrostatics Force on Flat Surfaces/Curved Surfaces\n\n\n

5. Verification of Bernoulli\'s Theorem\n\n\n

6. Venturimeter\n\n\n

7. Orifice meter\n\n\n

8. Impacts of jets\n\n\n

9. Flow Visualisation-Ideal Flow\n\n\n

10. Length of establishment of flow\n\n\n

11. Velocity distribution in pipes\n\n\n

12. Laminar Flow\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Fluid Mechanics and Machinery, C. S. P. Ojha, R. Berndtsson and P. N. Chadramouli, Oxford

University Press, 2010\n\n\n

2. Hydraulics and Fluid Mechanics, PM Modi and S M Seth, Standard Book House\n\n\n

3. Theory and Applications of Fluid Mechanics, K. Subramanya, Tata McGraw Hill\n\n\n

4. Fluid Mechanics with Engineering Applications, R.L. Daugherty, J.B. Franzini and E.J.

Finnemore, International Student Edition, Mc Graw Hill.\n\n\n

</string>
<string name="cvsem4sub5">Introduction To Solid Mechanics</string>
<string name="SMcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 3L:0T:0P 3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

The objective of this Course is to introduce to continuum mechanics and material modelling of

engineering materials based on first energy principles: deformation and strain; momentum

balance, stress and stress states; elasticity and elasticity bounds; plasticity and yield design.\n\n\n The

overarching theme is a unified mechanistic language using thermodynamics, which allows

understanding, modelling and design of a large range of engineering materials.\n\n\n The subject of

mechanics of materials involves analytical methods for determining the strength, stiffness

(deformation characteristics), and stability of the various members in a structural system.\n\n\n The

behaviour of a member depends not only on the fundamental laws that govern the equilibrium of

forces, but also on the mechanical characteristics of the material.\n\n\n These mechanical characteristics

come from the laboratory, where materials are tested under accurately known forces and their

behaviour is carefully observed and measured.\n\n\n For this reason, mechanics of materials is a blended

science of experiment and Newtonian postulates of analytical mechanics.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n

Simple Stresses and Strains- Concept of stress and strain, St. Venant\'s principle, stress

and strain diagram, Elasticity and plasticity Types of stresses and strains, Hooke\'s law - stress -

strain diagram for mild steel - Working stress - Factor of safety - Lateral strain, Poisson\'s ratio and

volumetric strain - Elastic moduli and the relationship between them Bars of varying section -

composite bars - Temperature stresses. Strain Energy - Resilience - Gradual, sudden, impact and

shock loadings simple applications.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n

Compound Stresses and Strains- Two dimensional system, stress at a point on a plane,

principal stresses and principal planes, Mohr circle of stress, ellipse of stress and their applications.

Two dimensional stress-strain system, principal strains and principal axis of strain, circle of strain

and ellipse of strain. Relationship between elastic constants.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n

Bending moment and Shear Force Diagrams- Bending moment (BM) and shear force (SF)

diagrams.BM and SF diagrams for cantilevers simply supported and fixed beams with or without

overhangs. Calculation of maximum BM and SF and the point of contra flexure under concentrated

loads, uniformly distributed loads over the whole span or part of span, combination of

concentrated loads (two or three) and uniformly distributed loads, uniformly varying loads,

    application of moments.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n

Flexural Stresses-Theory of simple bending - Assumptions Derivation of bending

equation: M/I = f/y = E/R-Neutral axis - Determination of bending stresses - Section modulus of

rectangular and circular sections (Solid and Hollow), I,T, Angle and Channel sections - Design of

simple beam sections.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n

Shear Stresses- Derivation of formula - Shear stress distribution across various beam

sections like rectangular, circular, triangular, I, T angle sections.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n

Slope and deflection- Relationship between moment, slope and deflection, Moment area

method, Macaulay\'s method. Use of these methods to calculate slope and deflection for

determinant beams.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n

Torsion- Derivation of torsion equation and its assumptions. Applications of the equation

of the hollow and solid circular shafts, torsional rigidity, Combined torsion and bending of circular

shafts, principal stress and maximum shear stresses under combined loading of bending and

torsion. Analysis of close-coiled-helical springs.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8:</font></b>\n\n\n

Thin Cylinders and Spheres- Derivation of formulae and calculations of hoop stress,

longitudinal stress in a cylinder, and sphere subjected to internal pressures.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>List of Experiments:</font></b>\n\n\n

Tension test\n\n\n

Bending tests on simply supported beam and Cantilever beam.\n\n\n

Compression test on concrete\n\n\n

Impact test\n\n\n

Shear test\n\n\n

Investigation of Hook\'s law that is the proportional relation between force and stretching

in elastic deformation,\n\n\n

Determination of torsion and deflection,\n\n\n

Measurement of forces on supports in statically determinate beam,\n\n\n

Determination of shear forces in beams,\n\n\n

Determination of bending moments in beams,\n\n\n

Measurement of deflections in statically determinate beam,\n\n\n

Measurement of strain in a bar\n\n\n

Bend test steel bar;\n\n\n

Yield/tensile strength of steel bar;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Timoshenko, S. and Young, D. H., "Elements of Strength of Materials", DVNC, New York,

USA.\n\n\n

2. Kazmi, S. M. A., "Solid Mechanics" TMH, Delhi, India.\n\n\n

3. Hibbeler, R. C. Mechanics of Materials. 6th ed. East Rutherford, NJ: Pearson Prentice

Hall, 2004\n\n\n

4. Crandall, S. H., N. C. Dahl, and T. J. Lardner. An Introduction to the Mechanics of Solids.

2nd ed. New York, NY: McGraw Hill, 1979\n\n\n

5. Laboratory Manual of Testing Materials - William Kendrick Hall\n\n\n

6. Mechanics of Materials - Ferdinand P. Beer, E. Russel Jhonston Jr., John T. DEwolf - TMH

2002.\n\n\n
</string>

    <string name="cvsem4sub6">Structural Analysis</string>
<string name="SAcv">\n\n\n
    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 3L:1T:0P 4 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

Analysis of indeterminate structures by force methods, flexibility coefficients, Energy methods:\n\n\n

Principle of minimum potential energy, principle of virtual work, Castigliano\'s theorems, Reciprocal

theorem, unit load method, Influence line and Rolling loads, beam, frames and arches, Muller-

Breslau Principles and its applications to determinate and indeterminate structures.\n\n\n

Analysis of Beams and Frames: Moment Area method, Slope deflection method, Three Moment

Equation, Moments distribution methods, effect of symmetry and ant symmetry, sway correction,

Lateral load analysis: Portal and Cantilever methods, Matrix method of structural analysis,

Displacement/Stiffness methods.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. C.S. Reddy, Basic Structural Analysis, Second Edition, Tata McGraw Hill, 2005.\n\n\n

2. R.C. Hibbeler, Structural Analysis, Pearson Education, 6th edition, 2009.\n\n\n

3. C.K. Wang, Intermediate Structural Analysis, Tata McGraw Hill, 1984.\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem4sub7">Material,Testing and Evaluation</string>
<string name="MTEcv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>1L:1T:2P 3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

The objective of this Course is to deal with an experimental determination and evaluation of

mechanical characteristics and advanced behavior of metallic and non-metallic structural

materials.\n\n\n The course deals with explanation of deformation and fracture behavior of structural

materials.\n\n\n The main goal of this course is to provide students with all information concerning

principle, way of measurement, as well as practical application of mechanical characteristics.\n\n\n

Make measurements of behavior of various materials used in Civil Engineering.\n\n\n

Provide physical observations to complement concepts learnt

Introduce experimental procedures and common measurement instruments, equipment,

devices.\n\n\n

Exposure to a variety of established material testing procedures and techniques

Different methods of evaluation and inferences drawn from observations\n\n\n

The course reviews also the current testing technology and examines force applications

systems, force measurement, strain measurement, important instrument considerations,

equipment for environmental testing, and computers applications for materials testing provide an

introductory treatment of basic skills in material engineering towards\n\n\n (i) selecting material

for the design, and\n\n\n (ii) evaluating the mechanical and structural properties of material, as well as

 the knowledge necessary for a civil engineer.\n\n\n The knowledge acquired lays a good foundation for

analysis and design of various civil engineering structures/ systems in a reliable manner.\n\n\n

    <b>What will I learn?</b>\n\n\n

• Different materials used in civil engineering applications\n\n\n

• Planning an experimental program, selecting the test configuration, selecting the test

specimens and collecting raw data\n\n\n

• Documenting the experimental program including the test procedures, collected data,

method of interpretation and final results\n\n\n

• Operating the laboratory equipment including the electronic instrumentation, the test

apparatus and the data collection system\n\n\n

• Measuring physical properties of common structural and geotechnical construction

materials\n\n\n

• Interpreting the laboratory data including conversion of the measurements into

engineering values and derivation of material properties (strength and stiffness) from the

engineering values\n\n\n

• Observing various modes of failure in compression, tension, and shear\n\n\n

• Observing various types of material behavior under similar loading conditions\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Proposed Syllabus\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Introduction to Engineering Materials covering, Cements, M-Sand, Concrete

(plain, reinforced and steel fibre/ glass fibre-reinforced, light-weight concrete, High

Performance Concrete, Polymer Concrete) Ceramics, and Refractories, Bitumen and asphaltic

materials, Timbers, Glass and Plastics, Structural Steel and other Metals, Paints and

Varnishes, Acoustical material and geo-textiles, rubber and asbestos, laminates and

adhesives, Graphene, Carbon composites and other engineering materials including

properties and uses of these\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction to Material Testing covering, What is the "Material Engineering"?;

Mechanical behavior and mechanical characteristics; Elasticity - principle and

characteristics; Plastic deformation of metals; Tensile test - standards for different material

(brittle, quasi-brittle, elastic and so on) True stress - strain interpretation of tensile test;

hardness tests; Bending and torsion test; strength of ceramic; Internal friction, creep

fundaments and characteristics; Brittle fracture of steel - temperature transition approach;

Background of fracture mechanics; Discussion of fracture toughness testing different materials;

concept of fatigue of materials; Structural integrity assessment procedure and fracture

mechanics\n\n\n
    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: </font></b>\n\n\nStandard Testing &amp; Evaluation Procedures covering, Laboratory for mechanical

testing, Discussion about mechanical testing; Naming systems

for various irons, steels and

nonferrous metals; Discussion about elastic deformation; Plastic deformation; Impact test and

transition temperatures; Fracture mechanics - background; Fracture toughness - different

materials; Fatigue of material; Creep.\n\n\n

Tutorials from the above modules covering, understanding \n\n\ni) Tests &amp; testing of bricks, ii) Tests

&amp; testing of sand, \n\n\niii) Tests &amp; testing of concrete, \n\n\niv) Tests &amp; testing of soils, v) Tests &amp; testing of

bitumen &amp; bituminous mixes,\n\n\n vi) Tests &amp; testing of polymers and polymer based materials,\n\n\n vii)

Tests &amp; testing of metals &amp; \n\n\n viii) Tests &amp; testing of other special materials, composites and

cementitious materials.\n\n\n  Explanation of mechanical behavior of these materials.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practicals:\n\n\n</font></b>

Gradation of coarse and fine aggregates\n\n\n

Different corresponding tests and need/application of these tests in design and quality

control\n\n\n

Tensile Strength of materials &amp; concrete composites\n\n\n

Compressive strength test on aggregates\n\n\n

Tension I- Elastic Behaviour of metals &amp; materials\n\n\n

Tension II - Failure of Common Materials\n\n\n

Concrete I- Early Age Properties\n\n\n

Concrete II - Compression and Indirect Tension

    Compression - Directionality\n\n\n

Consolidation and Strength Tests\n\n\n

Tension III - Heat Treatment

Torsion test\n\n\n

Hardness tests (Brinnel\'s and Rockwell)\n\n\n

Tests on closely coiled and open coiled springs\n\n\n

Theories of Failure and Corroboration with Experiments\n\n\n

Concrete Mix Design as per BIS\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Chudley, R., Greeno (2006), "Building Construction Handbook" (6th ed.), R. Butterworth-

Heinemann\n\n\n

2. Khanna, S.K., Justo, C.E.G and Veeraragavan, A,  "Highway Materials and Pavement

Testing", Nem Chand&amp; Bros, Fifth Edition\n\n\n

3. Various related updated &amp; recent standards of BIS, IRC, ASTM, RILEM, AASHTO, etc.

corresponding to materialsused for Civil Engineering applications\n\n\n

4. Kyriakos Komvopoulos (2011), Mechanical Testing of Engineering Materials, Cognella\n\n\n

5. E.N. Dowling (1993), Mechanical Behaviour of Materials, Prentice Hall International

Edition\n\n\n

6. American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM), Annual Book of ASTM Standards

(post 2000)\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="cvsem4sub8">Civil ENGINEERING-Societal and Global Impact</string>
<string name="SGIcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>2L:0T:0P 2 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

The course is designed to provide a better understanding of the impact which Civil Engineering has

on the Society at large and on the global arena. \n\n\nCivil Engineering projects have an impact on the

Infrastructure, Energy consumption and generation, Sustainability of the Environment, Aesthetics

of the environment, Employment creation, Contribution to the GDP, and on a more perceptible

level, the Quality of Life.\n\n\n It is important for the civil engineers to realise the impact which this field

has and take appropriate precautions to ensure that the impact is not adverse but beneficial.\n\n\n

    <b>The course covers:</b>\n\n\n

Awareness of the importance of Civil Engineering and the impact it has on the Society and

at global levels\n\n\n

Awareness of the impact of Civil Engineering for the various specific fields of human

endeavour\n\n\n

Need to think innovatively to ensure Sustainability\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction to Course and Overview; Understanding the past to look into the future:

Pre-industrial revolution days, Agricultural revolution, first and second industrial revolutions, IT

revolution, Recent major Civil Engineering breakthroughs and innovations; Present day world and

future projections, Ecosystems in Society and in Nature; the steady erosion in Sustainability; Global

warming, its impact and possible causes; Evaluating future requirements for various resources; GIS

 and applications for monitoring systems; Human Development

    Index and Ecological Footprint of

India Vs other countries and analysis;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Understanding the importance of Civil Engineering in shaping and impacting the world;

The ancient and modern Marvels and Wonders in the field of Civil Engineering; Future Vision for

Civil Engineering\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Infrastructure - Habitats, Megacities, Smart Cities, futuristic visions; Transportation

(Roads, Railways &amp; Metros, Airports, Seaports, River ways, Sea canals, Tunnels (below ground,

under water); Futuristic systems (ex, Hyper Loop)); Energy generation (Hydro, Solar (Photovoltaic,

Solar Chimney), Wind, Wave, Tidal, Geothermal, Thermal energy); Water provisioning;

Telecommunication needs (towers, above-ground and underground cabling); Awareness of various

Codes &amp; Standards governing Infrastructure development; Innovations and methodologies for

ensuring Sustainability;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Environment-Traditional &amp; futuristic methods; Solid waste management, Water

purification, Wastewater treatment &amp; Recycling, Hazardous waste treatment; Flood control (Dams,

Canals, River interlinking), Multi-purpose water projects, Atmospheric pollution; Global warming

phenomena and Pollution Mitigation measures, Stationarity and nonstationarity; Environmental

Metrics &amp; Monitoring; Other Sustainability measures; Innovations and methodologies for ensuring

Sustainability.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: </font></b>\n\n\nBuilt environment - Facilities management, Climate control; Energy efficient built

environments and LEED ratings, Recycling, Temperature/ Sound control in built environment,

Security systems; Intelligent/ Smart Buildings; Aesthetics of built environment, Role of Urban Arts

Commissions; Conservation, Repairs &amp; Rehabilitation of Structures &amp; Heritage structures;

Innovations and methodologies for ensuring Sustainability\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Civil Engineering Projects - Environmental Impact Analysis procedures; Waste

(materials, manpower, equipment) avoidance/ Efficiency increase; Advanced construction

techniques for better sustainability; Techniques for reduction of Green House Gas emissions in

various aspects of Civil Engineering Projects; New Project Management paradigms &amp; Systems (Ex.

Lean Construction), contribution of Civil Engineering to GDP, Contribution to employment(projects,

facilities management), Quality of products, Health &amp; Safety aspects for stakeholders, Innovations

and methodologies for ensuring Sustainability during Project development;\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7A:</font></b>\n\n\n Population Dynamics covering, Population ecology-Population characteristics,

ecotypes; Population genetics- Concept of gene pool and genetic diversity in populations,

    polymorphism and heterogeneity, (3 Lectures)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8B:</font></b>\n\n\n Environmental Management covering, Principles: Perspectives, concerns and

management strategies; Policies and legal aspects- Environment Protection Acts and modification,

 International Treaties; Environmental Impact Assessment- Case studies

(International Airport, thermal power plant); (3 Lectures)\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 9A: Molecular Genetics covering, Structures of DNA and RNA; Concept of Gene, Gene

    regulation, e.g., Operon concept; (3 Lectures)</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 9B:</font></b>\n\n\n Biotechnology covering, Basic concepts: Totipotency and Cell manipulation; Plant &amp;

Animal tissue culture- Methods and uses in agriculture, medicine and health; Recombinant DNA

Technology- Techniques and applications; (3 Lectures)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 10A: </font></b>\n\n\nBiostatistics covering, Introduction to Biostatistics:-Terms used, types of data;

Measures of Central Tendencies- Mean, Median, Mode, Normal and Skewed distributions; Analysis

of Data- Hypothesis testing and ANNOVA (single factor) (4 Lectures)\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>ORGANISATION OF COURSE (2-0-0)

        S. No. Module No of Lectures Details</font>
</b>\n\n\n

1 Introduction 3 \n\n\n

2 Understanding the Importance of Civil

Engineering 3\n\n\n

3 Infrastructure 8\n\n\n

4 Environment 7\n\n\n

5 Built Environment 5\n\n\n

6 Civil Engineering Projects 4\n\n\n

TOTAL 30\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Žiga Turk (2014), Global Challenges and the Role of Civil Engineering, Chapter 3 in:

Fischinger M. (eds) Performance-Based Seismic Engineering: Vision for an

Earthquake Resilient Society. Geotechnical, Geological and Earthquake Engineering, Vol.

32. Springer, Dordrecht\n\n\n

2. Brito, Ciampi, Vasconcelos, Amarol, Barros (2013) Engineering impacting Social,

Economical and Working Environment, 120th ASEE Annual Conference and Exposition\n\n\n

3. NAE Grand Challenges for Engineering (2006), Engineering for the Developing World, The

Bridge, Vol 34, No.2, Summer 2004.\n\n\n

4. Allen M. (2008) Cleansing the city. Ohio University Press.

Athens Ohio.\n\n\n

5. Ashley R., Stovin V., Moore S., Hurley L., Lewis L., Saul A. (2010). London Tideway Tunnels

Programme - Thames Tunnel Project Needs Report Potential source control and SUDS

applications: Land use and retrofit options\n\n\n

6. http://www.thamestunnelconsultation.co.uk/consultation -documents.aspx\n\n\n

7. Ashley R M., Nowell R., Gersonius B., Walker L. (2011). Surface Water Management and

Urban Green Infrastructure. Review of Current Knowledge. Foundation for Water Research

FR/R0014\n\n\n

8. Barry M. (2003) Corporate social responsibility - unworkable paradox or sustainable

paradigm? Proc ICE Engineering Sustainability 156. Sept Issue ES3 paper 13550. p 129-130\n\n\n

 9. Blackmore J M., Plant RAJ. (2008). Risk and resilience to enhance sustainability with

application to urban water systems. J. Water Resources Planning and Management. ASCE.

Vol. 134, No. 3, May.\n\n\n

10. Bogle D. (2010) UK\'s engineering Council guidance on sustainability. Proc ICE Engineering

Sustainability 163. June Issue ES2 p61-63\n\n\n

11. Brown R R., Ashley R M., Farrelly M. (2011). Political and Professional Agency Entrapment:

An Agenda for Urban Water Research. Water Resources Management.

Vol. 23, No.4. European Water Resources Association (EWRA) ISSN 0920-4741.\n\n\n

12. Brugnach M., Dewulf A., Pahl-Wosti C., Taillieu T. (2008) Toward a relational concept of

uncertainty: about knowing too little, knowing too differently and accepting not to know.

Ecology and Society 13 (2): 30\n\n\n

13. Butler D., Davies J. (2011). Urban Drainage. Spon. 3rd Ed.\n\n\n

14. Cavill S., Sohail M. (2003) Accountability in the provision of urban services. Proc. ICE.

Municipal Engineer 156. Issue ME4 paper 13445, p235-244.\n\n\n

15. Centre for Water Sensitive Cities (2012) Blueprint for a water sensitive city. Monash

University.\n\n\n

16. Charles J A. (2009) Robert Rawlinson and the UK public health revolution. Proc ICE Eng

History and Heritage. 162 Nov. Issue EH4. p 199-206\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem4sub9">Managemeny I(Organizational Behavior</string>
<string name="OBcv">

</string>

    <string name="cvsem4sub10">Open Elective-I(Humanities MOOC)</string>
    <string name="OEHcv">

</string>


<string name="cvsem5sub1">Mechanics of Materials</string>
<string name="MOMcv">\n\n\n


    The objective of this Course is to introduce to continuum mechanics and material modeling of engineering materials based on first energy principles: deformation and strain; momentum balance, stress and stress states; elasticity and elasticity bounds; plasticity and yield design. The overarching theme is a unified mechanistic language using thermodynamics, which allows understanding, modelling and design of a large range of engineering materials. The subject of mechanics of materials involves analytical methods for determining the strength, stiffness (deformation characteristics), and stability of the various members in a structural system. The behavior of a member depends not only on the fundamental laws that govern the equilibrium of forces, but also on the mechanical characteristics of the material. These mechanical characteristics come from the laboratory, where materials are tested under accurately known forces and their behavior is carefully observed and measured (learnt in the previous course on Materials, Testing &amp; Evaluation). For this reason, mechanics of materials is a blended science of experiment and Newtonian postulates of analytical mechanics.\n\n\n

    <b>What will I learn?</b>\n\n\n

• Understand the deformation and strains under different load action and response in terms of forces and moments\n\n\n

• Understand the behaviour under different loading actions\n\n\n

• Application of engineering principles to calculate the reactions, forces and moments\n\n\n

• Understand the energy methods used to derive the equations to solve engineering problems\n\n\n

• Make use of the capabilities to determine the forces and moments for design\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Proposed Syllabus\n\n\n</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\nDeformation and Strain covering description of finite deformation, Infinitesimal deformation; Analysis of statically determinate trusses; Stability of dams, retaining walls and chimneys; Stress analysis of thin, thick and compound cylinder;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Generalized state of stress and strain: Stress and strain tensor, Yield criteria and theories of failure; Tresca, Von-Mises, Hill criteria, Heigh-Westerguard\'s stress space.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: </font></b>\n\n\nMomentum Balance and Stresses covering Forces and Moments Transmitted by Slender Members, Shear Force and Bending Moment Diagrams, Momentum Balance, Stress

 States/Failure Criterion\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Mechanics of Deformable Bodies covering Force-deformation Relationships and Static Indeterminacy, Uniaxial Loading and Material Properties, Trusses and Their Deformations, Statically Determinate and Indeterminate Trusses,\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Force-Stress-Equilibrium covering Multiaxial Stress and Strain\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Displacement - Strain covering Multiaxial Strain and Multiaxial Stress-strain Relationships\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n Elasticity and Elasticity Bounds covering Stress-strain-temperature Relationships and Thin-walled Pressure Vessels, Stress and strain Transformations and Principal Stress, Failure of Materials,\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8:Bending:</font></b>\n\n\n Stress and Strains; Deflections and Torsion

covering Pure Bending, Moment-curvature Relationship, Beam Deflection, Symmetry, Superposition, and Statically Indeterminate Beams, Shear and Torsion, Torsion and Twisting, Thermoelasticity, Energy methods, Variational Methods; Strain energy, elastic, complementary and total strain energy, Strain energy of axially loaded bar, Beam in bending, shear and torsion; General energy theorems, Castigliano\'s theorem, Maxwell Bettie\'s reciprocal theorem; Virtual work and unit load method for deflection, Application to problems of beams and frames.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 9:</font></b>Structural stability; Stability of columns, Euler\'s formula, end conditions and effective length factor, Columns with eccentric and lateral load; Plasticity and Yield Design covering 1D-Plasticity - An Energy Approach, Plasticity Models, Limit Analysis and Yield Design\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Norris, C.H. and Wilber, J. B. and Utku, S. "Elementary Structural Analysis" Mc Graw Hill, Tokyo, Japan.\n\n\n

2. Timoshenko, S. and Young, D. H., "Elements of Strength of Materials", DVNC, New York, USA.\n\n\n

3. Kazmi, S. M. A., "Solid Mechanics" TMH, Delhi, India.\n\n\n

4. Hibbeler, R. C. Mechanics of Materials. 6th ed. East Rutherford, NJ: Pearson Prentice Hall, 2004\n\n\n

 5. Crandall, S. H., N. C. Dahl, and T. J. Lardner. An Introduction to the Mechanics of Solids. 2nd ed. New York, NY: McGraw Hill, 1979\n\n\n

6. Gere, J. M., and S. P. Timoshenko. Mechanics of Materials. 5th ed. Boston: PWS Kent Publishing, 1970.\n\n\n

7. Ashby, M. F., and D. R. H. Jones. Engineering Materials, An Introduction to their Properties and Applications. 2nd ed. Butterworth Heinemann.\n\n\n

8. Collins, J. A. Failure of Materials in Mechanical Design. 2nd ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1993.\n\n\n

9. Courtney, T. H. Mechanical Behavior of Materials. McGraw-Hill, 1990.\n\n\n

10. Hertzberg, R. W. Deformation and Fracture Mechanics of Engineering Materials, 4th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1996.\n\n\n

11. Nash, W. A. Strength of Materials. 3d ed. Schaum\'s Outline Series, McGraw-Hill, 1994.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="cvsem5sub2">Hydraulic Engineering</string>
<string name="HEcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Objectives:</font></b>\n\n\n

To introduce the students to various hydraulic engineering problems like open channel flows and hydraulic machines. At the completion of the course, the student should be able to relate

the theory and practice of problems in hydraulic engineering\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\nBoundary Layer Analysis-Assumption and concept of boundary layer theory. Boundary-layer thickness, displacement, momentum &amp; energy thickness, laminar and Turbulent boundary layers on a flat plate; Laminar sub-layer, smooth and rough boundaries. Local and average friction coefficients. Separation and Control.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction to Open Channel Flow-Comparison between open channel flow and pipe flow, geometrical parameters of a channel, classification of open channels, classification of open channel flow, Velocity Distribution of channel section.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Uniform Flow-Continuity Equation, Energy Equation and Momentum Equation, Characteristics of uniform flow, Chezy\'s formula, Manning\'s formula. Factors affecting Manning\'s Roughness Coefficient "n.Most economical section of channel. Computation of Uniform flow, Normal depth.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Non-Uniform Flow- Specific energy, Specific energy curve, critical flow, discharge curve Specific force Specific depth, and Critical depth. Channel Transitions. Measurement of Discharge and Velocity - Venturi Flume, Standing Wave Flume, Parshall Flume, Broad Crested Weir. Measurement of Velocity- Current meter, Floats, Hot-wire anemometer. Gradually Varied Flow-Dynamic Equation of Gradually Varied Flow, Classification of channel bottom slopes, Classification of surface profile, Characteristics of surface profile. Computation of water surface profile by graphical, numerical and analytical approaches. Direct Step method, Graphical Integration method and Direct integration method.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\nHydraulic Jump- Theory of hydraulic jump, Elements and characteristics of hydraulic jump in a rectangular Channel, length and height of jump, location of jump, Types, applications and location of hydraulic jump. Energy dissipation and other uses, surge as a moving hydraulic jump. Positive and negative surges.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Computational Fluid Dynamics: Basic equations of fluid dynamics, Grid generation, Introduction to in viscid incompressible flow, Boundary layer flow as applicable to

 C.F.D. Hydro informatics: Concept of hydro informatics -scope of internet and web based modeling in water resources engineering.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practical Work:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Flow Visualization\n\n\n

2. Studies in Wind Tunnel\n\n\n

3. Boundary Layer\n\n\n

4. Flow around an Aerofoil / circular cylinder\n\n\n

5. Uniform Flow\n\n\n

6. Velocity Distribution in Open channel flow\n\n\n

7. Venturi Flume\n\n\n

8. Standing Wave Flume\n\n\n

9. Gradually Varied Flow\n\n\n

10. Hydraulic Jump\n\n\n

11. Flow under Sluice Gate\n\n\n

12. Flow through pipes\n\n\n

13. Turbulent flow through pipes\n\n\n

14. Flow visualization\n\n\n

15. Laminar flow through pipes\n\n\n

16. Major losses/ Minor losses in pipe\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Hydraulics and Fluid Mechanics, P.M. Modi and S.M. Seth, Standard Book House\n\n\n

2. Theory and Applications of Fluid Mechanics, K. Subramanya, Tata McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

3. Open channel Flow, K. Subramanya, Tata McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

4. Open Channel Hydraulics, Ven Te Chow, Tata McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

 5. Burnside, C.D., " Electromagnetic Distance Measurement," Beekman Publishers, 1971.\n\n\n
</string>

    <string name="cvsem5sub3">Analysis and Design Of Concrete Structure</string>
<string name="ADCScv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Objectives:</font></b>\n\n\n

This course aims at providing students with a solid background on principles of structural engineering design. Students will be exposed to the theories and concepts of both concrete and steel design and analysis both at the element and system levels. Hands-on design experience and skills will be gained and learned through problem sets and a comprehensive design project. An understanding of real-world open-ended design issues will be developed. Weekly recitations and project discussions will be held besides lectures.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction- concepts of energy principles, safety,

sustainable development in performance; what makes a structure; principles of stability, equilibrium; what is a structural engineer, role of engineer, architect, user, builder, what are the functions\' what do the engineers design, first principles of process of design\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Introduction to reinforced concrete structures, Basic material properties: stress-strain relation of concrete and reinforcing steel\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:,</font></b>\n\n\n Planning and Design Process; Materials, Loads, and Design Safety; Behaviour and Properties of Concrete and Steel; Wind and Earthquake Loads Design philosophy: assumptions and code of practice,\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: </font></b>\n\n\nTheory of singly reinforced members in bending, Design of simply supported and continuous beams with rectangular and flanged section,\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Limit state of collapse in shear, Design for bond, Design of one-way and two-way slab systems\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>odule 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Design of columns under uniaxial and biaxial bending, Design of footings and staircase\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Nilson, A. H. Design of Concrete Structures. 13th edition. McGraw Hill, 2004\n\n\n

2. McCormac, J.C., Nelson, J.K. Jr., Structural Steel Design. 3rd edition. Prentice Hall, N.J., 2003.\n\n\n

3. Galambos, T.V., Lin, F.J., Johnston, B.G., Basic Steel Design with LRFD, Prentice Hall, 1996\n\n\n

 4. Segui, W. T., LRFD Steel Design, 2nd Ed., PWS Publishing, Boston.\n\n\n

5. Salmon, C.G. and Johnson, J.E., Steel Structures: Design and Behavior, 3rd Edition, Harper &amp; Row, Publishers, New York, 1990.\n\n\n

6. MacGregor, J. G., Reinforced Concrete: Mechanics and Design, 3rd Edition, Prentice Hall, New Jersey, 1997.\n\n\n
7. Nawy, E. G., Reinforced Concrete: A Fundamental Approach, 5th Edition, Prentice Hall, New Jersey.\n\n\n

8. Wang C-K. and Salmon, C. G., Reinforced Concrete Design, 6th Edition, Addison Wesley, New York.\n\n\n

9. Nawy, E. G. Prestressed Concrete: A Fundamental Approach, Prentice Hall, NJ, (2003).\n\n\n

10. Related Codes of Practice of BIS\n\n\n

11. Smith, J. C., Structural Analysis, Harpor and Row, Publishers, New York.\n\n\n

12. W. McGuire, R. H. Gallagher and R. D. Ziemian. "Matrix Structural Analysis", 2nd Edition, John Wiley and Sons, 2000.\n\n\n

13. NBC, National Building Code, BIS (2017).\n\n\n

14. ASCE, Minimum Design Loads for Buildings and Other Structures, ASCE 7-02, American Society of Civil Engineers, Virginia, 2002.\n\n\n

15. S. U. Pillai and D. Menon, Reinforced Concrete Design, Tata McGraw-Hill, 3rd edition, 2009.\n\n\n

16. P. C. Varghese, Limit State Design of Reinforced Concrete, Prentice Hall India, 2nd edition, 2008\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem5sub4">Geotechnical Engineering-I</string>
<string name="GEcv">
    \n\n\n <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction-Types of soils, their formation and

deposition, Definitions: soil mechanics, soil engineering, rock mechanics, geotechnical engineering. Scope of soil engineering. Comparison and difference between soil and rock. Basic Definitions and Relationships-Soil as three-phase system in terms of weight, volume, voids ratio, and porosity. Definitions: moisture content, unit weights, degree of saturation, voids ratio, porosity, specific gravity, mass specific gravity, etc. Relationship between volume weight, voids ratio- moisture content, unit weight- percent air voids, saturation- moisture content, moisture content-specific gravity etc. Determination of various parameters such as: Moisture content by oven dry method, pycnometer, sand bath method, torsional balance method, nuclear method, alcohol method and sensors. Specific gravity by density bottle method, pycnometer method, measuring flask method. Unit weight by water displacement method, submerged weight method, core-cutter method, sand-replacement method.\n\n\n

    <b>On completion of this module, the students must be able to:\n\n\n</b>

• Understand the different types of soil based on their formation mechanism;\n\n\n

• Understand the various phase diagrams and derive various phase relationships of the soil; Perform various laboratory experiments to determine moisture content, specific gravity; Perform field experiments to estimate the field density of the soil mass.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: </font></b>\n\n\nPlasticity Characteristics of Soil - Introduction to definitions of: plasticity of soil, consistency limits-liquid limit, plastic limit, shrinkage limit, plasticity, liquidity and consistency indices, flow &amp; toughness indices, definitions of activity and sensitivity. Determination of: liquid limit, plastic limit and shrinkage limit. Use of consistency limits. Classification of Soils-Introduction of soil classification: particle size classification, textural classification, unified soil classification system, Indian standard soil classification system.

Identification: field identification of soils, general characteristics of soil in different groups.\n\n\n

    <b>On completion of this module, the students must be able to:</b>\n\n\n

• Understand the behaviour of soils based on their moisture contents;\n\n\n

• Perform laboratory experiments to estimate various Atterberg limits and evaluate index properties of soils;\n\n\n

 • Classify any soils based on their particle size distribution and index properties;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Permeability of Soil - Darcy\'s law, validity of Darcy\'s law. Determination of coefficient of permeability: Laboratory method: constant-head method, falling-head method. Field method: pumping- in test, pumping-out test. Permeability aspects: permeability of stratified soils, factors affecting permeability of soil. Seepage Analysis- Introduction, stream and potential functions, characteristics of flow nets, graphical method to plot flow nets.

    <b>On completion of this module, the student must be able to:\n\n\n</b>

• Determine the permeability of soils through various laboratory and field tests;\n\n\n

• Analytically calculate the effective permeability of anisotropic soil mass;\n\n\n

• Determine the seepage quantities and pore water pressures below the ground;\n\n\n

• Graphically plot the equipotential lines and flow lines in a seepage flow.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Effective Stress Principle - Introduction, effective stress principle, nature of effective stress, effect of water table. Fluctuations of effective stress, effective stress in soils saturated by capillary action, seepage pressure, quick sand condition.\n\n\n

    <b>On completion of this module, the student must be able to:\n\n\n</b>

• Understand the physical significance of effective stress and its relation with pore pressure;\n\n\n

• Plot various stress distribution diagrams along the depth of the soil mass;\n\n\n

• Understand the effect of capillary action and seepage flow direction on the effective stress at a point in the soil mass.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Compaction of Soil-Introduction, theory of compaction, laboratory determination of optimum moisture content and maximum dry density. Compaction in field, compaction specifications and field control.\n\n\n

    <b>On completion of this module, the student must be able to:</b>\n\n\n

• Perform laboratory test to determine the maximum dry

 density and optimum moisture content of the soil;\n\n\n

• Variation in compaction curve with compaction effort and soil type;\n\n\n

• Determine the compactive effort required to obtain necessary degree of compaction in-situ;\n\n\n

•Differentiate among various field methods of compaction and their usage based on the type of soil.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Stresses in soils - Introduction, stresses due to point load, line load, strip load, uniformly loaded circular area, rectangular loaded area. Influence factors, Isobars, Boussinesq\'s equation, Newmark\'s Influence Chart. Contact pressure under rigid and flexible area, computation of displacements from elastic theory. On completion of this module, the student must be able to:\n\n\n

• Analytically compute the vertical stress in a semi-infinite soil mass due to various loading conditions; Plot isobars due various loading conditions.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practical Work: List of tests on-</font></b>
    \n\n\n

1. Field Density using Core Cutter method.\n\n\n

2. Field Density using Sand replacement method.\n\n\n

3. Natural moisture content using Oven Drying method.\n\n\n

4. Field identification of Fine Grained soils.\n\n\n

5. Specific gravity of Soils.\n\n\n

6. Grain size distribution by Sieve Analysis.\n\n\n

7. Grain size distribution by Hydrometer Analysis.\n\n\n

8. Consistency limits by Liquid limit\n\n\n

9. Consistency limits by Plastic limit\n\n\n

10. Consistency limits by Shrinkage limit.\n\n\n

11. Permeability test using Constant-head test method.\n\n\n

12. Permeability test using Falling-head method.\n\n\n

13. Compaction test: Standard Proctor test.\n\n\n

 14. Compaction test: Modified Proctor test.\n\n\n

15. Relative density.\n\n\n

16. Consolidation Test.\n\n\n

17. Triaxial Test (UU)\n\n\n

18. Vane shear test\n\n\n

19. Direct Shear Test\n\n\n

20. Unconfined Compression Strength Test.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Soil Mechanics by Craig R.F., Chapman &amp; Hall\n\n\n

2. Fundamentals of Soil Engineering by Taylor, John Wiley &amp; Sons\n\n\n

3. An Introduction to Geotechnical Engineering, by Holtz R.D. and Kovacs, W.D., Prentice Hall, NJ\n\n\n

4. Principles of Geotechnical Engineering, by Braja M. Das, Cengage Learning\n\n\n

5. Principles of Foundation Engineering, by Braja M. Das, Cengage Learning\n\n\n

6. Essentials of Soil Mechanics and Foundations: Basic Geotechnics by David F. McCarthy\n\n\n

7. Soil Mechanics in Engineering Practice by Karl Terzaghi, Ralph B. Peck, and Gholamreza Mesri.\n\n\n

8. Geotechnical Engineering: Principles and Practices of Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering (Civil and Environmental Engineering) by V.N.S. Murthy\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem5sub5">Hydrology and Water Resourcse Engineering</string>
<string name="HWREcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction - hydrologic cycle, water-budget equation, history of hydrology, world water balance, applications in engineering, sources of data.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Precipitation - forms of precipitation, characteristics

of precipitation in India, measurement of precipitation, rain gauge uge network, mean precipitation over an area, deptharea-duration relationships, maximum intensity/ depth-duration-frequency relationship, Probable Maximum Precipitation (PMP), rainfall data in India.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Abstractions from precipitation - evaporation

process, evaporimeters, analytical methods of evaporation estimation, reservoir evaporation and methods for its reduction, evapotranspiration, measurement of evapotranspiration, evapotranspiration equations, potential evapotranspiration over India, actual evapotranspiration, interception, depression storage, infiltration, infiltration capacity, measurement of infiltration, modelling infiltration capacity, classification of infiltration capacities, infiltration indices.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\nRunoff runoff volume, SCS-CN method of estimating runoff volume, flowduration curve, flow-mass curve, hydrograph, factors affecting runoff hydrograph, components of hydrograph, base flow separation, effective rainfall, unit hydrograph surface water resources of India, environmental flows.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Ground water and well hydrology - forms of subsurface water, saturated formation, aquifer properties, geologic formations of aquifers, well hydraulics: steady state flow in wells, equilibrium equations for confined and unconfined aquifers, aquifer tests.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: </font></b>\n\n\nWater withdrawals and uses water for energy

production, water for agriculture, water for hydroelectric generation; flood control. Analysis of surface water supply, Water requirement of crops-Crops and crop seasons in India, cropping pattern, duty and delta; Quality of irrigation water; Soil-water relationships, root zone soil water, infiltration, consumptive use, irrigation requirement, frequency of irrigation; Methods of applying water to the fields: surface, sub-surface, sprinkler and trickle / drip irrigation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n Distribution systems canal systems, alignment of canals, canal losses, estimation of design discharge. Design of channels-rigid boundary channels, alluvial channels, Kennedy\'s and Lacey\'s theory of regime channels. Canal outlets: non-modular, semi-modular and modular outlets. Water logging: causes, effects and remedial measures. Lining of canals, types of lining. Drainage of irrigated lands: necessity, methods.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8:</font></b>\n\n\n Dams and spillways - embankment dams: Classification, design considerations, estimation and control of seepage, slope protection. Gravity dams: forces on gravity dams, causes of failure, stress analysis, elementary and practical profile. Arch and buttress dams. Spillways: components of spillways, types of gates for spillway crests; Reservoirs- Types, capacity of reservoirs, yield of reservoir, reservoir regulation, sedimentation, economic height of dam, selection of suitable site.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. K Subramanya, Engineering Hydrology, Mc-Graw Hill.\n\n\n

2. K N Muthreja, Applied Hydrology, Tata Mc-Graw Hill.\n\n\n

3. K Subramanya, Water Resources Engineering through Objective Questions, Tata McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

4. GL Asawa, Irrigation Engineering, Wiley Eastern\n\n\n

5. L W Mays, Water Resources Engineering, Wiley.\n\n\n

6. JD Zimmerman, Irrigation, John Wiley &amp; Sons\n\n\n

7. CSP Ojha, R Berndtsson and P Bhunya, Engineering Hydrology, Oxford.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Outcomes:\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b>At the end of the course, students must be in a position to:</b>\n\n\n

Understand the interaction among various processes in the hydrologic cycle\n\n\n

Apply the application of fluid mechanics and use of computers in solving a host of problems in hydraulic engineering\n\n\n

Study types and classes of hydrologic simulation models and design procedures for safe and effective passage of flood flows for design of hydraulic structures\n\n\n

 Understand the basic aquifer parameters and estimate groundwater resources for different hydro-geological boundary conditions\n\n\n

Understand application of systems concept, advanced optimization techniques to cover the socio-technical aspects in the field of water resources\n\n\n

Apply the principles and applications of remote sensing, GPS and GIS in the context to hydrological extreme flood and drought events in water resources engineering\n\n\n
</string>

    <string name="cvsem5sub6">Environmental Engineering-I </string>
<string name="EEcv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Water: -Sources of Water and quality issues, water

quality requirement for different beneficial uses, Water quality standards, water quality indices, water safety plans, Water Supply systems, Need for planned water supply schemes, Water demand industrial and agricultural water requirements,

Components of water supply system; Transmission of water, Distribution system, Various valves used in W/S systems, service reservoirs and design.

Water Treatment: aeration, sedimentation, coagulation flocculation, filtration, disinfection, advanced treatments like adsorption, ion exchange, membrane processes\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Air-Composition and properties of air, Quantification of air pollutants, Monitoring of air pollutants, Air pollution- Occupational hazards, Urban air pollution automobile pollution, Chemistry of combustion, Automobile engines, quality of fuel, operating conditions and interrelationship. Air quality standards, Control measures for Air pollution, construction and limitations\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Noise- Basic concept, measurement and various control methods.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Building Plumbing-Introduction to various types of home plumbing systems for water supply and waste water disposal, high rise building plumbing, Pressure reducing valves, Break pressure tanks, Storage tanks, Building drainage for high rise buildings, various kinds of fixtures and fittings used.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practical Work: List of Experiments</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Physical Characterization of water: Turbidity, Electrical Conductivity, pH\n\n\n

2. Analysis of solids content of water: Dissolved, Settleable, suspended, total, volatile, inorganic etc.\n\n\n

3. Alkalinity and acidity, Hardness: total hardness, calcium and magnesium hardness\n\n\n

4. Analysis of ions: copper, chloride and sulfate\n\n\n

5. Optimum coagulant dose\n\n\n

6. Chemical Oxygen Demand (COD)\n\n\n

7. Dissolved Oxygen (D.O) and Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD)\n\n\n

 8. Break point Chlorination\n\n\n

9. Bacteriological quality measurement: MPN,\n\n\n

10. Ambient Air quality monitoring (TSP, RSPM, SOX, NOx)\n\n\n

11. Ambient noise measurement\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Introduction to Environmental Engineering and Science by Gilbert Masters, Prentice Hall, New Jersey.\n\n\n

2. Introduction to Environmental Engineering by P. Aarne Vesilind, Susan M. Morgan, Thompson/Brooks/Cole; Second Edition 2008.\n\n\n

3. Peavy, H.s, Rowe, D.R, Tchobanoglous, G. Environmental Engineering, Mc-Graw Hill International Editions, New York 1985.\n\n\n

4. MetCalf and Eddy. Wastewater Engineering, Treatment, Disposal and Reuse, Tata McGraw-Hill, New Delhi.\n\n\n

5. Manual on Water Supply and Treatment. Ministry of Urban Development, New Delhi.\n\n\n
6. Plumbing Engineering. Theory, Design and Practice, S.M. Patil, 1999\n\n\n

7. Integrated Solid Waste Management, Tchobanoglous, Theissen &amp; Vigil. McGraw Hill Publication\n\n\n

8. Manual on Sewerage and Sewage Treatment Systems, Part A, B and C. Central Public Health and Environmental Engineering Organization, Ministry of Urban Development.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem5sub7">Transportation Engineering</string>
<string name="TEcv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Highway development and planning-Classification of roads, road development in India, Current road projects in India, highway alignment and project preparation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Geometric design of highways-: Introduction; highway cross section elements; sight distance, design of horizontal alignment, design of vertical alignment; design of intersections, problems\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Traffic engineering &amp; control- Traffic Characteristics, traffic engineering studies, traffic flow and capacity, traffic regulation and control; design of road intersections; design of parking facilities; highway lighting; problems\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: </font></b>\n\n\nPavement materials-Materials used in Highway Construction- Soils, Stone aggregates, bituminous binders, bituminous paving mixes; Portland cement and cement concrete: desirable properties, tests, requirements for different types of pavements Problems.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Design of pavements- Introduction; flexible pavements, factors affecting design and performance; stresses in flexible pavements; design of flexible pavements as per IRC; rigid pavements- components and functions; factors affecting design and performance of CC pavements; stresses in rigid pavements; design of concrete pavements as per IRC; problems\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Khanna, S.K., Justo, C.E.G and Veeraragavan, A, "Highway Engineering", Revised 10th Edition, Nem Chand &amp; Bros, 2017\n\n\n

2. Kadiyalai, L.R., Traffic Engineering and Transport Planning, Khanna Publishers.\n\n\n

3. Partha Chakraborty, "Principles Of Transportation Engineering", PHI Learning.\n\n\n

4. Fred L. Mannering, Scott S. Washburn, Walter P. Kilareski, Principles of Highway Engineering and Traffic Analysis, 4th Edition, John Wiley\n\n\n

5. Srinivasa Kumar, R, Textbook of Highway Engineering, Universities Press, 2011.\n\n\n

6. Paul H. Wright and Karen K. Dixon, Highway Engineering, 7th Edition, Wiley Student Edition, 2009.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem5sub8">Environmental Science</string>
<string name="EScv">\n\n\n

    We as human being are not an entity separate from the environment around us rather we are a constituent seamlessly integrated and co-exist with the environment around us. We are not an entity so separate from the environment that we can think of mastering and controlling it rather we must understand that each and every action of ours reflects on the environment and vice versa. Ancient wisdom drawn from Vedas about environment and its sustenance reflects these ethos. There is a direct application of this

wisdom even in modern times.\n\n\n Idea of an activity based course on environment protection is to sensitize the students on the above issues through following two type of activities:\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>(a) Awareness Activities:</font></b>\n\n\n

i) Small group meetings about water management, promotion of recycle use, generation of less waste, avoiding electricity waste\n\n\n

ii) Slogan making events\n\n\n

iii) Poster making events\n\n\n

iv) Cycle rally\n\n\n

v) Lectures from experts\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>(b) Actual Activities:\n\n\n</font></b>

i) Plantation\n\n\n

ii) Gifting a tree to see its full growth\n\n\n

iii) Cleanliness drive\n\n\n

iv) Drive for segregation of waste\n\n\n

v) To live some big environmentalist for a week or so to understand his work\n\n\n

vi) To work in kitchen garden for mess\n\n\n

vii) To know about the different varieties of plants\n\n\n

viii) Shutting down the fans and ACs of the campus for an hour or so\n\n\n

********************************************************************************

</string>

<string name="cvsem5sub9">Summer Entrepreneurship-II</string>
<string name="SE2cv">

</string>



<string name="cvsem6sub1">Construction Engineering</string>
<string name="CEcv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n

Basics of Construction-Unique features of construction, construction projects- types and features, phases of a project, agencies involved and their methods of execution;\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Construction project planning- Stages of project planning: pre-tender planning, pre-construction planning, detailed construction planning, role of client and contractor, level of detail. Process of development of plans and schedules, work break-down structure, activity lists, assessment of work content, concept of productivities, estimating durations, sequence of activities, activity utility data; Techniques of planning- Bar charts, Gantt Charts. Networks: basic terminology, types of precedence relationships, preparation of CPM networks: activity on link and activity on node representation, computation of float values, critical and semi critical paths, calendaring networks. PERT- Assumptions underlying PERT analysis, determining three time estimates, analysis, slack computations, calculation of probability of completion.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\nConstruction Methods basics: Types of foundations and construction methods; Basics of Formwork and Staging; Common building construction methods (conventional walls and slabs, conventional framed structure with blockwork walls; Modular construction methods for repetitive works; Precast concrete construction methods; Basics of Slip forming for tall structures; Basic construction methods for steel structures; Basics of construction methods for Bridges.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Construction Equipment basics: Conventional

construction methods Vs Mechanized methods and advantages of latter; Equipment for Earthmoving, Dewatering; Concrete mixing, transporting &amp; placing; Cranes, Hoists and other equipment for lifting; Equipment for transportation of materials. Equipment Productivities\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: </font></b>\n\n\nPlanning and organizing construction site and

resources- Site: site layout including enabling structures, developing site organization, Documentation at site; Manpower: planning, organizing, staffing, motivation; Materials: concepts of planning, procurement and inventory control; Equipment: basic concepts of planning and organizing; Funds: cash flow, sources of funds, Histograms and S-Curves. Earned Value; Resource Scheduling- Bar chart, line of balance technique, resource constraints and conflicts; resource aggregation, allocation, smoothening and leveling. Common Good Practices in Construction\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Project Monitoring &amp; Control- Supervision, record

keeping, periodic progress reports, periodical progress meetings. Updating of plans: purpose, frequency and methods of updating. Common causes of time and cost overruns and corrective measures. Basics of Modern Project management systems such as Lean Construction; Use of Building Information Modelling (BIM) in project management, Quality control: concept of quality, quality of constructed structure, use of manuals and checklists for quality control, role of inspection, basics of statistical quality control. Safety, Health and Environment on project sites: accidents, their causes, effects and preventive measures, costs of accidents, occupational health problems in construction, organizing for safety and health.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n Contracts Management basics: Importance of contracts; Types of Contracts, parties to a contract; Common contract clauses (Notice to proceed, rights and duties of various parties, notices to be given, Contract Duration and Price. Performance parameters; Delays, penalties and liquidated damages; Force Majeure, Suspension and Termination. Changes &amp; variations, Dispute Resolution methods.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8:</font></b>\n\n\n Construction Costs: Make-up of construction costs; Classification of costs, timecost trade-off in construction projects, compression and decompression.\n\n\n

Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n

1. Varghese, P.C., "Building Construction", Prentice Hall India, 2007.\n\n\n

2. National Building Code, Bureau of Indian Standards, New Delhi, 2017.\n\n\n

3. Chudley, R., Construction Technology, ELBS Publishers, 2007.\n\n\n

4. Peurifoy, R.L. Construction Planning, Methods and Equipment, McGraw Hill, 2011\n\n\n

5. Nunnally, S.W. Construction Methods and Management, Prentice Hall, 2006\n\n\n

6. Jha, Kumar Neeraj., Construction Project management, Theory &amp; Practice, Pearson Education India, 2015\n\n\n

7. Punmia, B.C., Khandelwal, K.K., Project Planning with PERT and CPM, Laxmi Publications, 2016.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem6sub2">Engineering Economics</string>
<string name="EEcocv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\nBasic Principles and Methodology of Economics. Demand/Supply - elasticity-Government Policies and Application. Theory of the Firm and Market Structure. Basic Macro-economic Concepts (including GDP/GNP/NI/ Disposable Income) and Identities for both closed and open economies. Aggregate demand and Supply (IS/LM). Price Indices (WPI/CPI), Interest rates, Direct and Indirect Taxes (3 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 2: Public Sector Economics -Welfare, Externalities, Labour Market. Components of Monetary and Financial System, Central Bank -Monetary Aggregates; Commercial Banks &amp; their functions; Capital and Debt Markets. Monetary and Fiscal Policy Tools &amp; their impact on the economy - Inflation and Phillips Curve. (2 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 3:Elements of Business/Managerial Economics and forms of organizations. Cost &amp; Cost Control-Techniques, Types of Costs, Lifecycle costs, Budgets, Break even Analysis, Capital Budgeting, Application of Linear Programming. Investment Analysis - NPV, ROI, IRR, Payback Period, Depreciation, Time value of money (present and future worth of cash flows). Business Forecasting - Elementary techniques. Statements - Cash flow, Financial. Case Study Method. (3 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 4:Indian economy - Brief overview of post-independence period - plans. Post reform Growth, Structure of productive activity. Issues of Inclusion - Sectors, States/Regions, Groups of people (M/F), Urbanization. Employment-Informal, Organized, Unorganized, Public, Private. Challenges and Policy Debates in Monetary, Fiscal, Social, External sectors. (2 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 5:Estimation / Measurements for various items- Introduction to the process of Estimation; Use of relevant Indian Standard Specifications for the same, taking out quantities from the given requirements of the work, comparison of different alternatives, Bar bending schedules, Mass haul Diagrams, Estimating Earthwork and Foundations, Estimating Concrete and Masonry, Finishes, Interiors, MEP works; BIM and quantity take-offs; adding equipment costs; labour costs; rate analysis; Material survey-Thumb rules for computation of materials requirement for different materials for buildings, percentage breakup of the cost, cost sensitive index, market survey of basic materials. Use of Computers in quantity surveying (7 lectures)\n\n\n

 Module 6: Specifications-Types, requirements and importance, detailed specifications for buildings, roads, minor bridges and industrial structures. (3 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 7: Rate analysis-Purpose, importance and necessity of the same, factors affecting, task work, daily output from different equipment/ productivity. (3 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 8: Tender- Preparation of tender documents,

importance of inviting tenders, contract types, relative merits, prequalification. general and special conditions, termination of contracts, extra work and Changes, penalty and liquidated charges, Settlement of disputes, R.A. Bill &amp; Final Bill, Payment of advance, insurance, claims, price variation, etc. Preparing Bids- Bid Price buildup: Material, Labour, Equipment costs, Risks, Direct &amp; Indirect Overheads, Profits; Bid conditions, alternative specifications; Alternative Bids. Bid process management (6 lectures)\n\n\n

Module 9: Introduction to Acts pertaining to-Minimum wages, Workman\'s compensation, Contracts, Arbitration, Easement rights. (1 lecture)\n\n\n

Term Work Assignments may include:\n\n\n

1. Deriving an approximate estimate for a multistoried building by approximate methods.\n\n\n

2. Detailed estimate for the following with the required material survey for the same.\n\n\n

a. Ground plus three storied RCC Framed structure building with blockwork walls\n\n\n

b. bridge with minimum 2 spans\n\n\n

c. factory building\n\n\n

d. road work\n\n\n

e. cross drainage work\n\n\n

f. Ground plus three storied building with load-bearing walls g Cost of finishes, MEPworks for (f) above\n\n\n

3. Preparation of valuation report in standard Government form.\n\n\n

4. Assignments on rate analysis, specifications and simple estimates.\n\n\n

 5. Detailed estimate of minor structure.\n\n\n

6. Preparation of Bar bending schedule.\n\n\n

Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n

1. Mankiw Gregory N. (2002), Principles of Economics, Thompson Asia\n\n\n

2. V. Mote, S. Paul, G. Gupta (2004), Managerial Economics, Tata McGraw Hill\n\n\n

3. Misra, S.K. and Puri (2009), Indian Economy, Himalaya\n\n\n

4. Pareek Saroj (2003), Textbook of Business Economics, Sunrise Publishers\n\n\n

5. M Chakravarty, Estimating, Costing Specifications &amp; Valuation\n\n\n

6. Joy P K, Handbook of Construction Management, Macmillan\n\n\n
    7. B.S. Patil, Building &amp; Engineering Contracts\n\n\n

    8. Relevant Indian Standard Specifications.\n\n\n

9. World Bank Approved Contract Documents.\n\n\n

10. FIDIC Contract Conditions.\n\n\n

11. Acts Related to Minimum Wages, Workmen\'s Compensation, Contract, and Arbitration\n\n\n

12. Typical PWD Rate Analysis documents.\n\n\n

13. UBS Publishers &amp; Distributors, Estimating and Costing in Civil Engineering: Theory and Practice including Specification and Valuations,2016\n\n\n

14. Dutta, B.N., Estimating and Costing in Civil Engineering (Theory &amp; Practice), UBS Publishers, 2016\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem6sub3">Design Of Steel Structure</string>
<string name="DSScv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>   Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\n Introduction: Steel structures, material properties,

Limit states and design philosophies; analysis and design methods, Loads, partial safety factors and load combinations, analysis of roof for wind loads. Codes and standards. Section Classification: Plastic, compact, semi-compact, and slender sections.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Connections: Structural fasteners - Rivets, bolts and welds, strength under combined stresses, Bolted and Welded Connections- Simple and Eccentric and Column bases.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Tension members: Design based on net section including shear lag effects and block shear, lug angles. Compression members:\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Design for flexural and flexural-torsional buckling, Effective length factor: Sway and Non- sway frames, Local buckling, Built-up columns - Battens and lacings. Laterally Supported and Unsupported Beams:\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Design strength using shear-moment interaction; Built-up beams, Shear buckling strength, Plate girders and design of stiffeners, Lateral torsional buckling, Effect of restraints and effective length.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Beam-Columns: Effect of axial load on flexure behaviour, P-M interaction and moment amplification, Flexural torsional buckling and Bi-axial bending.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. McCormac, J.C., Nelson, J.K. Jr., Structural Steel Design. 3rd edition. Prentice Hall, N.J., 2003.\n\n\n

2. Galambos, T.V., Lin, F.J., Johnston, B.G., Basic Steel Design with LRFD, Prentice Hall, 1996\n\n\n

3. Segui, W. T., LRFD Steel Design, 2nd Ed., PWS Publishing,

Boston.\n\n\n

4. Salmon, C.G. and Johnson, J.E., Steel Structures: Design and Behavior, 3rd Edition, Harper &amp; Row, Publishers, New York, 1990.\n\n\n

5. Related Codes of Practice of BIS\n\n\n

6. NBC, National Building Code, BIS (2017).\n\n\n

7. ASCE, Minimum Design Loads for Buildings and Other Structures, ASCE 7-02, American Society of Civil Engineers, Virginia, 2002.\n\n\n

 8. Subramanian, N. (2010). Steel Structures: Design and Practice, Oxford University Press.\n\n\n

9. Duggal, S.K. (2014). Limit State Design of Steel Structures, McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem6sub4">Geotechnical Engineering-II</string>
<string name="GE2cv">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Consolidation of Soil - Introduction, comparison

between compaction and consolidation, initial, primary &amp; secondary consolidation, spring analogy for primary consolidation, interpretation of consolidation test results, Terzaghi\'s theory of consolidation, final settlement of soil deposits, computation of consolidation settlement and secondary consolidation.\n\n\n

    <b>On completion of this module, the student must be able to:</b>\n\n\n

• Understand the basic mechanism of consolidation of soil;\n\n\n

• Determine various consolidation parameters of soil through laboratory test; Evaluate ground settlements against time.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b> Shear Strength - Mohr circle and its characteristics,

    principal planes, relation between major and minor principal stresses, Mohr-Coulomb theory, types of shear tests: direct shear test, merits of direct shear test, triaxial compression tests, test behaviour of UU, CU and CD tests, pore- pressure measurement, computation of effective shear strength parameters unconfined compression test, vane shear test\n\n\n 
   <b>On completion of this module, the student must be able to:</b> \n\n\n

• Determine graphically and analytically the stress state in any plane of the soil mass;\n\n\n
    Perform various shear strength tests and appreciate the different field conditions which they simulate;\n\n\n

• Understand the significance of shear strength parameters in various geotechnical analyses;\n\n\n

• Evaluate the stiffness of soil using shear strength parameters\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>Stability of Slopes - Introduction, types of slopes and their failure mechanisms, factor of safety, analysis of finite and infinite slopes, wedge failure Swedish circle method, friction circle method, stability numbers and charts.\n\n\n<b> On completion of this module, the student must be able to:</b>

• Differentiate various modes of slope failure;\n\n\n

• Evaluate factor of safety of infinite slopes based on different ground conditions; \n\n\nUnderstand various methods for computation of factor of safety for finite slopes.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Soil Exploration- Introduction, methods of site exploration and soil investigation, methods of boring, soil samplers, sampling procedures, trail pits, borings, penetrometer tests, analysis of borehole logs, geophysical and advance soil exploration methods.\n\n\n

    <b>On completion of this module, the student must be able to:\n\n\n</b>

Specify a strategy for site investigation to identify the soil deposits and determine the depth and spatial extent within the ground;\n\n\n

• Understand various site investigation techniques and their in-situ applications;\n\n\n Prepare a soil investigation report based on borehole log data and various in-situ tests like SPT, CPT, etc.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5</font></b>\n\n\n Application of soil mechanics to determine earth pressures, analysis of retaining walls, cuts &amp; excavations and sheet piles, stability of slopes, instrumentation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Soil Mechanics by Craig R.F., Chapman &amp; Hall\n\n\n

2. Fundamentals of Soil Engineering by Taylor, John Wiley &amp; Sons\n\n\n

3. An Introduction to Geotechnical Engineering, by Holtz R.D. and Kovacs, W.D., Prentice Hall, NJ\n\n\n

4. Principles of Geotechnical Engineering, by Braja M. Das, Cengage Learning\n\n\n

5. Principles of Foundation Engineering, by Braja M. Das, Cengage Learning\n\n\n

6. Essentials of Soil Mechanics and Foundations: Basic Geotechnics by David F. McCarthy\n\n\n

7. Soil Mechanics in Engineering Practice by Karl Terzaghi, Ralph B. Peck, and Gholamreza Mesri.\n\n\n

8. Geotechnical Engineering: Principles and Practices of Soil Mechanics and Foundation

Engineering (Civil and Environmental Engineering) by V.N.S. Murthy\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem6sub5">Environmaental Engineering-II</string>
<string name="EE2cv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Sewage-Domestic and Storm water, Quantity of Sewage, Sewage flow variations. Conveyance of sewage- Sewers, shapes design parameters, operation and maintenance of sewers, Sewage pumping, Sewerage, Sewer appurtenances, Design of sewerage systems. Small bore systems, Storm Water- Quantification and design of Storm water; Sewage and Sullage, Pollution due to improper disposal of sewage, National River cleaning plans, Wastewater treatment, aerobic and anaerobic treatment systems, suspended and attached growth systems, recycling of sewage - quality requirements for various purposes.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module2:</font></b>\n\n\n Solid waste management-Municipal solid waste, Composition and various chemical and physical parameters of MSW, MSW management: Collection, transport, treatment and disposal of MSW. Special MSW: waste from commercial establishments and other urban areas, solid waste from construction activities, biomedical wastes, Effects of solid waste on environment: effects on air, soil, water surface and ground health hazards. Disposal of solid waste-segregation, reduction at source, recovery and recycle. Disposal methods- Integrated solid waste management. Hazardous waste: Types and nature of hazardous waste as per the HW Schedules of regulating authorities.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Government authorities and their roles in water supply, sewerage disposal. Solid waste management and monitoring/control of environmental pollution.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practical Work: List of Experiments\n\n\n</font></b>


1. Physical Characterization of water: Turbidity, Electrical Conductivity, pH\n\n\n

2. Analysis of solids content of water: Dissolved, Settleable, suspended, total, volatile, inorganic etc.\n\n\n

3. Alkalinity and acidity, Hardness: total hardness, calcium and magnesium hardness\n\n\n

4. Analysis of ions: copper, chloride and sulfate\n\n\n

5. Optimum coagulant dose\n\n\n

6. Chemical Oxygen Demand (COD)\n\n\n

7. Dissolved Oxygen (D.O) and Biochemical Oxygen Demand (BOD)\n\n\n

8. Break point Chlorination\n\n\n

 9. Bacteriological quality measurement: MPN,\n\n\n

10. Ambient Air quality monitoring (TSP, RSPM, SOX, NOx)\n\n\n

11. Ambient noise measurement\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Introduction to Environmental Engineering and Science by Gilbert Masters, Prentice Hall, New Jersey.\n\n\n

2. Introduction to Environmental Engineering by P. Aarne Vesilind, Susan M. Morgan,

Thompson/Brooks/Cole; Second Edition 2008.\n\n\n

3. Peavy, H.s, Rowe, D.R, Tchobanoglous, G. Environmental Engineering, Mc-Graw Hill International Editions, New York 1985.\n\n\n

4. MetCalf and Eddy. Wastewater Engineering, Treatment, Disposal and Reuse, Tata McGraw-Hill, New Delhi.\n\n\n

5. Manual on Water Supply and Treatment. Ministry of Urban Development, New Delhi.\n\n\n

6. Plumbing Engineering. Theory, Design and Practice, S.M. Patil, 1999\n\n\n

7. Integrated Solid Waste Management, Tchobanoglous, Theissen &amp; Vigil. McGraw Hill Publication\n\n\n

8. Manual on Sewerage and Sewage Treatment Systems, Part A, B and C. Central Public Health and Environmental Engineering Organization, Ministry of Urban Development.\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem7sub1">Graduate Employability Skills and Competitive Cources(Gate,IES,ETC)</string>
<string name="Graduatecv">
    Graduate Employability Skills and Competitive Cources(Gate,IES,ETC)
</string>

    <string name="cvsem7sub2">Professional Practice, LAW,and Ethics</string>
    <string name="PPLEcv">\n\n\n

    Basic elements of civil engineering professional practice are introduced in this course. Roles of all participants in the process-owners, developers, designers, consultants, architects, contractors, and suppliers are described. Basic concepts in professional practice, business management, public policy, leadership, and professional licensure are introduced. The course covers professional relations, civic responsibilities, and ethical obligations for engineering practice. The course also describes contracts management, and various legal aspects related to engineering. Further, the course familiarizes students with elementary knowledge of laws that would be of utility in their profession, including several new areas of law such as IPR, ADR.\n\n\n

The course is designed to address the following:\n\n\n

• To make the students understand the types of roles they are expected to play in the society as practitioners of the civil engineering profession\n\n\n

• To develop some ideas of the legal and practical aspects of their profession\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Proposed Syllabus</font></b>\n\n\n

Professional practice covering the respective roles of the various stakeholders in the profession of civil engineering and the factors governing the same; Professional ethics relating to civil engineering; Various aspects of contracts relating to construction and management of contracts; types of contractual and other disputes in the profession and methods of dispute resolution, legal aspects relating to employment and service conditions of labour; intellectual property rights and their legal framework\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
Modules:

     Module 1 A-</font></b>\n\n\n Professional Practice - Respective roles of

various stakeholders: Government (constituting regulatory bodies and standardization organizations, prescribing norms to ensure safety of the citizens); Standardization Bodies (ex. BIS, IRC) (formulating standards of practice); professional bodies (ex. Institution of Engineers(India), Indian Roads Congress, IIA/ COA, ECI, Local Bodies/ Planning Authorities) (certifying professionals and offering platforms for interaction); Clients/ owners (role governed by contracts); Developers (role governed by regulations such as RERA); Consultants (role governed by bodies such as CEAI); Contractors (role governed by contracts and regulatory Acts and Standards); Manufacturers/Vendors/ Service agencies (role governed by contracts and regulatory Acts and Standards)\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Module 1 B- </font></b>\n\n\n Professional Ethics - Definition of Ethics,

Professional Ethics, Business Ethics, Corporate Ethics, Engineering Ethics, Personal Ethics; Code of Ethics as defined in the website of Institution of Engineers (India); Profession, Professionalism, Professional Responsibility, Professional Ethics; Conflict of Interest, Gift Vs Bribery, Environmental breaches, Negligence, Deficiencies in state-of-theart; Vigil Mechanism, Whistleblowing, protected disclosures.\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\nGeneral Principles of Contracts Management: Indian Contract Act, 1972 and amendments covering General principles of contracting; Contract Formation &amp; Law, Privacy of contract, Various types of contract and their features; Valid &amp; Voidable Contracts; Prime and sub-contracts; Joint Ventures &amp; Consortium; Complex contract terminology; Tenders, Request For Proposals, Bids &amp; Proposals; Bid Evaluation; Contract Conditions &amp; Specifications; Critical/"Red Flag" conditions; Contract award &amp; Notice To Proceed; Variations &amp; Changes in Contracts; Differing site conditions; Cost escalation; Delays, Suspensions &amp; Terminations; Time extensions &amp; Force Majeure; Delay Analysis; Liquidated damages &amp; Penalties; Insurance &amp; Taxation; Performance and Excusable Nonperformance; Contract documentation; Contract Notices; Wrong practices in contracting (Bid shopping, Bid fixing, Cartels); Reverse auction, Case Studies; Build-Own-Operate &amp; variations; PublicPrivate Partnerships; International Commercial Terms;\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Module 3 :</font></b>\n\n\nArbitration, Conciliation and ADR (Alternative

Dispute Resolution) system: Arbitration - meaning, scope and types distinction between laws of 1940 and 1996; UNCITRAL model law - Arbitration and expert determination; Extent of judicial intervention; International commercial arbitration; Arbitration agreements essential and kinds, validity, reference and interim measures by court, Arbitration tribunal - appointment, challenge, jurisdiction of arbitral tribunal, powers, grounds of challenge, procedure and court assistance; Award including Form and content, Grounds for setting aside an award, Enforcement, Appeal and Revision; Enforcement of foreign awards - New York and Geneva Convention Awards; Distinction between conciliation, negotiation, mediation and arbitration, confidentiality, resort to judicial proceedings, costs; Dispute Resolution Boards; Lok Adalats\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Engagement of Labour and Labour &amp; other construction-related Laws: Role of Labour in Civil Engineering; Methods of engaging labour-on rolls, labour sub-contract, piece rate work; Industrial Disputes Act, 1947; Collective bargaining; Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946; Workmen\'s Compensation Act, 1923; Building &amp; Other Construction Workers (regulation of employment and conditions of service) Act (1996) and Rules (1998); RERA Act 2017, NBC 2017\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Law relating to Intellectual property: Introduction - meaning of intellectual property, main forms of IP, Copyright, Trademarks, Patents and Designs, Secrets; Law relating to Copyright in India including Historical evolution of Copy Rights Act, 1957, Meaning of copyright - computer programs, Ownership of copyrights and assignment, Criteria of infringement, Piracy in Internet - Remedies and procedures in India; Law relating to Patents under Patents Act, 1970 including Concept and historical perspective of patents law in India, Patentable inventions with special reference to biotechnology products, Patent protection for computer programs, Process of obtaining patent application, examination, opposition and sealing of patents, Patent cooperation treaty and grounds for opposition, Rights and obligations of patentee, Duration of patents - law and policy considerations, Infringement and related remedies;\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     ORGANISATION OF COURSE (2-0-0)\n\n\n</font></b>
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
            S.No) Module ~ No of Lectures</font>
 </b>\n\n\n

1A) Professional Practice ~ 2\n\n\n

1B) Professional Ethics ~2\n\n\n

2) Contracts Management~18\n\n\n

3) Dispute Resolution Mechanisms ~ 5\n\n\n

4) Labour; Labour &amp; other Laws ~ 2\n\n\n

5) Intellectual Property Management ~ 1\n\n\n

TOTAL 30\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Text/Reference Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. B.S. Patil, Legal Aspects of Building and Engineering Contracts, 1974.\n\n\n

2. The National Building Code, BIS, 2017\n\n\n

3. RERA Act, 2017\n\n\n

4. Meena Rao (2006), Fundamental concepts in Law of Contract, 3rd Edn. Professional Offset\n\n\n

 5. Neelima Chandiramani (2000), The Law of Contract: An Outline, 2nd Edn. Avinash Publications Mumbai\n\n\n

6. Avtarsingh (2002), Law of Contract, Eastern Book Co.\n\n\n

7. Dutt (1994), Indian Contract Act, Eastern Law House\n\n\n

8. Anson W.R. (1979), Law of Contract, Oxford University Press\n\n\n

9. Kwatra G.K. (2005), The Arbitration &amp; Conciliation of Law in India with case law on UNCITRAL Model Law on Arbitration, Indian Council of Arbitration\n\n\n

10. Wadhera (2004), Intellectual Property Rights, Universal Law Publishing Co.\n\n\n

11. T. Ramappa (2010), Intellectual Property Rights Law in India, Asia Law House\n\n\n

12. Bare text (2005), Right to Information Act\n\n\n

13. O.P. Malhotra, Law of Industrial Disputes, N.M. Tripathi Publishers\n\n\n

14. K.M. Desai (1946), The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act\n\n\n

15. Rustamji R.F., Introduction to the Law of Industrial Disputes, Asia Publishing House\n\n\n

16. Vee, Charles &amp; Skitmore, Martin (2003) Professional Ethics in the Construction Industry, Engineering Construction and Architectural management, Vol. 10, Iss2,pp 117-127, MCB UP Ltd\n\n\n

17. American Society of Civil Engineers (2011) ASCE Code of Ethics - Principles Study and Application\n\n\n

18. Ethics in Engineering- M.W.Martin&amp; R.Schinzinger, McGraw-Hill\n\n\n

19. Engineering Ethics, National Institute for Engineering Ethics, USA\n\n\n

20. www.ieindia.org\n\n\n

 19. Engineering Ethics, National Institute for Engineering Ethics, USA\n\n\n

20. www.jeindia.org\n\n\n

21. Engineering ethics: concepts and cases - C. E. Harris, M.S. Pritchard, M.J.Rabins\n\n\n

22. CONSTRUCTION CONTRACTS, http://www.jnormanstark .com/contract.html\n\n\n

23. Internet and Business Handbook, Chap 4, CONTRACTS LAW, http://www.laderapress.com/laderapress/contractslaw1 .html\n\n\n

24. Contract&amp;Agreements http://www.tco.ac.ir/law/English /agreements/General/Contract%20Law/C.html\n\n\n

25. Contracts, http://206.127.69.152/jgretch/crj/211/ch7.ppt\n\n\n

26. Business &amp; Personal Law. Chapter 7. "How Contracts Arise", http://yucaipahigh.com/schristensen/lawweb/lawch7 .ppt\n\n\n

27. Types of Contracts, http://cmsu2.cmsu.edu/public/classes /rahm/meiners.con.ppt\n\n\n

    </string>


<string name="cvsem7sub3">Project-I</string>
<string name="Projectcv7">Project-I</string>

<string name="cvsem7sub4">Summer Entrepreneurship-III</string>
<string name="summercv7">Summer Entrepreneurship-III</string>


    <string name="cvsem7sub5">Open Elective-I</string>
<string name="cvsem7sub6">Program Elective-III</string>
<string name="cvsem7sub7">Program Elective-II</string>


<string name="cvsem7ele1">Pavement Design</string>
<string name="cvsem7elePD">
   <b> Pavement Design.</b>

Introduction: Types and component parts of pavements, Factors affecting design and performance of pavements.

Highway and airport pavements. Stresses and Deflections in masses. Burmister\'s two layer theory, three layer and

Flexible Pavements: Stresses and deflections in homogeneous

multi-layer theories; wheel load stresses, various factors in traffic wheel loads; ESWL of multiple wheels. Repeated loads and EWL factors, sustained loads. Pavement behaviour under transient traffic loads. Flexible Pavement Design Methods For Highways and Airports: Empirical, semi-empirical and theoretical approaches, development, principle, design steps, advantages; design of flexible pavements as per IRC; Stresses in Rigid Pavements: Types of stresses and causes, factors influencing the stresses; general considerations in rigid pavement analysis, EWL; wheel load stresses, warping stresses, frictional stresses, combined stresses.

Rigid Pavement Design: Types of joints in cement concrete

pavements and their functions, joint spacings; design of CC pavement for roads and runways as per IRC, design of joint details for longitudinal joints, contraction joints and expansion joints. IRC method of design by stress ratio method. Design of continuously reinforced concrete pavements; Maintenance, repair and rehabilitation of pavements including design of bituminous and concrete overlays as per IRC Prerequisite:

</string>

<string name="cvsem7ele2">Building Construction Practice</string>
<string name="cvsem7ele2bcp">
    <b>Building Construction Practice.</b>

Specifications, details and sequence of activities and construction co-ordination - Site Clearance - Marking - Earthwork-masonry stone masonry - Bond in masonry - concrete hollow block masonry flooring damp proof courses construction joints - movement and expansion joints - pre cast pavements - Building foundations - basements temporary shed - centering and shuttering slip forms scaffoldings-de-shuttering forms - Fabrication and erection of steel trusses frames braced domes - laying brick— weather and water proof - roof finishes acoustic and fire protection; Sub Structure Construction- Techniques of Box jacking - Pipe Jacking under water construction of diaphragm walls and basement-Tunnelling techniques - Piling techniques - well and caisson - sinking cofferdam - cable anchoring and grouting-driving diaphragm walls, sheet piles - shoring for deep cutting - well points -Dewatering and stand by Plant equipment for underground open excavation; Super Structure Construction- Launching girders, bridge decks, off shore platforms special forms for shells-techniques for heavy decks in-situ pre-stressing in high rise structures, Material handling erecting light weight components on tall structures - Support structure for heavy Equipment and conveyors Erection of articulated structures, braced domes and space decks; Prerequisite:
</string>

    <string name="cvsem7ele3">Transport of Water and Wastewater</string>
    <string name="cvsem7ele3TWW">
        <b>Transport of water and wastewater.</b>

The objective of the course is to make students gain insight into how the water and wastewater gets transported through conduits and open channels, and use the same for the design, operation and maintenance of these systems. Water Supply Systems: Storage requirements, impounding reservoirs, intake structures, pipe hydraulics, design of distribution systems, distribution and balancing reservoirs, pipe materials, appurtenances, design for external loads, maintenance and operation. Sanitary Sewerage Systems: Flow estimation, sewer materials, hydraulics of flow in sewers, sewer lay out, sewer transitions, materials for sewers, appurtenances, manholes, sewer design, conventional and model based design, sewage pumps and pumping stations, corrosion prevention, operation and maintenance, safety. Storm water Drainage Systems: Drainage layouts, storm runoff estimation, hydraulics of flow in storm water drains, materials, cross sections, design of storm water drainage systems, inlets, storm water pumping, operation and maintenance

    </string>
<string name="cvsem7ele4">Pipleline Engineering</string>
<string name="cvsem7ele4pe">
    <b>Pipeline Engineering:</b>

The course should cover key issues for designing and operating pipelines for transmission and distribution of water; Analysis of flow in water transmission and water distribution systems (pump &amp; gravity); optimal design and operation of systems for achieving different goals (including latest tools available for optimization); Extended period simulations, Software for WDN analysis and design, Rehabilitation of pipeline systems; Water auditing, online monitoring and control, leak and burst detection; transient analysis and surge protection; Appurtenances (valves / flow meters etc.); Selection of pipe material; Jointing details; Pipe laying and testing; Structural design for buried and surface mounted pipes

Pre-Requisite: Basic course in Hydraulic Engineering

</string>

    <string name="cvsem7ele5">Surface Hydrology</string>
    <string name="cvsem7ele5pe">
        <b>Surface Hydrology.</b>

Study of descriptive and quantitative hydrology dealing with the distribution, circulation, and storage of water on the earth\'s surface; discusses principles of hydrologic processes and presents methods of analysis and their applications to engineering and environmental problems.

Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvsem7ele6">  Masonry Structures</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele6pe">
       <b> Masonry Structures.</b>

Introduction to analysis, design and construction of masonry structures. Mechanical properties of clay and concrete masonry units, mortar, and grout. Compressive, tensile, flexural, and shear behavior of masonry structural components. Strength and behavior of unreinforced bearing walls. Detailed design of reinforced masonry beams, columns, structural walls with and without openings, and complete lateral-force resisting building systems.

Prerequisite:

</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele7">Wood Structures</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele7pe">
        <b>Wood Structures.</b>


Mechanical properties of wood, stress grades and working stresses; effects of strength-reducing characteristics, moisture content, and duration of loading and causes of wood deterioration; glued-laminated timber and plywood; behavior and design of connections, beams, and beam-columns; design of buildings and bridges; other structural applications: trusses, rigid frames, arches, and pole-type buildings, and prismatic plates and hyperbolic paraboloids.

Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele8">Concrete Technology</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele8pe">
        <b>Concrete Technology</b>
         Concrete; Properties of ingredients, tests, Production of concrete, mixing, compaction curing, Properties of fresh concrete; Defects in Concrete, Concrete additives.; Behavior of concrete in tension and compression, shear and bond, Influence of various factors on test results, Time dependent behavior of concrete -creep, shrinkage and fatigue; Concrete mix design; Proportioning of concrete mixes, basic considerations, cost specifications, factors in the choice of mix proportion, different method of mix design. Quality control, Behavior of concrete in extreme environment; temperature problem in concreting, hot weather, cold weather and under water conditions, Resistance to freezing, sulphate and acid attack, efflorescence, fire resistance; Inspection and testing of concrete- Concrete cracking, types of cracks, causes and remedies Non-destructive tests on concrete; Chemical tests on cement and aggregates; Special concrete; types and specifications, Fibre reinforced and steel Fibre reinforced concrete, Polymer concrete, Use of admixtures; Deterioration of concrete and its prevention Repair and rehabilitation.

Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele9">Advanced Structural Analysis</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele9pe">
Advanced Structural Analysis. Elasticity: Introduction, Components of strain and strain, Hooke\'s law, Plane stress and plane strain, Equations of equilibrium and compatibility, Boundary conditions, Two dimensional problems in rectangular and polar coordinates, Bending of simple and cantilever beams; Model Analysis: Structural similitude, Direct and indirect model analysis, Model material and model making, Measurement for forces and deformations; Introduction to Finite element method for structural analysis; Review of principle of virtual work, Ritz method, Discretization of domain, Basic element shape, Discretization process; Application of finite element method to one and two-dimensional plane stress strain elements.
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele10">Soil Mechanics-II</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele10pe">
Soil Mechanics-II. Application of soil mechanics to determine earth pressures, analysis of retaining walls, cuts &amp; excavations and sheet piles, stability of slopes, instrumentation.

Prerequisite:

Reference books:

•Soil Mechanics by Craig R.F., Chapman &amp; Hall

•Principles of Geotechnical Engineering, by Braja M. Das, Cengage Learning

•On successful completion of this course, the students:

Should be able design retaining wall subjected to various loads with the knowledge of earth pressure theories.

•Should be able to design sheet pile wall with different methods.

Should get familiarized with different construction practices for excavation with advantages and disadvantages of each method.

Should be able to determine the safety analysis for slopes with different methods proposed in the syllabus. Should get introduced with the commercial softwares for analyzing the stability of slopes and retaining walls.
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele11">Environmental impact assessment and life cycle analyses</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele11pe">
Environmental impact assessment and life cycle analyses. Evolution of EIA: Concepts of EIA methodologies, Screening and scoping; Rapid EIA and Comprehensive EIA; General Framework for Environmental Impact Assessment, Characterization and site assessment. Environmental Risk Analysis, Definition of Risk, Matrix Method. Checklist method, Fault tree analysis, Consequence Analysis; Socioeconomic aspects, measures of effectiveness of pollution control activities; Environmental Legislation; Introduction to Environmental Management Systems; Environmental Statement procedures; Environmental Audit: Cost Benefit Analysis; Life Cycle Assessment, Resource Balance, Energy Balance &amp; Management Review; Operational Control; Case Studies on EΙΑ.
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele12">Groundwater Engineering</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele12pe">
Groundwater Engineering: The main objective is to provide sufficient knowledge to the students about the groundwater hydrology, well hydraulics and well construction, geophysical explorations, groundwater quality and management of groundwater resources; Problems and perspectives regarding groundwater in India; Hydrogeology: Darcy\'s Equation; flow characteristics; general flow equations; unsaturated flow; Well Hydraulics: Steady and unsteady radial flows in aquifers; partially penetrating wells; multiple well systems; characteristic well losses; specific capacity, Surface and Subsurface investigations (Geologic methods; remote sensing; geophysical explorations; electrical resistivity and seismic refraction), Water Wells: Construction; completion, development, protection and rehabilitation of wells; Groundwater quality; Groundwater Management: Basin management, investigations, conjunctive use, modeling, artificial recharge; Saline water intrusion
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele13">Structural Dynamics</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele13pe">
Structural Dynamics. Analysis of the dynamic response of structures and structural components to transient loads and foundation excitation; single-degree-of-freedom and multidegree-of-freedom systems; response spectrum concepts; simple inelastic structural systems; and introduction to systems with distributed mass and flexibility. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele14">Geographic Information Systems and Science</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele14pe">
Geographic Information Systems and Science. Investigation of geographic information systems (GIS) and science (GIScience) including theory and applications areas. A major portion of the course will be based on use of a current widely-used GIS computer software system. Aspects of geographic data entry and editing, spatial analysis, and map development and display will be considered. Relationship of GIS to the Global Positioning System (GPS) and satellite generated data will be addressed. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele15">Civil Engineering Design-II</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele15pe">
Civil Engineering Design-II. Innovation and creativity in conceptual design; sustainability; health and safety; investigative procedures. The use of analysis, synthesis and optimization in design; project planning, networks and graphs. Design of embankments, dams; drainage design; route location and alignment design of roads, assessment of natural hazard impacts and environmental impacts. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele16">Public Transportation Systems</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele16pe">
Public Transportation Systems: Public Transport: Definitions, modes of public transport and comparison, public transport travel characteristics, trip chaining, technology of bus, rail, rapid transit systems, basic operating elements; Transit Network Planning: Planning Objectives, principles, considerations, transit lines types, geometry and characteristics, transit routes and their characteristics, timed transfer networks, prediction of transit usage, evaluation of network, accessibility considerations; Transit Scheduling: Components of scheduling process, determination of service requirements, scheduling procedure, marginal ridership, crew scheduling, Transit Agency and Economics: Organizational structure of transit agency, management and personnel, transit system statistics, performance and economic measures, operations, fare structure; Design of Facilities: Design of bus stops, design of terminals principles of good layout, types of layout, depot location, twin depot concept, crew facilities and amenities. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele17">Traffic Engineering and Management</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele17pe">
Traffic Engineering and Management: Traffic Forecast: General travel forecasting principles, different methods of traffic forecast - Mechanical and analytical methods, Demand relationships, methods for future projection; Design Hourly Volume For Varying Demand Conditions: Concept of Design vehicle units and determination of PCU under mixed traffic conditions, Price-volume relationships, demand functions. Determination of design hourly volume; critical hour concept, Highway Capacity: Factors affecting capacity, level of service; Capacity studies - Capacity of different highway facilities including unsignalised and signalised intersections. Problems in Mixed Traffic flow; Case studies; Accident Analysis: Analysis of individual accidents and statistical data; Methods of representing accident rate; Factors in traffic accidents; influence of roadway and traffic conditions on traffic safety; accident coefficients; Driver strains due to roadway and traffic conditions; Traffic Flow Theory: Fundamental flow relationship and their applications, Traffic flow theories and applications, Shock waves; Queuing theory and applications; Probabilistic Aspects Of Traffic Flow: Vehicle arrivals, distribution models, gaps and headway distribution models; gap acceptance merging parameters, delay models, applications; Simulation: Fundamental principle, application of simulation techniques in traffic engineering - formulation of simulation models, Case studies. Formulation of system models. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele18">Foundation Engineering</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele18pe">
Foundation Engineering. Analysis and design of foundations, types of foundations, bearing capacity and settlement of foundations; ground movements due to construction; analysis and design of excavations, retaining walls, cuts &amp; excavations and sheet piles, slopes and underground structures.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Reference books:\n\n\n

A. Singh, Modern Geotechnical Engineering, 3rd Ed., CBS Publishers, New Delhi, 1999.\n\n\n

•B.M. Das, Principles of Foundation Engineering, 5th Ed., Thomson Asia, Singapore, 2003.\n\n\n

•N. Som, Theory and Practice of Foundation Design, Prentice Hall, New Delhi, 2003.\n\n\n

After successful completion of this course, the students would:\n\n\n

• Learn about types and purposes of different foundation systems and structures.\n\n\n

• Have an exposure to the systematic methods for designing foundations.\n\n\n

• Be able evaluate the feasibility of foundation solutions to different types of soil conditions considering the time effect on soil behaviour.\n\n\n

• Have necessary theoretical background for design and construction of foundation systems.\n\n\n
    </string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele20">Structural Analysis by Matrix Methods</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele20pe">
Structural Analysis by Matrix Methods. Analysis of truss and frame structures using flexibility and stiffness methods of matrix analysis; computer applications. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele21">Structural Mechanics</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele21pe">
Structural Mechanics. Beams under lateral load and thrust; beams on elastic foundations; virtual work and energy principles; principles of solid mechanics, stress and strain in three dimensions; static stability theory; torsion; computational methods. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele22">Reinforced Concrete</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele22pe">
Reinforced Concrete. Study of the strength, behavior, and design of reinforced concrete members subjected to moments, shear, and axial forces; extensive discussion of the influence of the material properties on behavior. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele23">Decision and Risk Analysis</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele23pe">
Decision and Risk Analysis. Development of modern statistical decision theory and risk analysis, and application of these concepts in civil engineering design and decision making; Bayesian statistical decision theory, decision tree, utility concepts, and multi-objective decision problems; modeling and analysis of uncertainties, practical risk evaluation, and formulation of risk-based design criteria, risk benefit trade-offs, and optimal decisions. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele24">Design of Concrete Structures-I</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele24pe">
Design of Concrete Structures-I. Study of the strength, behavior, and design of indeterminate reinforced concrete structures, Load and stresses, load combinations, Working stress and limit state approach. Analysis and design of sections in bending working stress and limit state method, Rectangular and T-sections, Beams with reinforcement in compression, One-way slab. Design for shear and bond, Mechanism of shear and bond failure, Design of shear using limit state concept, Development length of bars; Design of sections in torsion. Design of two-way slabs; Design of flat slab direct method; Circular slab; Slab type staircase, Placement of reinforcement in slabs; Voided slab. Design of compression members, Short column, Columns with uniaxial and bi-axial bending; Long columns, use of design charts. Design of foundation; Wall footing, Isolated and combined footing for columns. All designs to be as per the most recent BIS standards as applicable Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele25">Environmental Fluid Mechanics</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele25pe">
Environmental Fluid Mechanics. Incompressible fluid mechanics with particular emphasis on topics in analysis and applications in civil engineering areas; primary topics include principles of continuity, momentum and energy, kinematics of flow and stream functions, potential flow, laminar motion, turbulence, and boundary-layer theory. Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele26">Unsteady Open Channel Flow</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele26pe">
Unsteady Open Channel Flow: This course should discuss how to analyze for unsteady flows in open channels; Derivation of 1-D and 2-D shallow water flow equations; Consideration for non-hydrostatic pressure distribution; Basics of numerical methods: Finite Difference and Finite Element Methods; Latest shock capturing Finite Volume methods for solving 1-D and 2-D shallow water flow equations; Dambreak flow; Flood routing in large channel networks, Flood routing in compound channels; Flood routing in channels with flood plains, Surface irrigation flow modeling

Pre-Requisite: Basic course in Hydraulic Engineering
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele27">Environmental Laws and Policy</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele27pe">
Environmental Laws and Policy. Overview of environment, nature and eco system, Concept of laws and policies, Origin of environmental law, Introduction to environmental laws and policies, Environment and Governance, sustainable development and environment, understanding climate change, carbon crediting, carbon foot print etc., Introduction to trade and environment. International environmental laws, Right to Environment as Human Right, International Humanitarian Law and Environment, environment and conflicts management, Famous international protocols like Kyoto.
</string>


<string name="cvesem7ele28">Rock Mechanics</string>
<string name="cvesem7ele28pe">
Rock Mechanics. Determination of physical properties of rocks, failure criterion, rock mass classification, stress around mine openings, strain and displacement of the rock mass, rock reinforcement and support, subsidence. Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Reference books:\n\n\n

• Engineering Rock Mechanics: An Introduction to the Principles by J. A. Hudson and\n\n\n

J. P. Harrison\n\n\n

• Rock Mechanics: For Underground Mining by Barry H.G. Brady Fundamentals of Rock Mechanics, 4th Edition, John Conrad Jaeger, Neville G. W. Cook, Robert Zimmerman\n\n\n

On successful completion of this course the students will be able to:\n\n\n

• Define the properties (viz., physical, mechanical) of rocks and failure criterion of rock mass.\n\n\n

• Use engineering rock mass classification (RMR, Q-system, RQD)\n\n\n

• Analyse the stress distribution insitu and around an opening in underground structures (viz., mine openings, tunnels).\n\n\n

• Determine the relation between strain and displacement components of rockmass.\n\n\n

• Perform field Instrumentation techniques and laboratory studies. Understand the fundamentals of ground subsidence.\n\n\n
</string>

    <string name="cvesem7ele29">Earthquake Engineering</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele29pe">
Earthquake Engineering. Theory of Vibrations; Concept of inertia and damping - Types of Damping - Difference between static forces and dynamic excitation - Degrees of freedom - SDOF idealization - Equations of motion of SDOF system for mass as well as base excitation - Free vibration of SDOF system - Response to harmonic excitation - Impulse and response to unit impulse - Duhamel integral; Multiple Degree of Freedom System; Two degree of freedom system - Normal modes of vibration - Natural frequencies - Mode shapes - Introduction to MDOF systems - Decoupling of equations of motion - Concept of mode superposition (No derivations); Elements of Seismology; Causes of Earthquake - Geological faults - Tectonic plate theory - Elastic rebound - Epicentre; Hypocentre - Primary, shear and Raleigh waves - Seismogram - Magnitude and intensity of earthquakes - Magnitude and Intensity scales Spectral Acceleration - Information on some disastrous earthquakes; Response of Structures to Earthquake; Response and design spectra - Design earthquake - concept of peak acceleration - Site specific response spectrum - Effect of soil properties and damping - Liquefaction of soils - Importance of ductility - Methods of introducing ductility into RC structures Design Methodology IS 1893, IS 13920 and IS 4326 - Codal provisions - Design as per the codes - Base isolation techniques - Vibration control measures - Important points in mitigating effects of earthquake on structures Prerequisite:
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele30">Transients in Closed Conduits</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele30pe">
Transients in Closed Conduits: This course should cover key issues for understanding the unsteady flow in pipes (water hammer) and designing for surge protection; Differential equations for unsteady pipe flow, Characteristic method for solution; Formulation of boundary conditions; transients in pumping mains (power failure; pump start up); transients in penstocks of hydro-electric schemes; analysis for transient control using surge tanks; air chambers; air valves; pressure regulating valves etc.; Emphasis should be on development of computer programs for transient analysis; awareness about commercially available software for transient analysis

Pre-Requisite: Basic course in Hydraulic Engineering
</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele31">Urban Hydrology and Hydraulics</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele31pe">Urban Hydrology and Hydraulics. Hydraulic analysis and design of urban, highway, airport, and small rural watershed drainage problems; discussion of overland and drainage channel flows; hydraulics of storm-drain systems and culverts; determination of design flow; runoff for highways, airports, and urban areas; design of drainage gutters, channels, sewer networks, and culverts.

Prerequisite:

    </string>


    <string name="cvesem7ele32">Structural Analysis-II</string>
    <string name="cvesem7ele32pe">
    Structural Analysis-II. Analysis of building frames; Kani\'s, moment distribution and other methods and Approximate methods; Stiffness matrix method; Application to simple problems of beams and frames; Flexibility matrix method; Application to simple problems of beams and frames; Moving loads for determinate beams; Different load cases, Influence lines for forces for determinate beams; Influence lines for pin-jointed trusses; Influence lines for indeterminate beams using Muller Breslau principle. Influence lines for Arches and stiffening girders.

Prerequisite:

    </string>




<string name="cvsem8su1">Open Elective</string>
<string name="OEcv8">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Choose ANY ONE Subject:</font></b>\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Metro Systems and Engineering</font></b>\n\n\n

GENERAL: Overview of Metro Systems; Need for Metros; Routing studies; Basic Planning and Financials\n\n\n

CIVIL ENGINEERING-Overview and construction methods for: Elevated and underground Stations; Viaduct spans and bridges; Underground tunnels; Depots; Commercial and Service buildings. Initial Surveys &amp; Investigations; Basics of Construction Planning &amp; Management, Construction Quality &amp; Safety Systems. Traffic integration, multimodal transfers and pedestrian facilities; Environmental and social safeguards; Track systems-permanent way. Facilities Management\n\n\n

ELECTRONICS AND COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING- Signaling systems; Automatic fare collection; Operation Control Centre (OCC and BCC); SCADA and other control systems; Platform Screen Doors.\n\n\n

MECHANICAL &amp; TV + AC: Rolling stock, vehicle dynamics and structure; Tunnel Ventilation systems; Air conditioning for stations and buildings; Fire control systems; Lifts and Escalators\n\n\n

ELECTRICAL: OHE, Traction Power; Substations- TSS and ASS; Power SCADA; Standby and Back-up systems; Green buildings, Carbon credits and clear air mechanics.\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Economic Policies in India</font></b>\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Detailed contents</font></b>\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Module 1

Lecture 10 hrs.</font></b>\n\n\n

Framework of Indian Economy: National Income - Trends and Structure of National Income, Demographic Features and Indicators of Economic Growth, Development Rural-Urban Migration and issues related to Urbanization, Poverty debate and Inequality, Nature, Policy and Implications, Unemployment-Nature, Central and State Government\'s policies, policy implications, Employment trends in Organized and Unorganized Sector\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
 Module 2

     Lecture 10 hrs.</font></b>\n\n\n

Development Strategies in India: Agricultural- Pricing. Marketing and Financing of Primary Sector, Economic Reforms- Rationale of Economic Reforms, Liberalization, Privatization and Globalization of the Economy, Changing structure of India\'s Foreign Trade, Role of Public Sector- Redefining the role of Public Sector, Government Policy towards Public Sector, problems associated with Privatization, issues regarding Deregulation-Disinvestment and future of Economic Reforms\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
Module 3

     Lecture 10 hrs.</font></b>\n\n\n

The Economic Policy and Infrastructure Development: Energy and Transport, Social Infrastructure- Education, Health and Gender related issues, Social Inclusion, Issues and policies in Financing Infrastructure Development, Indian Financial System-issues of Financial Inclusion, Financial Sector Reforms-review of Monetary Policy of R.B.I. Capital Market in India.\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
Module 4

     Lecture 10 hrs.</font></b>\n\n\n

The Economic Policy and Industrial Sector: Industrial Sector in Pre-reforms period, Growth and Pattern of Industrialization, Industrial Sector in Post-reform period- growth and pattern of Micro, Small, Medium Enterprises s, problems of India\'s Industrial Exports, Labor Market- issues in Labor Market Reforms and approaches to Employment Generation.\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
     Text Books</font></b>\n\n\n

Dhingra, Ishwar C. [2006], Indian Economy, Sultan Chand and Sons, New Delhi.\n\n\n

Datt, Ruddar and Sundaram, K.P.M. [Latest edition],Indian Economy, S. Chand and Co, New Delhi.\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
        Reference Books</font>
 </b>\n\n\n

1. Brahmananda, P.R. and V.A. Panchmukhi. [2001], Ed. Development Experience in Indian Economy, Inter-state Perspective, Bookwell, New Delhi.\n\n\n

2. Gupta,S.P. [1989] Planning and Development in India: A Critique, Allied Publishers Private Limited, New Delhi.\n\n\n

 3. Bhagwati, Jagdish. [2004],In Defense of Globalization, Oxford University Press, U.K.\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="cvsem8sub2">Program Elective-IV</string>
<string name="PE4cv">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Choose ANY ONE Subject:</font></b>\n\n\n

Urban Transportation Planning: Urban morphology-\n\n\n

Urbanization and travel demand - Urban activity systems and travel patterns - Systems approach - Trip based and Activity based approach - Urban Transportation Planning - Goals,\n\n\n

Objectives and Constraints - Inventory, Model building, Forecasting and Evaluation - Study area delineation - Zoning -\n\n\n

UTP survey, Trip generation models Trip classification - productions and attractions - Trip rate analysis - Multiple regression models - Category analysis - Trip distribution models -\n\n\n

Growth factor models, Gravity model and Opportunity modes; Modal split models - Mode choice behavior - Trip end and trip interchange models - Probabilistic models - Utility functions - Logit models - Two stage model. Traffic\n\n\n

assignment - Transportation networks -\n\n\n

Minimum Path Algorithms - Assignment methods - All or Nothing assignment, Capacity\n\n\n

restrained assignment and Multi path assignment- Route-choice behavior, Land use\n\n\n

transportation models - Urban forms and structures - Location\n\n\n

models - Accessibility - Land use models - Lowry derivative models - Quick response techniques - Non-Transport solutions for transport problems; Preparation of alternative plans - Evaluation techniques - Plan implementation - Monitoring - Financing of Project - urban development planning\n\n\n

policy - Case studies. Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Geometric Design of Highways: Introduction: Classification of\n\n\n

rural highways and urban roads. Objectives and requirements of highway geometric\n\n\n

design; Design Controls: Topography, vehicle characteristics and design vehicle, driver characteristics, speed, traffic flow and capacity, levels of service, pedestrian and other facilities, environmental factors;\n\n\n

Design Elements: Sight distances, Horizontal alignment- design considerations, stability at curves, super elevation, widening, transition curves; curvature at intersections, vertical alignment - grades, ramps, design of summit and valley curves, combination of vertical and horizontal alignment including design of hair pin bends, design of expressways, IRC\n\n\n

 standards and guidelines for design problems; Cross Section\n\n\n

Elements: Right of way and width considerations, roadway, shoulders, kerbs traffic barriers, medians, frontage roads; Facilities for pedestrians, bicycles, buses and trucks, Pavement surface characteristics - types, cross slope, skid resistance, unevenness; Design Considerations: Design considerations for rural and urban arterials, freeways, and other rural and urban roads; Design Of Intersections: Characteristics and design considerations of at-grade intersections;; Rotary intersections; Grade separations and interchanges; Design of Parking lots\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Contracts Management. Contract Management - Introduction, Importance of Contracts,\n\n\n

Overview of Contract Management, Overview of Activities in Contract Management; Planning and People- Resource Management; Types of Contracts, Parties to a Contract, Contract Formation, Formulation of Contract, Contract Start-Up, Managing Relationships; Common contract clauses (Notice to proceed, rights and duties of various parties, notices to be given, Contract Duration and Price. Performance parameters, Delays, penalties and liquidated damages; Force Majeure, Suspension and Termination. Changes &amp; variations, Notices under contracts; Conventional and Alternative Dispute Resolution methods. Various Acts governing Contracts; Contract Administration and Payments- Contract Administration,\n\n\n

Payments; Contract Management in Various Situations- Contract Management in NCB Works, Contract Management in ICB Works Contracts, Contract of Supply of Goods- Design, Supply and Installation Contracts, Contract Management in Consultancy,; Managing Risks and Change- Managing Risks, Managing Change; Contract Closure and Review- Ending a Contract, Post-Implementation Review; Legal Aspects in Contract Management- Contract Management Legal View, Dispute Resolution, Integrity in Contract Management; Managing Performance- Introduction, Monitoring and\n\n\n

Measurement\n\n\n

 Physico-Chemical Processes for water and wastewater treatment. The Objective of this course is to provide an in depth understanding of physical and physico-chemical processes used for water and wastewater treatment systems and to provide capability to design such systems. Water purification in natural systems, physical processes, chemical processes and biological processes. Primary, secondary and tertiary treatment. Unit operations, unit processes. Aeration and gas transfer. Sedimentation, different types of settling, sedimentation tank design. Coagulation and flocculation, coagulation processes, stability of colloids, destabilization of colloids, destabilization in water and wastewater treatment, transport of colloidal particles, design aspects. Filtration: filtration processes, Hydraulics of flow through porous media, Rate control patterns and methods, Filter effluent quality parameters, mathematical model for deep granular filters, slow sand filtration, rapid sand filtration, precoat filtration, design aspects. Disinfection: Types of disinfectants, Kinetics of disinfection, chlorination and its theory, Design of Chlorinators. Precipitation: Hardness removal, Iron, Mn, and heavy metal removal; Adsorption, adsorption equilibria and adsorption isotherm, rates of adsorption, Sorption kinetics in batch reactors, continuous reactors, factors affecting adsorption. Ion Exchange-exchange processes, materials and reactions, methods of operation, Application, design aspects. Membrane Processes, Reverse osmosis, Ultrafiltration, Electrodyalisis\n\n\n

River Engineering: Knowledge about river behavior is essential for practicing hydraulic and\n\n\n

water resources engineers. River Morphology (Bars; Bends and Meanders, Thalweg; Braiding; Bifurcations etc.); Sediment Transport Mechanics (Bed forms, Bed Load transport, Transport of suspended sediment, Critical Shear stress, Sediment Transport Equations); Aggradation and Degradation; Local Scour at Bridge Piers and other Hydraulic Structures. Measurements in Rivers (Stage measurements, Channel geometry, Discharge, Sediment samplers and suspended and bed load measurement), Physical river Models (fixed and\n\n\n

 movable bed models; sectional models, distorted Models), Mathematical models for aggradations, degradation and local scour, River Protection and Training Works (Revetments, Dikes, Gabions, Spurs, Bank Protective measures and Bed control structures), Design of river training and flood protection structures, Diversion and Cofferdams; River regulations systems; Dredging and Disposal, River restoration\n\n\n

Water Resources Field Methods. Scientific principles of measurement technologies and protocols used for water-resources measurements and experimental design of field-scale water-resources and environmental studies. Planning field studies; instruments and protocols for surface-water, ground-water, and water-quality sampling; description of data quality. One-half-day laboratory field trips to streamflow monitoring stations and groundwater monitoring wells nearby.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Design of Concrete Structures-II. Design of continuous beams and building frames, Moment redistribution, Estimation of wind and seismic loads, Desirable features of earthquake resistant construction, Detailing for earthquake resistant construction - ductility criteria; Water tank and staging; Introduction, Design criteria, Design of rectangular and circular water tank, Design of Intze tank, Staging for overhead tank; Introduction to bridge engineering, Investigation for bridges, IRC loadings, Design of slab culvert; Design of Masonry walls and columns; Prestressed concrete, Introduction, pre-stressing system, losses in pre-stress, Design of simple span girders, Design of end block; Design of staircases; Design of cantilever and counterforte type retaining wall; All design steps/process to as per the most recent BIS code of practices Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Prestressed Concrete. Study of strength, behavior, and design\n\n\n

of prestressed reinforced concrete members and structures, with primary emphasis on pretensioned, precast\n\n\n

 construction; emphasis on the necessary coordination between design and construction techniques in prestressing.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Geotechnical Design. Subsurface site evaluation; integrated design of retaining walls, foundations, pavements, and materials for airports, highways, dams, or other facilities.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Reference books:\n\n\n

• Analysis and Design of Substructures: Limit State Design by Swami Saran\n\n\n

Upon completion of the course, the student would be:\n\n\n

• Well acquainted with the various investigation specifications as per the infrastructure to be build on the proposed site.\n\n\n

 •knowing about the properties of materials required for the constructing a desired infrastructure\n\n\n

familiar with design concepts of various foundation systems familiar with design of transportation facilities\n\n\n

Systems Engineering &amp; Economics: Introduction to the formulation and solution of civil engineering problems. Major topics are: engineering economy, mathematical modeling, and optimization. Techniques, including classical optimization, linear and nonlinear programming, network theory, critical path methods, simulation, decision theory, and dynamic programming are applied to a variety of civil engineering problems. Prerequisite:\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem8sub3">Program Elective-V</string>
<string name="PE5cv">\n\n\n

     Choose ANY ONE Subject:\n\n\n

Intelligent Transportation Systems: Introduction to Intelligent Transportation Systems\n\n\n

(ITS) Definition of ITS and Identification of ITS Objectives, Historical Background, Benefits of ITSITS Data collection techniques - Detectors, Automatic Vehicle Location (AVL), Automatic Vehicle Identification (AVI), Geographic Information Systems (GIS), video data collection. Telecommunications in ITS - Importance of telecommunications in the ITS system, Information Management, Traffic Management Centres (TMC). Vehicle - Road\n\n\n

side communication - Vehicle Positioning System; ITS functional areas - Advanced Traffic\n\n\n

Management Systems (ATMS), Advanced Traveler Information Systems (ATIS). Commercial Vehicle Operations (CVO), Advanced Vehicle Control Systems (AVCS), Advanced Public Transportation Systems (APTS), Advanced Rural Transportation Systems (ARTS); ITS User Needs and Services - Travel and Traffic management, Public nager Transportation Management, Electronic Payment, Commercial Vehicle Operations, Emergency Management, Advanced Vehicle safety systems, Information Management; Automated Highway Systems - Vehicles in Platoons - Integration of Automated Highway Systems. ITS Programs in the World - Overview of ITS implementations in developed countries, ITS in developing countries.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Pavement Materials. Soil - Classification, characteristics, compaction, evaluation of soil\n\n\n

strength; stabilized pavement materials; Aggregates: requirements, properties and tests on road aggregates for flexible and rigid pavements. Bitumen: Origin, preparation, properties and tests, constitution of bituminous road binders; requirements; Criterion for selection of different binders. Bituminous Emulsions and Cutbacks: Preparation, characteristics, uses and tests, Bituminous Mixes: Mechanical properties: Resilient modulus, dynamic modulus and fatigue characteristics of bituminous mixes. bituminous mix design methods and\n\n\n

 specifications. Weathering and Durability of Bituminous\n\n\n

Materials and Mixes. Performance\n\n\n

based Bitumen Specifications; Superpave mix design method:\n\n\n

design example problems. Cement Concrete for Pavement Construction: Requirements, and design of mix for CC pavement, IRC and IS specifications and tests, joint filler and sealer materials. Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Basics of Computational Hydraulics. Derivation of governing equations for flow and transport in surface and sub-surface (saturated and unsaturated flow); Equations for reactive transport, Coupled surface and sub-surface flow models; Basics of finite difference, finite element and finite volume methods (consistency, stability, convergence, order of accuracy, computational efficiency); application of numerical methods for solving flow and transport equations, fully coupled and iteratively coupled models; Model simplification, Parameter estimation (Model calibration and validation), Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) software for three-dimensional turbulent flow modeling, Software for sub-surface flow simulation\n\n\n

Port and Harbour Engineering: Harbour Planning: Types of\n\n\n

water transportation, water transportation in India, requirements of ports and harbours, classification of harbours, selection of site and planning of harbours, location of harbour, traffic estimation, master plan, ship characteristics, harbour design, turning basin, harbour entrances, type of docks, its location and number, Site investigations - hydrographic survey, topographic survey, soil investigations, current observations, tidal observations; Docks and Repair Facilities: Design and construction of breakwaters, berthing structures - jetties, fenders, piers, wharves, dolphins, trestle, moles, Harbour docks, use of wet docks, design of wet docks, repair docks, lift docks, dry docks, keel and bilge blocking, construction of dry docks, gates for dry docks, pumping plant, floating docks, slipways, locks, size of lock, lock gates, types of gates;\n\n\n

Navigational Aids: Requirements of signals, fixed navigation structures, necessity of\n\n\n

 navigational aids, light houses, beacon lights, floating navigational aids, light ships, buoys, radar, Dredging and Coastal Protection: Classification, types of dredgers, choice of dredger, uses of dredged materials, coastal erosion and protection, sea wall, revetment, bulkhead, coastal zone and beach profile; Port facilities: Port development, port planning, port building facilities, transit sheds, warehouses, cargo handling facilities, container handling terminal facilities, shipping terminals, inland port facilities. Inland waterways, Inland water transportation in India, classification of waterways, economics of inland waterways transportation, national waterways.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Railway Engineering. Railway track gauge, alignment of railway lines, engineering surveys and construction of new lines, tracks and track stresses; rails, sleepers; ballast; subgrade and formation, rack fittings and fastenings, creep of rails, geometric design of track, curves and super-elevation, points and crossings, track junctions and simple track layouts; rail joints and welding of rails; track maintenance, track drainage; modern methods of track maintenance, rehabilitation and renewal of track; tractive resistance and power, railway stations and yards; railway tunneling; signaling and interlocking; maintenance of railways and high speed trains.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Structural Geology. Description, classification, and origin of earth structures. Ways in which the continental crust can deform; link scales of structure from the field, outcrops, hand specimen, thin section by integrating analytical techniques with practical examples. Theoretical and meso to microscale analysis of structures developed through a linked series of lectures and practicals; practical 2D strain analysis; 3D strain concepts; incremental strain, kinematics and polyphase deformations; fold construction and classes; fault evolution and section balancing; fault rock microstructures; fault and fold mechanics, current concepts in plate tectonics, cross-section construction techniques, structural interpretation of seismic data, structural styles in different tectonic settings (thrust and\n\n\n

 fold belts, rifts, strike and slip,\n\n\n

gravity tectonics, inversion), structural geology of reservoir\n\n\n

units.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Reference books:\n\n\n

Ghosh, S.K., Structural Geology: Fundamentals and Modern Developments, Elsevier;\n\n\n

First edition\n\n\n

On successful completion of this course the students will be able to:\n\n\n

• Acquire knowledge on the geometry and type of structures present in earth.\n\n\n

• Understand and describe the features formed in rocks when subjected to stress.\n\n\n

• Understand the impact of structural geology to active tectonic settings\n\n\n

• Understand micro and macro scale deformation mechanisms (viz., brittle, ductile).\n\n\n

• Portray 2D and 3D strain analysis for various deformation behaviours.\n\n\n

• Interpret graphs and models used in structural geology to understand and demonstrate poly phase deformations.\n\n\n

Design of Steel Structures. Properties of materials; loads and stresses, Design of semi-rigid,\n\n\n

rigid and moment resistant connections; Built-up sections Design of tension members\n\n\n

subjected to axial tension and bending, splicing of tension member, Design of compression members, Beam-column connections, Design of columns and their bases Design of flexural members and Plate girder; loads, specification and design Industrial buildings; loads, design of purlins, trusses, bracings; gantry girders; Introduction to Plastic analysis; Simple cases of beams and frames; All design steps/process to as per the most recent BIS code of practices\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Civil Engineering Design-I. Concept of design and its\n\n\n

contribution to the quality of life; Civil Engineering Design, the role of geomatics, the environment, and scientific laws in design; Introduction to the design of buildings and Civil Engineering Infrastructure, site appraisal; Risk and vulnerability in design; Health and safety in Civil Engineering Design,\n\n\n

 environmental impact assessment, Civil Engineering drawing, CAD techniques, introduction to GIS techniques.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Industrial Structures. Industrial steel building frames: Types\n\n\n

of frames, bracing, crane girders and columns, workshop sheds, trussed bents, Pressed steel tank, circular tank; Transmission and Communication towers: Types and configuration, Analysis and design; Chimneys, Loads and stresses in chimney shaft, Earthquake and wind effect, Stresses due to temperature difference, combined effect of loads and temperature, temperature. Design of chimney, Silos and Bunkers; Jassen\'s theory, Airy\'s theory, Shallow and deep bins, Rectangular bunkers with slopping bottom, Rectangular bunkers with high side walls; Steel stacks; introduction, force acting on a steel stack, design consideration, design example of stacks; Concrete Shell Structures: Folded plate and cylindrical shell structures; Introduction, structural behaviour of long and short shells, beam and arch action, analysis and design of cylindrical shell structures, Analysis and design of folded plates; Machine foundations; introduction, machine vibration, structural design of foundation to rotary machines, impact machines, vibration characteristics, design consideration of foundation to impact machine, grillage, pile and raft foundation. Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Construction Cost Analysis. Introduction to the application of scientific principles to costs\n\n\n

and estimates of costs in construction engineering; concepts and statistical measurements of the factors involved in direct costs, general overhead costs, cost markups and profits; and the fundamentals of cost recording for construction cost accounts and cost controls. Prerequisite:\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem8sub4">Program Elective-VI</string>
<string name="PE6cv">\n\n\n

    Choose ANY ONE Subject:\n\n\n

Hydraulic Modeling: The main objective of this course is to\n\n\n

introduce various concepts which will help in designing physical hydraulic models. Basics\n\n\n

of Hydraulic Modelling (similarity mechanics, model laws, distinction between numerical and hydraulic models,\n\n\n

classification of hydraulic modelling, materials used in the model, scale effect, design, construction, operation and interpretation of the results); Role of instrumentation and data processing, Gravity dominated models (modelling of energy Gravity friction models: (pumped flow models, ship models,\n\n\n

dissipaters, overflow spillways, siphon spillways, bridge piers, vortex formation, cavitation, flow induced vibrations);\n\n\n

surge tank models); Friction dominated models; River models with fixed and mobile bed; Basin and reservoir models; Tidal models with fixed and mobile bed; estuarine models; harbor and breakwater models, models of offshore structures; Hybrid and Analogue models;
\n\n\n
Scope and limitations of\n\n\n

hydraulic modelling, complementary aspects of numerical and\n\n\n

hydraulic modelling.
\n\n\n
Biological processes for contaminant removal. Understanding of basics of microbiology,\n\n\n

metabolism and energetic, bio kinetic parameter, reactors and reactor analyses.
\n\n\n
Characterization of waste. Aerobic, anaerobic and anoxic systems. Suspended and attached\n\n\n

growth biological systems. Activated Sludge processand process modifications, Process design considerations, Treatment Ponds and aerated Lagoons, aerobic pond, facultative pond, anaerobic ponds, polishing ponds, constructed wet lands etc.
\n\n\n
Attached Growth Biological Treatment Systems, Trickling Filters, Rotating Biological Contactors, Activated Biofilters, Moving bed biological reactor (MBBR), Sequential Batch reactors (SBR), Membrane Biological Reactors (MBR) etc. Anaerobic processes, Process fundamentals, Standard, high rate and hybrid reactors, Anaerobic filters, Expanded/fluidized bed reactors, Upflow\n\n\n

anaerobic sludge blanket reactors, Performance and design aspects, Expanded granular bed\n\n\n

 reactors, Two stage/phase anaerobic reactors. Siuage Digestion, anaerobic digestion, aerobic digestion\n\n\n

Rural water supply and onsite sanitation systems. Attributes of water supply systems, drinking water quality. Relationships between diseases and water quality, hygiene and sanitation. Need for water treatment. Point of use water treatment systems, filters, bio-sand filters, disinfection systems for rural areas, chlorination, Solar disinfection systems, removal\n\n\n

of arsenic, fluoride and iron. Onsite sanitation systems: Nexus between water quality and\n\n\n

sanitation. Importance of hydrogeology on selection of onsite sanitation systems, Design of\n\n\n

Septic tanks, single pit and double pit toilets. Small bore systems, bio digesters, reed beds, constructed wetlands, sludge/septage management systems.\n\n\n

Construction Engineering Materials. Design, production, application, specification, and quality control of construction materials unique to civil engineering. Stones, bricks, mortars, Plain, Reinforced &amp; Prestressed Concrete, Construction Chemicals; Structural Steel, High Tensile Steel, Carbon Composites; Plastics in Construction; 3D printing; Recycling of Construction &amp; Demolition wastes Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Solid and hazardous waste management. Solid Wastes:\n\n\n

Origin, Analysis, Composition and Characteristics. Integrated Solid Waste Management System: Collection, Storage, Segregation, Reuse and Recycling possibilities, Transportation, Treatment/Processing and Transformation Techniques, Final Disposal. Management of: Municipal, Biomedical, Nuclear, Electronic and Industrial Solid Wastes and the rules and regulations. Introduction to Hazardous wastes, Definition of Hazardous waste, The magnitude of the problem; Hazardous\n\n\n

waste: Risk assessment, Environmental legislation, Characterization and site assessment, Waste minimization and resource recovery, Transportation of hazardous waste, Physical, chemical and biological treatment, Ground water contamination, Landfill disposal, Current\n\n\n

 Management Practices, Environmental audit, Pollution Prevention, Facility Development and operation, Site Remediation: Quantitative risk assessment, site and subsurface characterization, Containment, remedial alternatives.\n\n\n

Bridge Engineering. General, classification of bridges, site\n\n\n

selection, geometric and hydraulic design consideration, loading standards for highway and railway bridges, general design consideration; optimum spans; Concrete bridges: culverts; Slab, T-beam, box girder bridges, balanced cantilever bridge, cable stayed bridge, extrados bridges; arch bridge; Special requirements for Prestressed Concrete bridges; Steel bridges: plate girder bridge, truss bridge, suspension cable bridge, cable stayed bridge, Substructures: design of piers and abutments, pile and well foundations, bearings and expansion joints, special wearing coats; seismic design considerations; Aerodynamic stability considerations; special durability measures; provisions for inspection and maintenance;\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Design of Structural Systems. The whole structural design\n\n\n

process including definition of functional requirements, selection of structural scheme, formulation of design criteria, preliminary and computer-aided proportioning, and analysis of response, cost, and value.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

Offshore Engineering. Introduction to offshore structures, codes of practice, offshore\n\n\n

project management, deep water, offshore site investigations, geophysical methods; offshore sediment sampling, in-situ testing, geological aspects; development of design stratigraphies.\n\n\n

Prerequisite:\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="cvsem8sub5">Project-II</string>
<string name="project2cv8">Project-II</string>



</resources>