<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

<string name="eeesem1sub2">Mathematics-I(Calculus and Differential Equation)</string>
  <string name="EEEmath">\n\n\n

      <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:3 T:1 P:0 Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n

      <b>CONTENTS</b>\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1:

     CALCULUS (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EVOLUTES AND INVOLUTES; EVALUATION OF DEFINITE AND IMPROPER INTEGRALS; BETA AND GAMMA FUNCTIONS AND THEIR PROPERTIES; APPLICATIONS OF DEFINITE INTEGRALS TO EVALUATE SURFACE AREAS AND VOLUMES OF REVOLUTIONS. ROLLES THEOREM, MEAN VALUE THEOREMS, TAYLORS AND MACLAURIN THEOREMS WITH REMAINDERS; INDETERMINATE FORMS AND L HOSPITAL RULE; MAXIMA AND MINIMA.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2:

     SEQUENCES AND SERIES (7 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

CONVERGENCE OF SEQUENCE AND SERIES, TESTS FOR CONVERGENCE, POWER SERIES, TAYLORS SERIES. SERIES FOR EXPONENTIAL, TRIGONOMETRIC AND LOGARITHMIC FUNCTIONS; FOURIER SERIES: HALF RANGE SINE AND COSINE SERIES, PARSEVALS THEOREM.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3:

     MULTIVARIABLE CALCULUS: DIFFERENTIATION (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

LIMIT, CONTINUITY AND PARTIAL DERIVATIVES, DIRECTIONAL DERIVATIVES, TOTAL DERIVATIVE; TANGENT PLANE AND NORMAL LINE; ΜΑΧΙΜΑ, MINIMA AND SADDLE POINTS; METHOD OF LAGRANGE MULTIPLIERS; GRADIENT, CURL AND DIVERGENCE.\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4:

      MULTIVARIABLE CALCULUS: INTEGRATION (7 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

MULTIPLE INTEGRATION: DOUBLE AND TRIPLE INTEGRALS (CARTESIAN AND POLAR), CHANGE OF ORDER OF INTEGRATION IN DOUBLE INTEGRALS, CHANGE OF VARIABLES (CARTESIAN TO POLAR), APPLICATIONS: AREAS AND VOLUMES BY (DOUBLE INTEGRATION) CENTER OF MASS AND GRAVITY (CONSTANT AND VARIABLE DENSITIES). THEOREMS OF GREEN, GAUSS AND STOKES, ORTHOGONAL CURVILINEAR COORDINATES, SIMPLE APPLICATIONS INVOLVING CUBES, SPHERE AND RECTANGULAR PARALLELEPIPEDS.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5:

     FIRST ORDER ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS (3 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EXACT, LINEAR AND BERNOULLI EQUATIONS, EULER EQUATIONS, EQUATIONS NOT OF FIRST DEGREE: EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR P, EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR Y, EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR X AND CLAIRAUTS TYPE.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6:

     ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS OF HIGHER ORDER (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

SECOND ORDER LINEAR DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS WITH VARIABLE COEFFICIENTS, METHOD OF VARIATION OF PARAMETERS, CAUCHY-EULER EQUATION; POWER SERIES SOLUTIONS; LEGENDRE POLYNOMIALS, BESSEL FUNCTIONS OF THE FIRST KIND AND THEIR PROPERTIES.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 7:

     PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS: FIRST ORDER (3 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

FIRST ORDER PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, SOLUTIONS OF FIRST ORDER LINEAR AND NON-LINEAR PDES.\n\n\n

      <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXT/REFERENCES:</font>
      </b>
      \n\n\n

~G.B. THOMAS AND R.L. FINNEY, CALCULUS AND ANALYTIC GEOMETRY, PEARSON, 2002.\n\n\n

~T. VEERARAJAN, ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, MCGRAW-HILL, NEW DELHI, 2008.\n\n\n

~ B. V. RAMANA, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, MCGRAW HILL, NEW DELHI, 2010.\n\n\n

~N.P. BALI AND M. GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, 2010.\n\n\n

~B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 2000.\n\n\n

~E. KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n

~W. E. BOYCE AND R. C. DIPRIMA, ELEMENTARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS AND BOUNDARY VALUE PROBLEMS, WILEY INDIA, 2009.\n\n\n

~S. L. ROSS, DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, WILEY INDIA, 1984.\n\n\n

~ E. A. CODDINGTON, AN INTRODUCTION TO ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, PRENTICE HALL INDIA, 1995.\n\n\n

~E. L. INCE, ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, DOVER PUBLICATIONS, 1958.\n\n\n

~G.F. SIMMONS AND S.G. KRANTZ, DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, MCGRAW HILL, 2007.\n\n\n
  </string>


    <string name="eeesem2sub3">Mathrmatics-II(Linear Algebra, Transform Calculus and Numerical Methods)</string>
    <string name="eeemath2">\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> L:3 T:1 P:0 Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1:

    MATRICES (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

ALGEBRA OF MATRICES, INVERSE AND RANK OF A MATRIX, RANK-NULLITY THEOREM; SYSTEM OF LINEAR EQUATIONS; SYMMETRIC, SKEW-SYMMETRIC AND ORTHOGONAL MATRICES; DETERMINANTS; EIGENVALUES AND EIGENVECTORS; DIAGONALIZATION OF MATRICES; CAYLEY-HAMILTON THEOREM, ORTHOGONAL TRANSFORMATION AND QUADRATIC TO CANONICAL FORMS.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2:

    NUMERICAL METHODS-I (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

SOLUTION OF POLYNOMIAL AND TRANSCENDENTAL EQUATIONS - BISECTION METHOD, NEWTON-RAPHSON METHOD AND REGULA-FALSI METHOD. FINITE DIFFERENCES, INTERPOLATION USING NEWTON\'S FORWARD AND BACKWARD DIFFERENCE FORMULAE. CENTRAL DIFFERENCE INTERPOLATION: GAUSS\'S FORWARD AND BACKWARD FORMULAE. NUMERICAL INTEGRATION: TRAPEZOIDAL RULE AND SIMPSON\'S 1/3RD AND 3/8 RULES.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3:

    NUMERICAL METHODS-II (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS: TAYLORS SERIES, EULER AND MODIFIED EULERS METHODS. RUNGE- KUTTA METHOD OF FOURTH ORDER FOR SOLVING FIRST AND SECOND ORDER EQUATIONS. MILNE\'S AND ADAM\'S PREDICATOR-CORRECTOR METHODS. PARTIAL DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS: FINITE DIFFERENCE SOLUTION TWO DIMENSIONAL LAPLACE EQUATION AND POISSON EQUATION, IMPLICIT AND EXPLICIT METHODS FOR ONE DIMENSIONAL HEAT EQUATION (BENDER-SCHMIDT AND CRANK-NICHOLSON METHODS), FINITE DIFFERENCE EXPLICIT METHOD FOR WAVE EQUATION.\n\n\n

     <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>   MODULE 4:

         TRANSFORM CALCULUS (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

LAPLACE TRANSFORM, PROPERTIES OF LAPLACE TRANSFORM, LAPLACE TRANSFORM OF PERIODIC FUNCTIONS. FINDING INVERSE LAPLACE TRANSFORM BY DIFFERENT METHODS, CONVOLUTION THEOREM. EVALUATION OF INTEGRALS BY LAPLACE TRANSFORM, SOLVING ODES AND PDES BY LAPLACE TRANSFORM METHOD. FOURIER TRANSFORMS.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TEXT/REFERENCES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~D. POOLE, LINEAR ALGEBRA: A MODERN INTRODUCTION, BROOKS/COLE, 2005. ~ N.P. BALI AND M. GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, 2008. B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 2010. ~ V. KRISHNAMURTHY, V. P. MAINRA AND J. L. ARORA, AN INTRODUCTION TO LINEAR ALGEBRA, AFFILIATED EAST-WEST PRESS, 2005.\n\n\n
    </string>


    <string name="eeesem2sub4">Physics(Waves and Optics And Introduction to Quantum Mechanics)</string>
<string name="phyeee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  L:3 T:1 P:3

        Credit:5.5</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> CONTENTS</font></b>\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 1:

     WAVES (3 LECTURES)</font>
 </b>\n\n\n

MECHANICAL AND ELECTRICAL SIMPLE HARMONIC OSCILLATORS, DAMPED HARMONIC OSCILLATOR, FORCED MECHANICAL AND ELECTRICAL OSCILLATORS, IMPEDANCE, STEADY STATE MOTION OF FORCED DAMPED HARMONIC OSCILLATOR\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 2:

     NON-DISPERSIVE TRANSVERSE AND LONGITUDINAL WAVES (4 LECTURES) </font></b>\n\n\nTRANSVERSE WAVE ON A STRING, THE WAVE EQUATION ON A STRING, HARMONIC WAVES, REFLECTION AND TRANSMISSION OF WAVES AT A BOUNDARY, IMPEDANCE MATCHING, STANDING WAVES AND THEIR EIGEN FREQUENCIES, LONGITUDINAL WAVES AND THE WAVE EQUATION FOR THEM, ACOUSTICS WAVES\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 3:

     LIGHT AND OPTICS (3 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

LIGHT AS AN ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVE AND FRESNEL EQUATIONS, REFLECTANCE AND TRANSMITTANCE, BREWSTER\'S ANGLE, TOTAL INTERNAL REFLECTION, AND EVANESCENT WAVE. MIRRORS AND LENSES AND OPTICAL INSTRUMENTS BASED ON THEM\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 4:

      WAVE OPTICS (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

HUYGENS\' PRINCIPLE, SUPERPOSITION OF WAVES AND INTERFERENCE OF LIGHT BY WAVEFRONT SPLITTING AND AMPLITUDE SPLITTING; YOUNG\'S DOUBLE SLIT EXPERIMENT, NEWTON\'S RINGS, MICHELSON INTERFEROMETER, MACH ZEHNDER INTERFEROMETER. FARUNHOFER DIFFRACTION FROM A SINGLE SLIT AND A CIRCULAR APERTURE, THE RAYLEIGH CRITERION FOR LIMIT OF RESOLUTION AND ITS APPLICATION TO VISION; DIFFRACTION GRATINGS AND THEIR RESOLVING POWER\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 5:

     LASERS (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EINSTEIN\'S THEORY OF MATTER RADIATION INTERACTION AND A AND B COEFFICIENTS; AMPLIFICATION OF LIGHT BY POPULATION INVERSION, DIFFERENT TYPES OF LASERS: GAS LASERS (HE-NE, CO2), SOLID-STATE LASERS (RUBY, NEODYMIUM), DYE LASERS; PROPERTIES OF LASER BEAMS: MONO-CHROMATICITY\n\n\n
 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 6:

     INTRODUCTION TO QUANTUM MECHANICS (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

WAVE NATURE OF PARTICLES, TIME-DEPENDENT AND TIME-INDEPENDENT SCHRODINGER EQUATION FOR WAVE FUNCTION, BORN INTERPRETATION, PROBABILITY CURRENT, EXPECTATION VALUES, FREE-PARTICLE WAVE FUNCTION AND WAVE-PACKETS, UNCERTAINTY PRINCIPLE.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 7:

     SOLUTION OF WAVE EQUATION (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

SOLUTION OF STATIONARY-STATE SCHRODINGER EQUATION FOR ONE DIMENSIONAL PROBLEMS-PARTICLE IN A BOX, PARTICLE IN ATTRACTIVE DELTA-FUNCTION POTENTIAL, SQUARE-WELL POTENTIAL, LINEAR HARMONIC OSCILLATOR. SCATTERING FROM A POTENTIAL BARRIER AND TUNNELING; RELATED EXAMPLES LIKE ALPHA- DECAY, FIELD-IONIZATION AND SCANNING TUNNELING MICROSCOPE, TUNNELING IN SEMICONDUCTOR STRUCTURES. THREE-DIMENSIONAL PROBLEMS: PARTICLE IN THREE DIMENSIONAL BOX AND RELATED EXAMPLES.\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 8:

      INTRODUCTION TO SOLIDS AND SEMICONDUCTORS (9 LECTURES)</font></b>
    \n\n\n

FREE ELECTRON THEORY OF METALS, FERMI LEVEL, DENSITY OF STATES IN 1, 2 AND 3 DIMENSIONS, BLOCH\'S THEOREM FOR PARTICLES IN A PERIODIC POTENTIAL, KRONIG-PENNEY MODEL AND ORIGIN OF ENERGY BANDS. TYPES OF ELECTRONIC MATERIALS: METALS, SEMICONDUCTORS, AND INSULATORS. INTRINSIC AND EXTRINSIC SEMICONDUCTORS, DEPENDENCE OF FERMI LEVEL ON CARRIER-CONCENTRATION AND TEMPERATURE (EQUILIBRIUM CARRIER STATISTICS), CARRIER GENERATION AND RECOMBINATION, CARRIER TRANSPORT: DIFFUSION AND DRIFT, P-N JUNCTION.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> TEXT/REFERENCES:</font>
    </b>\n\n\n

~G. MAIN, VIBRATIONS AND WAVES IN PHYSICS, CAMBRIDGE UNIVERSITY PRESS, 1993.\n\n\n

~H. J. PAIN, THE PHYSICS OF VIBRATIONS AND WAVES, WILEY, 2006.\n\n\n

~E. HECHT, OPTICS, PEARSON EDUCATION, 2008.\n\n\n

~ A. GHATAK, OPTICS, MCGRAW HILL EDUCATION, 2012.\n\n\n

~O. SVELTO, PRINCIPLES OF LASERS, SPRINGER SCIENCE and BUSINESS MEDIA, 2010.\n\n\n

~ D. J. GRIFFITHS, QUANTUM MECHANICS, PEARSON EDUCATION, 2014.\n\n\n

~R. ROBINETT, QUANTUM MECHANICS, OUP OXFORD, 2006.\n\n\n

~ D. MCQUARRIE, UANTUM CHEMISTRY, UNIVERSITY SCIENCE BOOKS, 2007.\n\n\n

~D. A. NEAMEN, SEMICONDUCTOR PHYSICS AND DEVICES, TIMES MIRROR HIGH EDUCATION GROUP, CHICAGO, 1997.\n\n\n

~E.S. YANG, MICROELECTRONIC DEVICES, MCGRAW HILL, SINGAPORE, 1988.\n\n\n

~B.G. STREETMAN, SOLID STATE ELECTRONIC DEVICES, PRENTICE HALL OF INDIA, 1995\n\n\n
</string>


    <string name="eeesem3sub1">Electrical Circuit AnaLysis</string>
<string name="ECA">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>3L:1T:0P 4 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

~ Apply network theorems for the analysis of electrical circuits.\n\n\n

~ Obtain the transient and steady-state response of electrical circuits.\n\n\n

~ Analyse circuits in the sinusoidal steady-state (single-phase and three-phase)

Analyse two port circuit behavior.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:

     Network Theorems (10 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Superposition theorem, Thevenin theorem, Norton theorem, Maximum power transfer theorem, Reciprocity theorem, Compensation theorem. Analysis with dependent current and voltage sources. Node and Mesh Analysis. Concept of duality and dual networks.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:

     Solution of First and Second order networks (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Solution of first and second order differential equations for Series and parallel R-L, R-C, R-L-C circuits, initial and final conditions in network elements, forced and free response, time constants, steady state and transient state response.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:

     Sinusoidal steady state analysis (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Representation of sine function as rotating phasor, phasor diagrams, impedances and admittances, AC circuit analysis, effective or RMS values, average power and complex power. Three-phase circuits. Mutual coupled circuits, Dot Convention in coupled circuits, Ideal Transformer.\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:

      Electrical Circuit Analysis Using Laplace Transforms (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Review of Laplace Transform, Analysis of electrical circuits using Laplace Transform for standard inputs, convolution integral, inverse Laplace transform, transformed network with initial conditions. Transfer function representation. Poles and Zeros. Frequency response (magnitude and phase plots), series and parallel resonances\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:

     Two Port Network and Network Functions (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Two Port Networks, terminal pairs, relationship of two port variables, impedance parameters, admittance parameters, transmission parameters and hybrid parameters, interconnections of two port networks.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. M. E. Van Valkenburg, "Network Analysis", Prentice Hall, 2006.\n\n\n

2. D. Roy Choudhury, "Networks and Systems", New Age International Publications, 1998.\n\n\n

3. W. H. Hayt and J. E. Kemmerly, "Engineering Circuit Analysis", McGraw Hill Education, 2013.\n\n\n

4. C. K. Alexander and M. N. O. Sadiku, "Electric Circuits", McGraw Hill Education, 2004.\n\n\n

5. K. V. V. Murthy and M. S. Kamath, "Basic Circuit Analysis", Jaico Publishers, 1999.\n\n\n


</string>


    <string name="eeesem3sub3">Electrical Machines-I</string>
<string name="Emeee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>3L:0T:0P 3 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Magnetic fields and magnetic circuits (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Review of magnetic circuits - MMF, flux, reluctance, inductance; review of Ampere Law and Biot Savart Law, Visualization of magnetic fields produced by a bar magnet and a current carrying coil - through air and through a combination of iron and air; influence of highly permeable materials on the magnetic flux lines.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Electromagnetic force and torque (9 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

B-H curve of magnetic materials; flux-linkage vs current characteristic of magnetic circuits; linear and nonlinear magnetic circuits; energy stored in the magnetic circuit; force as a partial derivative of stored energy with respect to position of a moving element; torque as a partial derivative of stored energy with respect to angular position of a rotating element. Examples - galvanometer coil, relay contact, lifting magnet, rotating element with eccentricity or saliency\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: DC machines (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Basic construction of a DC machine, magnetic structure - stator yoke, stator poles, pole-faces or shoes, air gap and armature core, visualization of magnetic field produced by the field winding excitation with armature winding open, air gap flux density distribution, flux per pole, induced EMF in an armature coil. Armature winding and commutation - Elementary armature coil and commutator, lap and wave windings, construction of commutator, linear commutation Derivation of back EMF equation, armature MMF wave, derivation of torque equation, armature reaction, air gap flux density distribution with armature reaction.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: DC machine - motoring and generation (7 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Armature circuit equation for motoring and generation, Types of field excitations - separately excited, shunt and series. Open circuit characteristic of separately excited DC generator, back EMF with armature reaction, voltage build-up in a shunt generator, critical field resistance and critical speed. V-I characteristics and torque-speed characteristics of separately excited, shunt and series motors. Speed control through armature voltage. Losses, load testing and back-to-back testing of DC machines\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Module 5: Transformers (12 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Principle, construction and operation of single-phase transformers, equivalent circuit, phasor diagram, voltage regulation, losses and efficiency Testing - open circuit and short circuit tests, polarity test, back-to-back test, separation of hysteresis and eddy current losses Three-phase transformer - construction, types of connection and their comparative features, Parallel operation of single-phase and three-phase transformers, Autotransformers - construction, principle, applications and comparison with two winding transformer, Magnetizing current, effect of nonlinear B-H curve of magnetic core material, harmonics in magnetization current, Phase conversion - Scott connection, three-phase to six-phase conversion, Tap-changing transformers - No-load and on-load tap-changing of transformers, Three-winding transformers. Cooling of transformers.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References</font></b>\n\n\n

1. A. E. Fitzgerald and C. Kingsley, Electric Machinery", New York, McGraw Hill Education, 2013.\n\n\n

2. A. E. Clayton and N. N. Hancock, "Performance and design of DC machines", CBS Publishers, 2004.\n\n\n

3. M. G. Say, "Performance and design of AC machines", CBS Publishers, 2002.\n\n\n

4. P. S. Bimbhra, "Electrical Machinery", Khanna Publishers, 2011.\n\n\n

5. I. J. Nagrath and D. P. Kothari, "Electric Machines", McGraw Hill Education, 2010.\n\n\n

 PCC-EE05: Electrical Machines Laboratory-1 (0:0:2-1 credit)\n\n\n

Hands-on experiments related to the course contents of EE04.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="eeesem3sub4">Electrical Machines Laboratory-I</string>
<string name="EML">Check Electrical Machines Module</string>

    <string name="eeesem3sub5">Electromagnetic Fields</string>
    <string name="EF">\n\n\n <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>3L:1T:0P 4 Credit</font>
    </b>
        \n\n\n

       <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:

           Review of Vector Calculus (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Vector algebra-addition, subtraction, components of vectors, scalar and vector multiplications, triple products, three orthogonal coordinate systems (rectangular, cylindrical and spherical). Vector calculus-differentiation, partial differentiation, integration, vector operator del, gradient, divergence a nd curl;integraltheorems of vectors. Conversion of a vector from one coordinate system to an other.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:

Static Electric Field

    (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Coulomb\'s law, Electric field intensity, Electrical field due to point charges. Line, Surface and Volume charge distributions. Gauss law and its applications. Absolute Electric potential, Potential difference, Calculation of potential differences for different configurations. Electric dipole, Electrostatic Energy and Energy density.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:

    Conductors, Dielectrics and Capacitance (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Current and current density, Ohms Law in Point form, Continuity of current, Boundary conditions of perfect dielectric materials. Permittivity of dielectric materials, Capacitance, Capacitance of a two wire line, Poisson\'s equation, Laplace\'s equation, Solution of Laplace and Poisson\'s equation, Application of Laplace\'s and Poisson\'s equations.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:

    Static Magnetic Fields (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Biot-Savart Law, Ampere Law, Magnetic flux and magnetic flux density, Scalar and Vector Magnetic potentials. Steady magnetic fields produced by current carrying conductors.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:

     Magnetic Forces, Materials and Inductance (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Force on a moving charge, Force on a differential current element, Force between differential current elements, Nature of magnetic materials, Magnetization and permeability, Magnetic boundary conditions, Magnetic circuits, inductances and mutual inductances.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:

    Time Varying Fields and Maxwell\'s Equations (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Faraday\'s law for Electromagnetic induction, Displacement current, Point form of Maxwell\'s equation, Integral form of Maxwell\'s equations, Motional Electromotive forces. Boundary Conditions.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:

    Electromagnetic Waves (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Derivation of Wave Equation, Uniform Plane Waves, Maxwell\'s equation in Phasor form, Wave equation in Phasor form, Plane waves in free space and in a homogenous material. Wave equation for a conducting medium, Plane waves in lossy dielectrics, Propagation in good conductors, Skin effect. Poynting theorem.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. M. N. O. Sadiku, "Elements of Electromagnetics", Oxford University Publication, 2014.\n\n\n

2. A. Pramanik, "Electromagnetism - Theory and applications", PHI Learning Pvt. Ltd, New Delhi, 2009.\n\n\n

3. A. Pramanik, "Electromagnetism-Problems with solution", Prentice Hall India, 2012.\n\n\n

4. G.W. Carter, "The electromagnetic field in its engineering aspects", Longmans, 1954.\n\n\n

5. W.J. Duffin, "Electricity and Magnetism", McGraw Hill Publication, 1980.\n\n\n

6. W.J. Duffin, "Advanced Electricity and Magnetism", McGraw Hill, 1968.\n\n\n

 7. E.G. Cullwick, "The Fundamentals of Electromagnetism", Cambridge University Press, 1966.\n\n\n

8. B. D. Popovic, "Introductory Engineering Electromagnetics", Addison-Wesley Educational Publishers, International Edition, 1971.\n\n\n

9. W. Hayt, "Engineering Electromagnetics", McGraw Hill Education, 2012.\n\n\n
    </string>


    <string name="eeesem3sub6">Engineering Mechanics</string>
<string name="Em2eee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  3L:1T:0P 4 credits</font></b>\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:

    Introduction to vectors and tensors and co-ordinate systems (5 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Introduction to vectors and tensors and coordinate systems; Vector and tensor algebra; Indical notation; Symmetric and anti-symmetric tensors; Eigenvalues and Principal axes.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:

    Three-dimensional Rotation (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Three-dimensional rotation: Euler\'s theorem, Axis-angle formulation and Euler angles; Coordinate transformation of vectors and tensors.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:

    Kinematics of Rigid Body (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Kinematics of rigid bodies: Dentition and motion of a rigid body; Rigid bodies as coordinate systems; Angular velocity of a rigid body, and its rate of change; Distinction between two-and threedimensional rotational motion; Integration of angular velocity to find orientation; Motion relative to a rotating rigid body: Five term acceleration formula.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:

    Kinetics of Rigid Bodies (5 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Kinetics of rigid bodies: Angular momentum about a point; Inertia tensor: Dentition and computation, Principal moments and axes of inertia, Parallel and perpendicular axes theorems; Mass moment of inertia of symmetrical bodies, cylinder, sphere, cone etc., Area moment of inertia and Polar moment of inertia, Forces and moments; Newton-Euler\'s laws of rigid body motion.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:

     Free Body Diagram (1 hour)</font></b>\n\n\n

Free body diagrams; Examples on modelling of typical supports and joints and discussion on the kinematic and kinetic constraints that they impose.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:

    General Motion (9 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Examples and problems. General planar motions. General 3-D motions. Free precession, Gyroscopes, Rolling coin.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:

    Bending Moment (5 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Transverse loading on beams, shear force and bending moment in beams, analysis of cantilevers, simply supported beams and overhanging beams, relationships between loading, shear force and bending moment, shear force and bending moment diagrams.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8:

    Torsional Motion (2 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Torsion of circular shafts, derivation of torsion equation, stress and deformation in circular and hollow shafts.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 9:

    Friction (3 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Concept of Friction; Laws of Coulomb friction; Angle of Repose; Coefficient of friction.\n\n\n

 Text / References:\n\n\n

1. J. L. Meriam and L. G. Kraige, "Engineering Mechanics: Dynamics", Wiley, 2011.\n\n\n

2. M. F. Beatty, "Principles of Engineering Mechanics", Springer Science and Business Media, 1986\n\n\n

</string>


<string name="eeesem4sub1">Analog Electronic Circuit</string>
<string name="AEC">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

1. Understand the characteristics of transistors.\n\n\n

2. Design and analyze various rectifier and amplifier circuits.\n\n\n

3. Design sinusoidal and non-sinusoidal oscillators.\n\n\n

4. Understand the functioning of OP-AMP and design OP-AMP based circuits.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Diode circuits (4 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

P-N junction diode, I-V characteristics of a diode; review of half-wave and full-wave rectifiers, Zener diodes, clamping and clipping circuits.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: BJT circuits (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Structure and I-V characteristics of a BJT; BJT as a switch. BJT as an amplifier: small-signal model, biasing circuits, current mirror; common-emitter, common-base and common-collector amplifiers; Small signal equivalent circuits, high-frequency equivalent circuits\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: MOSFET circuits (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

MOSFET structure and I-V characteristics. MOSFET as a switch. MOSFET as an amplifier: smallsignal model and biasing circuits, common-source, common-gate and common-drain amplifiers, small signal equivalent circuits - gain, input and output impedances, trans-conductance, high frequency equivalent circuit.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Differential, multi-stage and operational amplifiers (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Differential amplifier, power amplifier; direct coupled multi-stage amplifier; internal structure of an operational amplifier, ideal op-amp, non-idealities in an op-amp (Output offset voltage, input bias current, input offset current, slew rate, gain bandwidth product), Frequency Response of the amplifier.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Linear applications of op-amp (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Idealized analysis of op-amp circuits. Inverting and non-inverting amplifier, differential amplifier, +instrumentation amplifier, integrator, active filter, P, PI and PID controllers and lead/lag compensator using an op-amp, voltage regulator, Feedback amplifiers and Oscillators design (Wein bridge and phase shift). Analog to Digital Conversion.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: Nonlinear applications of op-amp (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Hysteretic Comparator, Zero Crossing Detector, Square-wave and triangular-wave generators. Precision rectifier, peak detector. Monoshot.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. A. S. Sedra and K. C. Smith, "Microelectronic Circuits", New York, Oxford University Press, 1998.\n\n\n

2. J. V. Wait, L. P. Huelsman and G. A. Korn, "Introduction to Operational Amplifier theory and applications", McGraw Hill U. S., 1992.\n\n\n

3. J. Millman and A. Grabel, "Microelectronics", McGraw Hill Education, 1988.\n\n\n

4. P. Horowitz and W. Hill, "The Art of Electronics", Cambridge University Press, 1989.\n\n\n

5. P.R. Gray, R.G. Meyer and S. Lewis, "Analysis and Design of Analog Integrated Circuits", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2001. PCC-EEE07: Analog Electronic Circuits Laboratory (0:0:2-1 credit) Hands-on experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE06.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="eeesem4sub2">Electrical Machines-II</string>
<string name="EMeee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

1. Understand the concepts of rotating magnetic fields.\n\n\n

2. Understand the operation of ac machines.\n\n\n

3. Analyse performance characteristics of ac machines.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Fundamentals of AC machine windings (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Physical arrangement of windings in stator and cylindrical rotor, slots for windings; single-turn coil - active portion and overhang; full-pitch coils, concentrated winding, distributed winding, winding axis, 3D visualization of the above winding types, Air-gap MMF distribution with fixed current through winding-concentrated and distributed, Sinusoidally distributed winding, winding distribution factor\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Pulsating and revolving magnetic fields (4 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Constant magnetic field, pulsating magnetic field - alternating current in windings with spatial displacement, Magnetic field produced by a single winding - fixed current and alternating current Pulsating fields produced by spatially displaced windings, Windings spatially shifted by 90 degrees, Addition of pulsating magnetic fields, Three windings spatially shifted by 120 degrees (carrying three-phase balanced currents), revolving magnetic field.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Induction Machines (12 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Construction, Types (squirrel cage and slip-ring), Torque Slip Characteristics, Starting and Maximum Torque. Equivalent circuit. Phasor Diagram, Losses and Efficiency. Effect of parameter variation on torque speed characteristics (variation of rotor and stator resistances, stator voltage, frequency). Methods of starting, braking and speed control for induction motors. Generator operation. Self-excitation. Doubly-Fed Induction Machines.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Single-phase induction motors (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Constructional features, double revolving field theory, equivalent circuit, determination of parameters. Split-phase starting methods and applications\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Synchronous machines (10 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Constructional features, cylindrical rotor synchronous machine-generated EMF, equivalent circuit and phasor diagram, armature reaction, synchronous impedance, voltage regulation. Operating characteristics of synchronous machines, V-curves. Salient pole machine - two reaction theory, analysis of phasor diagram, power angle characteristics. Parallel operation of alternators - synchronization and load division.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. A. E. Fitzgerald and C. Kingsley, "Electric Machinery", McGraw Hill Education, 2013.\n\n\n

2. M. G. Say, "Performance and design of AC machines", CBS Publishers, 2002.\n\n\n

3. P. S. Bimbhra, "Electrical Machinery", Khanna Publishers, 2011.\n\n\n

4. I. J. Nagrath and D. P. Kothari, "Electric Machines", McGraw Hill Education, 2010.\n\n\n

5. A. S. Langsdorf, "Alternating current machines", McGraw Hill Education, 1984.\n\n\n

6. P. C. Sen, "Principles of Electric Machines and Power Electronics", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2007.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem4sub3">Microprocessors</string>
<string name="MPeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

1 Do assembly language programming.\n\n\n

2 Do interfacing design of peripherals like I/O, A/D, D/A, timer etc.\n\n\n

3 Develop systems using different microcontrollers.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Fundamentals of Microprocessors: (7 Hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Fundamentals of Microprocessor Architecture. 8-bitMicroprocessor and Microcontroller architecture, Comparison of 8-bit microcontrollers, 16-bit and 32-bit microcontrollers. Definition of embedded system and its characteristics, Role of microcontrollers in embedded Systems. Overview of the 8051 family.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: The 8051 Architecture (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Internal Block Diagram, CPU, ALU, address, data and control bus, Working registers, SFRs, Clock and RESET circuits, Stack and Stack Pointer, Program Counter, I/O ports, Memory Structures, Data and Program Memory, Timing diagrams and Execution Cycles.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Instruction Set and Programming (8 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Addressing modes: Introduction, Instruction syntax, Data types, Subroutines Immediate addressing, Register addressing, Direct addressing, Indirect addressing, Relative addressing, Indexed addressing, Bit inherent addressing, bit direct addressing. 8051 Instruction set, Instruction timings. Data transfer instructions, Arithmetic instructions, Logical instructions, Branch instructions, Subroutine instructions, Bit manipulation instruction. Assembly language programs, C language programs. ams. Assemblers and compilers. Programming and debugging tools.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Memory and I/O Interfacing (6 Hours):</font></b>\n\n\n

Memory and I/O expansion buses, control signals, memory wait states. Interfacing of peripheral devices such as General Purpose I/O, ADC, DAC, timers, counters, memory devices.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: External Communication Interface (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Synchronous and Asynchronous Communication. RS232, SPI, I2C. Introduction and interfacing to protocols like Blue-tooth and Zig-bee.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: Applications (6 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

LED, LCD and keyboard interfacing. Stepper motor interfacing, DC Motor interfacing, sensor interfacing.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. M. A.Mazidi, J. G. Mazidi and R. D. McKinlay, "The8051 Microcontroller and Embedded Systems: Using Assembly and C", Pearson Education, 2007.\n\n\n

2. K. J. Ayala, "8051 Microcontroller", Delmar Cengage Learning, 2004.\n\n\n

3. R. Kamal, "Embedded System", McGraw Hill Education, 2009.4. R. S. Gaonkar, ", Microprocessor Architecture: Programming and Applications with the 8085", Penram International Publishing, 1996\n\n\n

5. D.A. Patterson and J.H. Hennessy, "Computer Organization and Design: The Hardware/Software interface", Morgan Kaufman Publishers, 2013.\n\n\n

6. D. V. Hall, "Microprocessors &amp; Interfacing", McGraw Hill Higher Education, 1991.\n\n\n

</string>


    <string name="eeesem4sub4"> Signal and System</string>
<string name="SASeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

1. Understand the concepts of continuous time and discrete time systems.\n\n\n

2. Analyse systems in complex frequency domain.\n\n\n

3. Understand sampling theorem and its implications.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Introduction to Signals and Systems (3 hours):</font></b>\n\n\n

Signals and systems as seen in everyday life, and in various branches of engineering and science. Signal properties: periodicity, absolute integrability, determinism and stochastic character. Some special signals of importance: the unit step, the unit impulse, the sinusoid, the complex exponential, some special time-limited signals; continuous and discrete time signals, continuous and discrete amplitude signals. System properties: linearity: additivity and homogeneity, shift-invariance, causality, stability, realizability. Examples.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Behavior of continuous and discrete-time LTI systems (8 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Impulse response and step response, convolution, input-output behavior with aperiodic convergent inputs, cascade interconnections. Characterization of causality and stability of LTI systems. System representation through differential equations and difference equations. Statespace Representation of systems. State-Space Analysis, Multi-input, multi-output representation. State Transition Matrix and its Role. Periodic inputs to an LTI system, the notion of a frequency response and its relation to the impulse response.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Fourier, Laplace and z- Transforms (10 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Fourier series representation of periodic signals, Waveform Symmetries, Calculation of Fourier Coefficients. Fourier Transform, convolution/multiplication and their effect in the frequency domain, magnitude and phase response, Fourier domain duality. The Discrete-Time Fourier Transform (DTFT) and the Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT). Parseval\'s Theorem. Review of the Laplace Transform for continuous time signals and systems, system functions, poles and zeros of system functions and signals, Laplace domain analysis, solution to differential equations and system behavior. The z-Transform for discrete time signals and systems, system functions, poles and zeros of systems and sequences, z-domain analysis.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Sampling and Reconstruction (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

The Sampling Theorem and its implications. Spectra of sampled signals. Reconstruction: ideal interpolator, zero-order hold, first-order hold. Aliasing and its effects. Relation between continuous and discrete time systems. Introduction to the applications of signal and system theory: modulation for communication, filtering, feedback control systems.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. A. V. Oppenheim, A. S. Willsky and S. H. Nawab, "Signals and systems", Prentice Hall India, 1997.\n\n\n

2. J. G. Proakis and D. G. Manolakis, "Digital Signal Processing: Principles, Algorithms, and Applications", Pearson, 2006.\n\n\n

3. H. P. Hsu, "Signals and systems", Schaum\'s series, McGraw Hill Education, 2010.\n\n\n

4. S. Haykin and B. V. Veen, "Signals and Systems", John Wiley and Sons, 2007.\n\n\n

5. A. V. Oppenheim and R. W. Schafer, "Discrete-Time Signal Processing", Prentice Hall, 2009.\n\n\n

6. M. J. Robert "Fundamentals of Signals and Systems", McGraw Hill Education, 2007.\n\n\n

7. B. P. Lathi, "Linear Systems and Signals", Oxford University Press, 2009.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem4sub5">Mathematics-III(Probability and Statistics)</string>
<string name="PASeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Basic Probability (12 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Probability spaces, conditional probability, independence; Discrete random variables, Independent random variables, the multinomial distribution, Poisson approximation to the binomial distribution, infinite sequences of Bernoulli trials, sums of independent random variables; Expectation of Discrete Random Variables, Moments, Variance of a sum, Correlation coefficient, Chebyshev\'s Inequality.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Continuous Probability Distributions (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Continuous random variables and their properties, distribution functions and densities, normal, exponential and gamma densities.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Bivariate Distributions (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Bivariate distributions and their properties, distribution of sums and quotients, conditional densities, Bayes\' rule.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Basic Statistics (8 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Measures of Central tendency: Moments, skewness and Kurtosis - Probability distributions: Binomial, Poisson and Normal - evaluation of statistical parameters for these three distributions, Correlation and regression - Rank correlation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Applied Statistics (8 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Curve fitting by the method of least squares-fitting of straight lines, second degree parabolas and more general curves. Test of significance: Large sample test for single proportion, difference of proportions, single mean, difference of means, and difference of standard deviations.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: Small samples (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Test for single mean, difference of means and correlation coefficients, test for ratio of variances - Chi-square test for goodness of fit and independence of attributes.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. E. Kreyszig, "Advanced Engineering Mathematics", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2006.\n\n\n

2. P. G. Hoel, S. C. Port and C. J. Stone, "Introduction to Probability Theory", Universal Book Stall, 2003.\n\n\n

3. S. Ross, "A First Course in Probability", Pearson Education India, 2002.\n\n\n

4. W. Feller, "An Introduction to Probability Theory and its Applications", Vol. 1, Wiley, 1968.\n\n\n

5. N.P. Bali and M. Goyal, "A text book of Engineering Mathematics", Laxmi Publications, 2010.\n\n\n

6. B.S. Grewal, "Higher Engineering Mathematics", Khanna Publishers, 2000.\n\n\n

7. T. Veerarajan, "Engineering Mathematics", Tata McGraw-Hill, New Delhi, 2010.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="eeesem4sub6">Biology</string>
<string name="bioeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1: Introduction (2 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: To convey that Biology is as important a scientific discipline as Mathematics, Physics and Chemistry. Bring out the fundamental differences between science and engineering by drawing a comparison between eye and camera, Bird flying and aircraft. Mention the most exciting aspect of biology as an independent scientific discipline. Why we need to study biology? Discuss how biological observations of 18th Century that lead to major discoveries. Examples from Brownian motion and the origin of thermodynamics by referring to the original observation of Robert Brown and Julius Mayor. These examples will highlight the fundamental importance of observations in any scientific inquiry.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Classification (3 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: To convey that classification per se is not what biology is all about. The underlying criterion, such as morphological, biochemical or ecological be highlighted. Hierarchy of life forms at phenomenological level. A common thread weaves this hierarchy Classification. Discuss classification based on\n\n\n

(a) cellularity- Unicellular or multicellular\n\n\n

(b) ultrastructureprokaryotes or eucaryotes.

© energy and Carbon utilization-Autotrophs, heterotrophs, lithotropes\n\n\n

(d) Ammonia excretion aminotelic, uricotelic, ureotelic\n\n\n (e) Habitata-acquatic or terrestrial\n\n\n

(f) Molecular taxonomy-three major kingdoms of life. A given organism can come under different category based on classification. Model organisms for the study of biology come from different groups. E.coli, S. cerevisiae, D. Melanogaster, C. elegance, A. Thaliana, M. musculus\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 3: Genetics (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: To convey that "Genetics is to biology what Newton\'s laws are to Physical Sciences". Mendel\'s laws, Concept of segregation and independent assortment. Concept of allele. Gene mapping, Gene interaction, Epistasis. Meiosis and Mitosis be taught as a part of genetics. Emphasis to be give not to the mechanics of cell division nor the phases but how genetic material passes from parent to offspring. Concepts of recessiveness and dominance. Concept of mapping of phenotype to genes. Discuss about the single gene disorders in humans. Discuss the concept of complementation using human genetics.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Biomolecules (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: To convey that all forms of life has the same building blocks and yet the manifestations are as diverse as one can imagine. Molecules of life. In this context discuss monomeric units and polymeric structures. Discuss about sugars, starch and cellulose. Amino acids and proteins. Nucleotides and DNA/RNA. Two carbon units and lipids.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Enzymes (4 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: To convey that without catalysis life would not have existed on earth. Enzymology: How to monitor enzyme catalysed reactions. How does an enzyme catalyse reactions? Enzyme classification. Mechanism of enzyme action. Discuss at least two examples. Enzyme kinetics and kinetic parameters. Why should we know these parameters to understand biology? RNA catalysis.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: Information Transfer (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: The molecular basis of coding and decoding genetic information is universal. Molecular basis of information transfer. DNA as a genetic material. Hierarchy of DNA structurefrom single stranded to double helix to nucleosomes. Concept of genetic code. Universality and degeneracy of genetic code. Define gene in terms of complementation and recombination.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7: Macromolecular analysis (5 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: To analyse biological processes at the reductionistic level. Proteins-structure and function. Hierarch in protein structure. Primary secondary, tertiary and quaternary structure. Proteins as enzymes, transporters, receptors and structural elements.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 8: Metabolism (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Purpose: The fundamental principles of energy transactions are the same in physical and biological world. Thermodynamics as applied to biological systems. Exothermic and endothermic versus endergonic and exergonic reactions. Concept of Keq and its relation to standard free energy. Spontaneity. ATP as an energy currency. This should include the breakdown of glucose to CO2 + H2O (Glycolysis and Krebs cycle) and synthesis of glucose from CO2 and H2O (Photosynthesis). Energy yielding and energy consuming reactions. Concept of Energy charge.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 9. Microbiology (3 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Concept of single celled organisms. Concept of species and strains. Identification and classification of microorganisms. Microscopy. Ecological aspects of single celled organisms. Sterilization and media compositions. Growth kinetics.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. N. A. Campbell, J. B. Reece, L. Urry, M. L. Cain and S. A. Wasserman, "Biology: A global approach", Pearson Education Ltd, 2014.\n\n\n

2. E. E. Conn, P. K. Stumpf, G. Bruening and R. H. Doi, "Outlines of Biochemistry", John Wiley and Sons, 2009.\n\n\n

3. D. L. Nelson and M. M. Cox, "Principles of Biochemistry", W.H. Freeman and Company, 2012.\n\n\n

4. G. S. Stent and R. Calendar, "Molecular Genetics", Freeman and company, 1978.5. L. M. Prescott, J. P. Harley and C. A. Klein, "Microbiology", McGraw Hill Higher Education, 2005.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem5sub1">Analog &amp; Digital Communication System</string>
<string name="ADCSeee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcome:</font></b>\n\n\n

At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to

Understand the basics of communication system, analog and digital modulation techniques.

Apply the knowledge of digital electronics and understand the error control coding techniques. Summarize different types of communication systems and

its requirements.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Basic blocks of Communication System. Analog Modulation - Principles of Amplitude Modulation, DSBSC, SSB-SC and VSB-SC. AM transmitters and receivers.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Angle Modulation - Frequency and Phase Modulation. Transmission Bandwidth of FM signals, Methods of generation and detection. FM Transmitters and Receivers.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Sampling theorem - Pulse Modulation Techniques - PAM, PWM and PPM concepts - PCM system - Data transmission using analog carriers (ASK, FSK, BPSK, QPSK).\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Error control coding techniques - Linear block codes- Encoder and decoder. Cyclic codes - Encoder, Syndrome Calculator. Convolution codes.\n\n\n

 <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Modern Communication Systems - Microwave communication systems - Optical communication system - Satellite communication system - Mobile communication system.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:</font></b>\n\n\n

    1. Simon Haykins, "Communication Systems", John Wiley, 3rd Edition, 1995.\n\n\n

2. D.Roddy &amp; J.Coolen, "Electronic Communications", Prentice Hall of India, 4th Edition, 1999.\n\n\n

3. Kennedy G, "Electronic Communication System", McGraw Hill, 1987.\n\n\n

PCC-EEE20: Analog &amp; Digital Communication System Laboratory (0:0:2-1 credit)\n\n\n

Hands-on/Computer experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE19\n\n\n
</string>
<string name="eeesem5sub2">Capstone Design Project</string>
<string name="CDPeee">

</string>
<string name="eeesem5sub3">Constitution Of INDIA/Essence Of INDIAN Knowledge Traditional</string>
<string name="consteee">
    \n\n\n
         The Constitution of India is the supreme law of India. Parliament of India cannot make any law which violates the Fundamental Rights enumerated under the Part III of the Constitution. The Parliament of India has been empowered to amend the Constitution under Article 368, however, it cannot use this power to change the "basic structure" of the constitution, which has been ruled and explained by the Supreme Court of India in its historical judgments. The Constitution of India reflects the idea of "Constitutionalism" - a modern and progressive concept historically developed by the thinkers of "liberalism" - an ideology which has been recognized as one of the most popular political ideology and result of historical struggles against arbitrary use of sovereign power by state. The historic revolutions in France, England, America and particularly European Renaissance and Reformation movement have resulted into progressive legal reforms in the form of "constitutionalism" in many countries. The Constitution of India was made by borrowing models and principles from many countries including United Kingdom and America.\n\n\n

The Constitution of India is not only a legal document but it also reflects social, political and economic perspectives of the Indian Society. It reflects India\'s legacy of "diversity". It has been said that Indian constitution reflects ideals of its freedom movement, however, few critics have argued that it does not truly incorporate our own ancient legal heritage and cultural values. No law can be "static" and therefore the Constitution of India has also been amended more than one hundred times. These amendments reflect political, social and economic developments since the year 1950. The Indian judiciary and particularly the Supreme Court of India has played an historic role as the guardian of people. It has been protecting not only basic ideals of the

Constitution but also strengthened the same through progressive interpretations of the text of the Constitution. The judicial activism of the Supreme Court of India and its historic contributions has been recognized throughout the world and it gradually made it "as one of the strongest court in the world".\n\n\n


<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course content:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Meaning of the constitution law and constitutionalism\n\n\n

2. Historical perspective of the Constitution of India\n\n\n

4. Salient features and characteristics of the Constitution of India\n\n\n

5. Scheme of the fundamental rights\n\n\n

6. The scheme of the Fundamental Duties and its legal status\n\n\n

7. The Directive Principles of State Policy Its importance and implementation\n\n\n

8. Federal structure and distribution of legislative and financial powers between the Union and the States\n\n\n

9. Parliamentary Form of Government in India - The constitution powers and status of the President of India\n\n\n

10. Amendment of the Constitutional Powers and Procedure\n\n\n

11. The historical perspectives of the constitutional amendments in India\n\n\n

12. Emergency Provisions: National Emergency, President Rule, Financial Emergency\n\n\n

13. Local Self Government - Constitutional Scheme in India\n\n\n

14. Scheme of the Fundamental Right to Equality\n\n\n

15. Scheme of the Fundamental Right to certain Freedom under Article 19\n\n\n

16. Scope of the Right to Life and Personal Liberty under Article 21.\n\n\n

</string>


    <string name="eeesem5sub4">Control System</string>
    <string name="CSeee">\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to

Understand the modelling of linear-time-invariant systems using transfer function and state- space representations. Understand the concept of stability and its assessment for linear-time invariant systems.

Design simple feedback controllers.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Introduction to control problem (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Industrial Control examples. Mathematical models of physical systems. Control hardware and their models. Transfer function

models of linear time-invariant systems. Feedback Control: Open-Loop and Closed-loop systems. Benefits of Feedback. Block diagram algebra.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Time Response Analysis (10 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Standard test signals. Time response of first and second order

systems for standard test inputs. Application of initial and final value theorem. Design specifications for second-order systems based on the time-response.

Concept of Stability. Routh-Hurwitz Criteria. Relative Stability analysis. Root-Locus technique. Construction of Root-loci.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Frequency-response analysis (6 hours) </font></b>\n\n\nRelationship between time and frequency response, Polar plots, Bode plots. Nyquist stability criterion. Relative stability using Nyquist criterion - gain and phase margin. Closed-loop frequency response.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Introduction to Controller Design (10 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Stability, steady-state accuracy, transient accuracy, disturbance rejection, insensitivity and robustness of control systems.\n\n\n

Root-loci method of feedback controller design. Design specifications in frequency-domain. Frequency-domain methods of design. Application of Proportional, Integral and Derivative Controllers, Lead and Lag compensation in designs. Analog and Digital

implementation of controllers.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: State variable Analysis (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Concepts of state variables. State space model. Diagonalization of State Matrix. Solution of state equations. Eigenvalues and Stability Analysis. Concept of controllability and observability.

Pole-placement by state feedback. Discrete-time systems. Difference Equations. State-space models of linear discrete-time systems. Stability of linear discrete-time systems.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 6: Introduction to Optimal Control and Nonlinear Control (5 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Performance Indices. Regulator problem, Tracking Problem. Nonlinear system-Basic concepts and analysis.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. M. Gopal, "Control Systems: Principles and Design", McGraw Hill Education, 1997.\n\n\n

2. B. C. Kuo, "Automatic Control System", Prentice Hall, 1995. 3. K. Ogata, "Modern Control Engineering", Prentice Hall, 1991.\n\n\n

4. I. J. Nagrath and M. Gopal, "Control Systems Engineering", New Age International, 2009\n\n\n

PCC-EEE16: Control Systems Laboratory (0:0:2-1 credit)\n\n\n Hands-on/Computer experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE15.\n\n\n
    </string>


<string name="eeesem5sub5">MOOCS/NPTEL ETC.COURSES-2/SWAYAM</string>
<string name="npteleee">

</string>
<string name="eeesem5sub6">Power Electronics</string>
<string name="PEeee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Understand the differences between signal level and power level devices.\n\n\n

Analyse controlled rectifier circuits.\n\n\n

Analyse the operation of DC-DC choppers. Analyse the operation of voltage source inverters.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1: Power switching devices (8 Hours) </font></b>\n\n\nDiode, Thyristor, MOSFET, IGBT: I-V Characteristics; Firing circuit for thyristor; Voltage and current commutation of a thyristor, Gate drive circuits for MOSFET and IGBT.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 2: Thyristor rectifiers (7 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Single-phase half-wave and full-wave rectifiers, Single-phase full-bridge thyristor rectifier with R- load and highly inductive load; Three-phase full-bridge thyristor rectifier with R-load and highly inductive load; Input current wave shape and power factor.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 3: DC-DC buck converter (5 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Elementary chopper with an active switch and diode, concepts of duty ratio and average voltage, power circuit of a buck converter, analysis and waveforms at steady state, duty ratio control of output voltage.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 4: DC-DC boost converter (5 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Power circuit of a boost converter, analysis and waveforms at steady state, relation between duty ratio and average output voltage.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 5: Single-phase voltage source inverter (10 Hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Power circuit of single-phase voltage source inverter, switch states and instantaneous output voltage, square wave operation of the inverter, concept of average voltage over a switching cycle, bipolar sinusoidal modulation and unipolar sinusoidal modulation, modulation index and output voltage\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 6: Three-phase voltage source inverter (8 Hours) </font></b>\n\n\nPower circuit of a three-phase voltage source inverter, switch states, instantaneous output voltages, average output voltages over a sub-cycle, three-phase sinusoidal modulation\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 7: A.C. to A.C. Converter (8 Hours)</font>
    </b>\n\n\n[14] Classification, principle of operation of step up and step down cyclo-converter, single phase to single phase cyclo-converter with resistive and inductive load, three phase to single phase cyclo-converter, half wave and full wave, cosine wave crossing technique, three phase to three phase cyclo-converter. output

voltage equation of cyclo-converter.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Text/References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. M. H. Rashid, "Power electronics: circuits, devices, and applications", Pearson Education India, 2009.\n\n\n

2. N. Mohan and T. M. Undeland, "Power Electronics: Converters, Applications and Design", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2007.\n\n\n

3. R. W. Erickson and D. Maksimovic, "Fundamentals of Power Electronics", Springer Science &amp; Business Media, 2007.\n\n\n

4. L. Umanand, "Power Electronics: Essentials and Applications", Wiley India, 2009.\n\n\n

PCC-EEE18: Power Electronics Laboratory (0:0:2-1 credit)\n\n\n Hands-on experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE17.\n\n\n
</string>

<string name="eeesem5sub7">Power System-I(Apparatus and Modelling)</string>
<string name="PSIeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Understand the concepts of power systems. Understand the various power system components.\n\n\n

Evaluate fault currents for different types of faults. Understand the generation of over-voltages and insulation coordination.\n\n\n

Understand basic protection schemes.\n\n\n

Understand concepts of HVDC power transmission and renewable energy generation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Basic Concepts (4 hours) </font></b>\n\n\nEvolution of Power Systems and Present-Day Scenario.

Structure of a power system: Bulk Power

Grids and Micro-grids.

Generation: Conventional and Renewable Energy Sources.

Distributed Energy Resources. Energy Storage. Transmission and Distribution Systems: Line diagrams, transmission and distribution voltage levels and topologies (meshed and radial systems). Synchronous Grids and Asynchronous (DC) interconnections. Review of Three-phase systems. Analysis of simple three-phase circuits. Power Transfer in AC circuits and Reactive Power.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Power System Components (15 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Overhead Transmission Lines and Cables: Electrical and Magnetic Fields around conductors, Corona. Parameters of lines and cables. Capacitance and Inductance calculations for simple

configurations. Travelling-wave Equations. Sinusoidal Steady state representation of Lines: Short, medium and long lines. Power Transfer, Voltage profile and Reactive Power. Characteristics of transmission lines. Surge Impedance Loading. Series and Shunt Compensation of transmission lines.

Transformers: Three-phase connections and Phase-shifts. Three-winding transformers, auto-transformers, Neutral Grounding transformers. Tap-Changing in transformers. Transformer Parameters. Single phase equivalent of three-phase transformers.

Synchronous Machines: Steady-state performance characteristics. Operation when connected to infinite bus. Real and Reactive Power Capability Curve of generators. Typical waveform under balanced terminal short circuit conditions - steady state, transient and sub-transient equivalent circuits.

Loa pes, Voltage and Frequency Dependence of Loads. Per- ystem and per-unit calculations.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Over-voltages and Insulation Requirements (4 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Generation of Over-voltages: Lightning and Switching Surges. Protection against Over-voltages, Insulation Coordination.

Propagation of Surges. Voltages produced by traveling surges.

Bewley

Diagrams.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Fault Analysis and Protection Systems (10 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Method of Symmetrical Components (positive, negative and zero sequences). Balanced and Unbalanced Faults. Representation of generators, lines and transformers in sequence networks. Computation of Fault Currents. Neutral Grounding.

Switchgear: Types of Circuit Breakers. Attributes of Protection schemes, Back-up Protection. Protection schemes (Over-current, directional, distance protection, differential protection) and their application.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Introduction to DC Transmission &amp; Renewable Energy Systems (9 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n DC Transmission Systems: Line-Commutated Converters

(LCC) and Voltage Source Converters (VSC). LCC and VSC based dc link, Real Power Flow control in a dc link. Comparison of ac and de

transmission. Solar PV systems: I-V and P-V characteristics of PV panels, power electronic interface of PV to the grid.

Wind Energy Systems: Power curve of wind turbine. Fixed and variable speed turbines. Permanent Magnetic Synchronous Generators and Induction Generators. Power Electronics interfaces of wind generators to the grid.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. J. Grainger and W. D. Stevenson, "Power System Analysis", McGraw Hill Education, 1994.\n\n\n

2. 0. 1. Elgerd, "Electric Energy Systems Theory", McGraw Hill Education, 1995.\n\n\n

3. A. R. Bergen and V. Vittal, "Power System Analysis", Pearson Education Inc., 1999.\n\n\n

4. D. P. Kothari and I. J. Nagrath, "Modern Power System Analysis", McGraw Hill Education, 2003.\n\n\n

5. B. M. Weedy, B. J. Cory, N. Jenkins, J. Ekanayake and G. Strbac, "Electric Power Systems", Wiley, 2012. PCC-EEE14: Power Systems - I Laboratory (0:0:2-1 credit)\n\n\n

Hands-on experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE13.\n\n\n Visits to power system installations (generation stations, EHV substations etc.) are suggested.\n\n\n Exposure to fault analysis and Electro-magnetic transient program (EMTP) and Numerical Relays are suggested.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="eeesem5sub8">Professional Elective Laboratory-1</string>
<string name="PEleee">
</string>

    <string name="eeesem5sub9">
        Summer Entrepreneurship-II
    </string>
    <string name="summereee">
    </string>

    
    <string name="eeesem6sub1">Digital Signal Processing</string>
    <string name="DSPeee">\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

        <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

• Represent signals mathematically in continuous and discrete-time, and in the frequency domain.\n\n\n

• Analyse discrete-time systems using z-transform.\n\n\n

• Understand the Discrete-Fourier Transform (DFT) and the FFT algorithms.\n\n\n

• Design digital filters for various applications.\n\n\n

• Apply digital signal processing for the analysis of real-life signals.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Discrete-time signals and systems (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Discrete time signals and systems: Sequences; representation of signals on orthogonal basis; Representation of discrete systems using difference equations, Sampling and reconstruction of signals -aliasing, Sampling theorem and Nyquist rate.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Z-transform (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n z-Transform, Region of Convergence, Analysis of Linear Shift Invariant systems using z-transform, Properties of z-transform for causal signals, Interpretation of stability in z-domain, Inverse z-transforms.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Discrete Fourier Transform (10 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Frequency Domain Analysis, Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT), Properties of DFT, Connvolution of signals, Fast Fourier Transform Algorithm, Parseval\'s Identity, Implementation of Discrete Time Systems.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Design of Digital filters(12 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n Design of FIR Digital filters: Window method, Park-McClellan\'s method. Design of IIR Digital Filters: Butterworth, Chebyshev and Elliptic Approximations; Low-pass, Band-pass, Band-stop and Highpass filters. Effect of finite register length in FIR filter design. Parametric and non-parametric spectral estimation. Introduction to multi-rate signal processing.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Applications of Digital Signal Processing (6 hours) </font></b>\n\n\nCorrelation Functions and Power Spectra, Stationary Processes, Optimal filtering using ARMA Model, Linear Mean-Square Estimation, Wiener Filter.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Text/ReferenceBooks:</font>
        </b>
        \n\n\n

1. S. K. Mitra, "Digital Signal Processing: A computer based approach", McGraw Hill, 2011.\n\n\n

2. A.V. Oppenheim and R. W. Schafer, "Discrete Time Signal Processing", Prentice Hall, 1989.\n\n\n

3. J. G. Proakis and D.G. Manolakis, "Digital Signal Processing: Principles, Algorithms And Applications", Prentice Hall, 1997.\n\n\n

4. L. R. Rabiner and B. Gold, "Theory and Application of Digital Signal Processing", Prentice Hall, 1992.\n\n\n

5. J. R.Johnson, "Introduction to Digital Signal Processing", Prentice Hall, 1992.\n\n\n

6. D. J. DeFatta, J. G. Lucas andW. S. Hodgkiss, "Digital Signal Processing", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1988.\n\n\n

PCC-EEE24: Digital Signal Processing Laboratory (0:0:2-1 credit)\n\n\n

Hands-on/Computer experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE23\n\n\n
    </string>


    <string name="eeesem6sub2">Measurements and Instrumentation</string>
<string name="maieee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

•Design and validate DC and AC bridges.\n\n\n

• Analyze the dynamic response and the calibration of few instruments.\n\n\n

• Learn about various measurement devices, their characteristics, their operation and their limitations.\n\n\n

Understand statistical data analysis.\n\n\n

Understand computerized data acquisition.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Lectures/Demonstrations:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Concepts relating to Measurements: True value, Accuracy, Precision, Resolution, Drift, Hysteresis, Dead-band, Sensitivity.\n\n\n

2. Errors in Measurements. Basic statistical analysis applied to measurements: Mean, Standard Deviation, Six-sigma estimation, Cp, Cpk.\n\n\n

3. Sensors and Transducers for physical parameters: temperature, pressure, torque, flow. Speed and Position Sensors.\n\n\n

4. Current and Voltage Measurements. Shunts, Potential Dividers. Instrument Transformers, Hall Sensors.\n\n\n

5. Measurements of R, L and C.\n\n\n

6. Digital Multi-meter, True RMS meters, Clamp-on meters, Meggers,\n\n\n

7. Digital Storage Oscilloscope.\n\n\n

8. Basic components of bio-medical instruments, bio-electric signals &amp; recording electrodes, transducers, recording and display devices. Patient care and monitoring systems, cardiovascular measurements-blood pressure, blood flow, cardiac output, heart sounds etc.; instrumentation for respiratory and nervous systems, analysis of EEG, ECG, EMG, EOG and action potentials, non-invasive diagnostic measurements - temperature, ultrasonic diagnosis, CAT scan techniques, sensory measurements-motor response.\n\n\n

 PCC-EEE26: Measurements and Instrumentation Laboratory (0:0:21 credit)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> List of Experiments\n\n\n</font>
    </b>

1. Measurement of a batch of resistors and estimating statistical parameters.\n\n\n

2. Measurement of Lusing abridgetechnique as well as LCRmeter.\n\n\n

3. Measurement of C using a bridge technique as well as LCR meter.\n\n\n

4. Measurement of Low Resistance using Kelvin\'s double bridge.\n\n\n

5. Measurement of High resistance and Insulation resistance using Megger.\n\n\n

6. Usage of DSO for steady state periodic waveforms produced by a function generator.\n\n\n

a. Selection of trigger source and trigger level, selection of time-scale and voltage scale.\n\n\n

b. Bandwidth of measurement and sampling rate.\n\n\n

7. Download of one-cycle data of a periodic waveform from a DSO and use values to compute the RMS values using a C program.\n\n\n

8. Usage of DSO to capture transients like a step change in R-L-C circuit.\n\n\n

9. Current Measurementusing Shunt, CT,andHallSensor.\n\n\n
</string>

    <string name="eeesem6sub3">Electronics Design Laboratory</string>
    <string name="EDLeee">\n\n\n
        Course Outcomes:

        <b>At the end of the course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Understand the practical issues related to practical implementation of applications using electronic circuits.\n\n\n

Choose appropriate components, software and hardware platforms.\n\n\n

• Design a Printed Circuit Board, get it made and populate/ solder it with components.\n\n\n

•Work as a team with other students to implement an application. Basic concepts on measurements; Noise in electronic systems; Sensors and signal conditioning circuits; Introduction to electronic instrumentation and PC based data acquisition; Electronic system design, Analog system design, Interfacing of analog and digital systems, Embedded systems, Electronic system design employing microcontrollers, CPLDs, and FPGAS, PCB design and layout; System assembly considerations. Group projects involving electronic hardware (Analog, Digital, mixed signal) leading to implementation of an application.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books\n\n\n</font></b>

1. A. S. Sedra and K. C. Smith, "Microelectronic circuits", Oxford University Press, 2007.\n\n\n

2. P. Horowitz and W. Hill, "The Art of Electronics", Cambridge University Press, 1997.\n\n\n

3. H.W.Ott, "Noise Reduction Techniques in Electronic Systems", Wiley, 1989.\n\n\n

4. W.C. Bosshart, "Printed Circuit Boards:Design and Technology", Tata McGraw Hill, 1983.\n\n\n

5. G.L. Ginsberg, "Printed Circuit Design", McGraw Hill, 1991.\n\n\n
    </string>


    <string name="eeesem6sub4">Professional Skill Development</string>
    <string name="PSDEEE">\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Objectives of the course:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. To learn various interpersonal skills\n\n\n

2. To help in developing various professionals skills.\n\n\n

3. To cover the facets of verbal and non-verbal languages, public speech, reading gestures and body languages, preparing for group discussion and enhancing presentations skills.\n\n\n

4. To enable learners to speak fluently and flawlessly in all kinds of communicative Contexts with speakers of all nationalities.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Detail contents:\n\n\n</font></b>

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1 Lecture 10 hrs.</font></b>\n\n\n Communication skills: Public speaking, Group discussion, Gestures and body language &amp; professional presentation skills\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2 Lecture 10 hrs. </font></b>\n\n\n Interpersonal skills: Group dynamics, Negotiation skills, Leadership, Emotional intelligence\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3 Lecture 10 hrs. </font></b>\n\n\n Employability and Corporate Skills: Time management and effective planning, Stress management, People skills, Team work, development of leadership qualities, Decision making and Negotiation skills, Positive attitude, Self-motivation, Professional ethics, Business etiquettes, balancing board room.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4 Lecture 10 hrs.</font></b>\n\n\n Business writing skills, Resume Writing. Interview Skills, Technical Presentation, Guest Lecture, Professional Ethics, Project Management, Entrepreneurship.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Suggested reference books:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. "Personality Development and Soft Skills", Barun Mitra, Oxford University Press.\n\n\n

2. "Managing Soft Skills for Personality Development", B.N. Ghosh, McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

3. "Communication Skills and Soft Skills: An Integrated Approach", E. Suresh Kumar, Pearson\n\n\n

4. "Communication to Win", Richard Denny, Kogan Page India Pvt. Ltd.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course outcomes\n\n\n</font></b>

1. Student can able to write their resume and can prepare for presentation, group discussion and interview.\n\n\n

2. Student can develop interpersonal skills like negotiation and leadership skills.\n\n\n

3. Students can develop Employability and Corporate Skills with proper time management and stress management.\n\n\n

4. Students learn to practice the professional ethics, project management and Entrepreneurship.\n\n\n

    </string>

    <string name="eeesem6sub5">Introduction to VLSI Design</string>
    <string name="vlsieee">\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

        <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

1. Understand the mathematical methods and circuit analysis models in analysis of CMOS digital electronics circuits, including logic components and their inter connect..\n\n\n

2. Understand the CMOS technology-specific layout rules in the placement and routing of transistors and interconnect, and to verify the functionality, timing, power, and parasitic effects\n\n\n

3. Understand the concepts and techniques of modern integrated circuit design and testing (CMOS VLSI).\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Introduction MOSFET, threshold voltage, current,

Channel length modulation, body bias effect and short channel effects, MOS switch, MOSFET capacitances, MOSFET models for calculation- Transistors and Layout, CMOS layout elements, parasitics, wires and vias-design rules-layout design SPICE simulation of MOSFET I-V characteristics and parameter extraction (10 hours)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n CMOS inverter, static characteristics, noise

margin, effect of process variation, supply scaling, dynamic characteristics, inverter design for a given VTC and speed, effect of input rise time and fall time, static and dynamic power dissipation, energy &amp; power delay product, sizing chain of inverters, latch up effect-Simulation of static and dynamic characteristics, layout, post layout simulation (10 hours)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Static CMOS design, Complementary CMOS, static

properties, propagation delay, Elmore delay model, power consumption, low power design techniques, logical effort for transistor sizing, ratioed logic, pseudo NMOS inverter, DCVSL, PTL, DPTL &amp; Transmission gate logic, dynamic CMOS design, speed and power considerations, Domino logic and its derivatives, C2MOS, TSPC registers, NORA CMOS - Course project (10 hours)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Circuit design considerations of Arithmetic circuits, shifter, CMOS memory design - SRAM and DRAM, BICMOS logic-static and dynamic behaviour-Delay and power consumption in BICMOS Logic. (10 hours)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text / References:</font></b>\n\n\n

1. David A. Hodges, Horace G. Jackson, and Resve A. Saleh, "Analysis and Design of Digital Integrated Circuits", McGraw-Hill, Third edition, 2004..\n\n\n

 2. R. J. Baker, H. W. Li, and D. E. Boyce, "MOS circuit design, layout, and simulation", Wiley-IEEE Press, 2007.\n\n\n

3. Sung-Mo Kang &amp; Yusuf Leblebici, "CMOS Digital Integrated Circuits - Analysis &amp; Design", Tata McGraw Hill, Third edition, 2003.\n\n\n

4. Wayne Wolf, "Modern VLSI design", Pearson Education, 2003\n\n\n

5. Christopher Saint and Judy Saint, "IC layout basics: A practical guide", Tata McGraw Hill Professional, 2001.\n\n\n

PCC-EEE22: Introduction to VLSI Design Laboratory (0:0:2 - 1 credit)\n\n\n

Hands-on/Computer experiments related to the course contents of PCC-EEE21\n\n\n

    </string>



<string name="eeesem7sub1"> Project-I</string>
<string name="eeeproject_1">Project-I</string>
<string name="eeesem7sub2">Seminar</string>
<string name="eeeseminar">Seminar</string>
<string name="eeesem7sub3">Summer Entrepreneurship-III</string>
<string name="SE3eee">Summer Entrepreneurship-III</string>


    <string name="eeesem7sub4">Open Elective-I</string>
    <string name="eeesem7sub5">Open Elective-II</string>
    <string name="eeesem7sub6">Program Elective-III</string>
    <string name="eeesem7sub7">Program Elective-IV</string>
<string name="eeesem7elective">EEE Elective</string>
    <string name="eeesem7ele1">Electromagnetic Waves</string>
<string name="EMWeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

• Analyse transmission lines and estimate voltage and current at any point on transmission line for different load conditions.\n\n\n

• Provide solution to real life plane wave problems for various boundary conditions.\n\n\n

• Analyse the field equations for the wave propagation in special cases such as lossy and low loss dielectric media.\n\n\n

• Visualize TE and TM mode patterns of field distributions in a rectangular wave-guide.\n\n\n

• Understand and analyse radiation by antennas.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1: Transmission Lines (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Introduction, Concept of distributed elements, Equations of voltage and current, Standing waves and impedance transformation, Lossless and low-loss transmission lines, Power transfer on a transmission line, Analysis of transmission line in terms of admittances, Transmission line calculations with the help of Smith chart, Applications of transmission line, Impedance matching using transmission lines.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2: Maxwell\'s Equations (6 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Basic quantities of Electromagnetics, Basic laws of Electromagnetics: Gauss\' slaw, Ampere\'s Circuital law, Faraday\'s law of Electromagnetic induction. Maxwell\'s equations, Surface charge and surface current, Boundary conditions at media interface.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: Uniform Plane Wave (7 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Homogeneous unbound medium, Wave equation for time harmonic fields, Solution of the wave equation, Uniform plane wave, Wave polarization, Wave propagation in conducting medium, Phase velocity of a wave, Power flow and Poynting vector.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4: Plane Waves at Media Interface (7 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Planewaveinarbitrarydirection, Planewaveatdielectricinterfa ce, Reflectionandrefractionofwaves at dielectric interface, Total internal reflection, Wave polarization at media interface, Brewster angle, Fields and power flow at media interface, Lossy media interface, Reflection from conducting boundary.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: Waveguides (7 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Parallel plane waveguide: Transverse Electric (TE) mode, transverse Magnetic (TM) mode, Cutoff frequency, Phase velocity and dispersion. Transverse Electromagnetic (TEM) mode, Analysis of waveguide-general approach, Rectangular waveguides.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: Antennas (7 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Radiation parameters of antenna, Potential functions, Solution for potential functions, Radiations from Hertz dipole, Near field, Far field, Total power radiated by a dipole, Radiation resistance and radiation pattern of Hertz dipole, Hertz dipole in receiving mode.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books\n\n\n</font></b>

1. R. K. Shevgaonkar, "Electromagnetic Waves", Tata McGraw Hill, 2005.\n\n\n

2. D. K. Cheng, "Field and Wave Electromagnetics", Addison-Wesley, 1989.\n\n\n

3. M. N.O. Sadiku, "Elements of Electromagnetics", Oxford University Press, 2007.\n\n\n

4. C. A. Balanis, "Advanced Engineering Electromagnetics", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2012.\n\n\n

5. C. A. Balanis, "Antenna Theory: Analysis and Design", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2005.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem7ele2">High Voltage Engineering</string>
<string name="HVEeee">\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of the course, the student will demonstrate</b>\n\n\n

•Understand the basic physics related to various breakdown processes in solid, liquid and gaseous insulating materials.\n\n\n

•Knowledge of generation and measurement of D. C., A.C., &amp; Impulse voltages.\n\n\n

•Knowledge of tests on H. V. equipment and on insulating materials, as per the standards.\n\n\n

Knowledge of how over-voltages arise in a power system, and protection against these over voltages.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Breakdown in Gases (8 Hours) lonization processes and de-ionization processes, Types of Discharge, Gases as insulating materials, Breakdown in Uniform gap, non-uniform gaps, Townsend\'s theory, Streamer mechanism, Corona discharge\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Breakdown in liquid and solid Insulating materials (7 Hours) Breakdown in pure and commercial liquids, Solid dielectrics and composite dielectrics, intrinsic breakdown, electromechanical breakdown and thermal breakdown, Partial discharge, applications of insulating materials.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Generation of High Voltages (7 Hours) Generation of high voltages, generation of high D. C. and A.C. voltages, generation of impulse voltages, generation of impulse currents, tripping and control of impulse generators.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Measurements of High Voltages and Currents (7 Hours) Peak voltage, impulse voltage and high direct current measurement method, cathode erayoscillo graphs for impulse voltage and current measurement, measurement of dielectric constant and loss factor, partial discharge measurements.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: </font></b>\n\n\nLightning and Switching Over-Voltages (7 Hours) Charge formation in clouds, Stepped leader, Dart leader, Lightning Surges. Switching overvoltages, Protection against over-voltages, Surge diverters, Surge modifiers.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n High Voltage Testing of Electrical Apparatus and

High Voltage Laboratories (7 Hours) Various standards for HV Testing of electrical apparatus, IS, IEC standards, Testing of insulators and bushings, testingofisolatorsandcircuitbreake rs, testingofcables,powertransformersandsomehigh voltage equipment, High voltage laboratory layout, indoor and outdoor laboratories, testing facility requirements, safety precautions in H. V. Labs.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Text/Reference Books</font></b>\n\n\n

1. M. S. Naidu and V. Kamaraju, "High Voltage Engineering", McGraw Hill Education, 2013.\n\n\n

2. C. L. Wadhwa, "High Voltage Engineering", New Age International Publishers, 2007.\n\n\n

3. D. V. Razevig (Translated by Dr. M. P. Chourasia), "High Voltage Engineering Fundamentals", Khanna Publishers, 1993.\n\n\n

4. E. Kuffel, W. S. Zaengl and J. Kuffel, "High Voltage Engineering Fundamentals", Newnes Publication, 2000.\n\n\n

5. R. Arora and W. Mosch "High Voltage and Electrical Insulation Engineering", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2011.\n\n\n

6. Various IS standards for HV Laboratory Techniques and Testing\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem7ele3">Industrial Electrical System</string>
<string name="IESeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

<b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Understand the electrical wiring systems for residential, commercial and industrial consumers, representing the systems with standard symbols and drawings, SLD.\n\n\n

•Understand various components of industrial electrical systems.\n\n\n

Analyze and select the proper size of various electrical

system components.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Electrical System Components (8 Hours) LTsystemwiringcomponents, selectionofcables, wires,switche s,distributionbox, meteringsystem, Tariff structure, protection components- Fuse, MCB, MCCB, ELCB, inverse current characteristics, symbols, single line diagram (SLD) of a wiring system, Contactor, Isolator, Relays, MPCB, Electric shock and Electrical safety practices\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Residential and Commercial Electrical Systems (8

Hours) Types of residential and commercial wiring systems, general rules and guidelines for installation, load calculation and sizing of wire, rating of main switch, distribution board and protection devices, earthing system calculations, requirements of commercial installation, deciding lighting scheme and number of lamps, earthing of commercial installation, selection and sizing of components.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 3: </font></b>\n\n\nIllumination Systems (6 Hours) Understanding various terms regarding light, lumen, intensity, candle power, lamp efficiency, specific consumption, glare, space to height ratio, waste light factor, depreciation factor, various illumination schemes, Incandescent lamps and modern luminaries like CFL, LED and their operation, energy saving in illumination systems, design of alighting scheme for a residential and commercial premises, flood lighting.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 4: </font></b>\n\n\nIndustrial Electrical Systems I (8 Hours) HT

connection, industrial substation, Transformer selection, Industrial loads, motors, starting of motors, SLD, Cable and Switchgear selection, Lightning Protection, Earthing design, Power factor correction - KVAR calculations, type of compensation, Introduction to PCC, MCC panels. Specifications of LT Breakers, MCB and other LT panel components.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Industrial Electrical Systems II (6 Hours) DG Systems, UPS System, Electrical Systems for the elevators, Battery banks, Sizing the DG, UPS and Battery Banks, Selection of UPS and Battery Banks.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Industrial Electrical System Automation (6

Hours) Study of basic PLC, Role of in automation, advantages of process automation, PLC based control system design, Panel Metering and Introduction to SCADA system for distribution automation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Text/Reference Books</font></b>\n\n\n

1. S.L. Uppal and G.C. Garg, "Electrical Wiring, Estimating &amp; Costing", Khanna publishers, 2008.\n\n\n

2. K. B. Raina, "Electrical Design, Estimating &amp; Costing", New age International, 2007.\n\n\n

3. S. Singh and R. D. Singh, "Electrical estimating and costing", Dhanpat Rai and Co., 1997.\n\n\n

4. Web site for IS Standards.\n\n\n

5. H. Joshi, "Residential Commercial and Industrial Systems", McGraw Hill Education, 2008.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem7ele4">Digital Control Systems</string>
<string name="DCSeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

<b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Obtain discrete representation of LTI systems.\n\n\n

Analyse stability of open loop and closed loop discrete-time systems.\n\n\n

Design and analyse digital controllers.\n\n\n

•Design state feedback and output feedback controllers.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Discrete Representation of Continuous Systems (6 hours) Basics of Digital Control Systems. Discrete representation of continuous systems. Sample and hold circuit. Mathematical Modelling of sample and hold circuit. Effects of Sampling and Quantization. Choice of sampling frequency. ZOH equivalent.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Discrete System Analysis (6 hours) Z-Transform and Inverse Z Transform for analyzing discrete time systems. Pulse Transfer function. Pulse transfer function of closed loop systems. Mapping from s-plane to z plane. Solution of Discrete time systems. Time response of discrete time system.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Stability of Discrete Time System (4 hours) Stabilityanalysisby Jurytest.Stabilityanalysisusingbilineartra nsformation.Designofdigitalcontrol system with dead beat response. Practical issues with dead beat response design.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n State Space Approach for discrete time systems (10 hours) State space models of discrete systems, State space analysis. Lyapunov Stability. Controllability, reach-ability, Reconstructibility and observability analysis. Effect of pole zero cancellation on the controllability &amp; observability.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Design of Digital Control System (8 hours) Design of Discrete PID Controller, Design of discrete state feedback controller. Design of set point tracker. Design of Discrete Observer for LTI System. Design of Discrete compensator.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6:</font></b>\n\n\n Discrete output feedback control (8 hours) Design of discrete output feedback control. Fast output sampling (FOS) and periodic output feedback controller design for discrete time systems.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text Books:\n\n\n</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Κ. Ogata, "Digital Control Engineering", Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, 1995.\n\n\n

2. M. Gopal, "Digital Control Engineering", Wiley Eastern, 1988.\n\n\n

3. G. F. Franklin, J. D. Powell and M. L. Workman, "Digital Control of Dynamic Systems", Addison-Wesley, 1998.\n\n\n

4. B.C. Kuo, "Digital Control System", Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1980.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="eeesem7ele5">Electrical And Hybrid Vehicles</string>
<string name="EHVeee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Understand the models to describe hybrid vehicles and their performance.\n\n\n

•Understand the different possible ways of energy storage.\n\n\n

Understand the different strategies related to energy storage systems.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Introduction (10 hours) Conventional Vehicles: Basics of vehicle performance, vehicle power source characterization, transmission characteristics, mathematical models to describe vehicle performance. Introduction to Hybrid Electric Vehicles: History of hybrid and electric vehicles, social and environmental importance of hybrid and electric vehicles, impact of modern drive-trains on energy supplies. Hybrid Electric Drive-trains: Basic concept of hybrid traction, introduction to various hybrid drive-train topologies, power flow control in hybrid drive-train topologies, fuel efficiency analysis.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>(Note: Module 2 was missing in official pdf of AKU syllabus)\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3: </font></b>\n\n\nElectric Trains (10 hours) Electric Drive-trains: Basic concept of electric traction, introduction to various electric drivetrain topologies, power flow control in electric drive-train topologies, fuel efficiency analysis. Electric Propulsion unit: Introduction to electric components used in hybrid and electric vehicles, Configuration and control of DC Motor drives, Configuration and control of Induction Motor drives, configuration and control of Permanent Magnet Motor drives, Configuration and control of Switch Reluctance Motor drives, drive system efficiency.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Energy Storage (10 hours) Energy Storage: Introduction to Energy Storage Requirements in Hybrid and Electric Vehicles, Battery based energy storage and its analysis, Fuel Cell based energy storage and its analysis, Super Capacitor based energy storage and its analysis, Flywheel based energy storage and its analysis, Hybridization of different energy storage devices. Sizing the drive system: Matching the electric machine and the internal combustion engine (ICE), Sizing the propulsion motor, sizing the power electronics, selecting the energy storage technology. Communications, supporting subsystems\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/References:\n\n\n</font></b>

1. C. Mi, M. A. Masrur and D. W. Gao, "Hybrid Electric Vehicles: Principles and Applications with Practical Perspectives", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2011.\n\n\n

2. S. Onori, L. Serrao and G. Rizzoni, "Hybrid Electric Vehicles: Energy Management Strategies", Springer, 2015.\n\n\n

3. M. Ehsani, Y. Gao, S. E. Gay and A. Emadi, "Modern Electric, Hybrid Electric, and FuelCell Vehicles: Fundamentals, Theory, and Design", CRC Press, 2004.\n\n\n

4. T. Denton, "Electric and Hybrid Vehicles", Routledge, 2016.\n\n\n

</string>

    <string name="eeesem8sub1">Open Elective-III</string>
<string name="eeeOE3">\n\n\n


    <b>CHOOSE ANY ONE SUBJECT:</b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Power Plant Engineering</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Objectives:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>To provide an overview of power plants and the associated energy conversion issues</b>\n\n\n

    <b>Contents:</b>\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 1</font></b>\n\n\n

Coal based thermal power plants, basic Rankine cycle and its modifications, layout of modern coal power plant, super critical boilers, FBC boilers, turbines, condensers, steam and heating rates. Sub systems of thermal power plants, fuel and ash handling, draught system, feed water treatment, binary cycles and cogeneration systems. (Lectures 8)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module : 2\n\n\n</font></b>

Gas turbine and combined cycle power plants, Brayton cycle analysis and optimization, components of gas turbine power plants, combined cycle power plants, (Lectures 4)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module : 3\n\n\n</font></b>

Basics of nuclear energy conversion, Layout and subsystems of nuclear power plants, Boiling Water Reactor (BWR), Pressurized Water Reactor (PWR), CANDU Reactor, Pressurized Heavy Water Reactor (PHWR), Fast Breeder Reactors (FBR), gas cooled and liquid metal cooled reactors, safety measures for nuclear power plants. (Lectures 8)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module : 4\n\n\n</font></b>

Hydroelectric power plants, Hydrological cycle, Rainfall &amp; run-off measurement &amp; plotting of various curves for estimating stream flow, site selection, classification, comparison with other types of power plant, typical layout and components, principles of wind, tidal, solar PV and solar thermal, geothermal, biogas and fuel cell power systems.

(Lectures 8)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module: 5\n\n\n</font></b>

Energy, economic and environmental issues, power tariffs, load distribution parameters, load curve, capital and operating cost of different power plants, pollution control technologies including waste disposal options for coal and nuclear plants, Geothermal power plants, Ocean thermal electric conversion, M.H.D power generation.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:\n\n\n</font></b>

Upon completion of the course, the students can understand the principles of operation for different power plants and their economics.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text Books:\n\n\n</font></b>\n\n\n

1 Power Plant Engineering, 5th Edition, Laxmi Publications(P) Ltd 3rd ea.\n\n\n

2 Nag P.K., Power Plant Engineering, 3r, Tata McGraw Hill, 2008.\n\n\n

3 El Wakil M.M., Power Plant Technology, Tata McGraw Hill, 2010.\n\n\n

4 Elliot T.C., Chen K and Swanekamp R.C., Power Plant Engineering, 2nd ed., McGraw

Hill, 1998.\n\n\n

    *****************************************************

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Automobile Engineering\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Objectives:\n\n\n</font></b>

    <b>To understand the construction and working principle of various parts of an automobile Contents:\n\n\n</b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 1\n\n\n</font></b>

Types of automobiles, vehicle construction and layouts, Car body Style, chassis, frame and body, vehicle aerodynamics, IC engines-components, function and materials, variable valve timing (VVT), Front engine front wheel drive, Front engine Rear wheel drive, foure wheel drive. (Lectures 6)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 2\n\n\n</font></b>

Engine auxiliary systems, electronic injection for SI and CI engines, unit injector system, rotary distributor type and common rail direct injection system, transistor based coil ignition &amp; capacitive discharge ignition systems, turbo chargers (WGT, VGT), engine emission control by 3-way catalytic converter system, Emission norms (Euro &amp; BS).

(Lectures 6)\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 3\n\n\n</font></b>

Transmission systems, clutch types, cone clutch, Single plate, multi plate, diaphragm spring &amp; centrifugal clutch, electromagnetic clutch &amp; construction, gear boxes- manual and automatic gear shift mechanisms, over drive principles, transfer box, Transaxles, flywheel, torque converter, propeller shaft, slip joints, universal joints, differential and rear axle, Hotchkiss drive and Torque tube drive.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 4\n\n\n</font></b>

Steering geometry and types of steering gear box, power steering, types of front axle, types of suspension systems, constructional details &amp; characteristics of Leaf spring, pneumatic and hydraulic braking systems, antilock braking system (ABS), electronic brake force distribution (EBD) and traction control.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 5\n\n\n</font></b>

Caster, Camber, King pin inclination Toe in Toe out, Full Floating, three quarter floating &amp;semi Floating rear axles.\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module: 6\n\n\n</font></b>

Alternative energy sources, natural gas, LPG, biodiesel, bio-ethanol, gasohol and hydrogen fuels in automobiles, modifications needed, performance, combustion &amp; emission characteristics of alternative fuels in SI and CI engines, Electric and Hybrid vehicles, application of Fuel Cells.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n

    <b>Upon completion of this course, students will understand the function of each automobile component and also have a clear idea about the overall vehicle performance.\n\n\n</b>

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text books:\n\n\n</font>
    </b>

1. Kirpal Singh, Automobile Engineering, ed., Standard Publishers, New Delhi, 1997.\n\n\n

Jain K.K. and Asthana R.B., Automobile Engineering, Tata McGraw Hill, New Delhi,\n\n\n

*Heitner, Automotive Mechanics, 2nd ed., East-West Press,

1999.\n\n\n

Heisler, Advanced Engine Technology, SAE International Publ., USA, 1998.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Practical:\n\n\n</font>
    </b>

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Automotive Clutches.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Automotive Transmission systems.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Automotive Drive Lines &amp; Differentials.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Multi-cylinder: Diesel and Petrol Engines.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Fuels supply systems.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Engine cooling &amp; lubricating Systems.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details,operation of the Automotive Suspension Systems.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Automotive Steering Systems.\n\n\n

•To study and prepare report on the constructional details, operation of the Automotive Brake systems.\n\n\n
**********************************<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
        E-Commerce and ERP\n\n\n</font></b>
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 1</font></b>\n\n\n

Introduction to E-Commerce: Evolution of E-commerce, Advantage and Disadvantage of E Commerce, Roadmap of E-Commerce in India. Business Models of E-Commerce: Model Based On Transaction Party: B2B, B2C, C2B, C2C.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 2\n\n\n</font></b>

E marketing: The scope of E-Marketing, Identifying Web Presence goals, Uniqueness of the web, Meeting the need of website visitors, Website Design Issues: Factors that make People Return to Your Site, Strategies for Website Development. Site Adhesion: Content, format and access: maintaining a Website, E- Advertising, [-Branding,\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 3</font></b>\n\n\n

E-Payment System: Digital Payment Requirement, Digital Token based E-Payment System, Electronic Cash, Smart card and Electronics payment system: Credit and Debit Card, Virtual Currency, Digital wallet, Risk of Electronics payment system, Digital Signature.\n\n\n

E Security: Security On the Internet: Network and Website Security Risk: Denial-of-Service attack, Viruses, Unauthorized access to computer Network. Security Standards: Firewall, Cryptography, Key Management, Password Systems, Digital certificates, Digital signatures.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 4</font></b>\n\n\n

Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP): Introductory Concepts, Advantages &amp; disadvantages of ERP, ERP and Related Technologies: - Business Process Reengineering, Data Warehousing, Data Mining, Supply Chain Management. ERP Implementation: ERP Implementation Life Cycle Implementation Methodology, Hidden Costs, Organizing Implementation - Contracts with Vendors, Consultants and Users, Project Management and Monitoring.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 5</font></b>\n\n\n

ERP Business Modules: Introduction to basic Modules of ERP System, Business Modules in an ERP Package- Finance - Manufacturing - Human Resource Plant Maintenance Materials Management - Quality Management - Sales and Distribution.\n\n\n

    <b>Case Study: Recent business issues on E-Commerce Perspective.</b>\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Text Books:\n\n\n</font></b>

Alexis Leon, "ERP Demystified", Tata McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

•E-Commerce An Indian Perspective by P.T.Joseph, PHI\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Reference Books</font></b>\n\n\n

K. Bajaj, D. Nag "E-Commerce, 2nd Edition, McGraw-Hill Education, New Delhi.\n\n\n
Bhaskar Bharat, "Electronic mmerce-Technology and Application", McGraw-Hill Education, New Delhi.\n\n\n

•Mary Sumner, "Enterprise Resource Planning", 2005, PHI Learning India Pvt. Ltd. /Pearson Education, New Delhi.\n\n\n

•Chan, "E-Commerce fundamentals and Applications", Wiley India, New Delhi.\n\n\n

•Vinod Kumar Garg and N.K.Venkata Krishnan, "Enterprise Resource Planning -concepts and Planning", Prentice Hall, 1998.\n\n\n

***

</string>

<string name="eeesem8sub2">Open Elective-IV</string>
<string name="OE3eee">\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    CHOOSE ANY ONE SUBJECT:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Electrical Materials:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    MODULE 1 ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING MATERIALS (6H)</font></b>\n\n\n

Introduction to Electrical Engineering Materials, Classification of materials, Material of importance-carbonated beverages container, Advanced Materials, Modern Material need, Atomic Structure and Interatomic Bonding, bonding forces and energies, secondary bonding and van-der-waals bonding,\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    MODULE II THE STRUCTURE OF CRYSTALLINE SOLIDS (8H)</font></b>\n\n\n

The structure of crystalline solids, crystallographic points, directions and planes, X-Ray diffraction, determination of crystalline structure, imperfections and defects in solids, diffusion mechanisms, steady state diffusion, diffusion in semiconducting materials, material of importance- Aluminum for integrated circuit interconnects, mechanical properties of material, stress strain behavior. Structure and properties of ceramics, crystal ceramics, silicate ceramics, material of importance-carbon nano-tubes, Imperfections in ceramics, application and processing of ceramics, Glass ceramics, refractories, abrasives, cements, materials of importance -piezoelectric ceramics\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    MODULE III INSULATING PROPERTIES OF MATERIAL (8H)\n\n\n</font></b>

Insulating materials; General Properties, Electrical Properties: Volume resistivity, surface resistance, dielectric loss, dielectric strength (breakdown voltage) dielectric constant, Thermal conductivity, Electro-thermal breakdown in solid dielectrics Insulating Materials and their applications:\n\n\n

Plastics, Definition and classification, Thermosetting materials, Phenol-formaldehyde resins (i.e. Bakelite) amino resins (urea formaldehyde and Malamine-formaldehyde), epoxy resins their important properties and applications, Thermo-plastic materials: Polyvinyl chloride (PVC), polyethelene, silicons, their important properties and applications, Bitumen - Mineral and insulating oil for transformers switchgear capacitors, high voltage insulated cables, insulating varnishes for coating and impregnation Enamels for winding wires, Glass fiber sleeves, SF6 their
 properties and applications\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    MODULE IV ELECTRICAL PROPERTIES OF MATERAILS (6H)</font></b>\n\n\n

Electrical conduction,electronic and ionic conduction, energy band structures in solids conduction in terms of band and atomic bonding models, electron mobility electrical resistivity of metals, materials of importance-aluminum electrical wires, semi conductivity, intrinsic semi conduction, extrinsic semi conduction, carrier mobility, semiconductor devices, electrical properties of polymers dielectric behavior, capacitance, field vectors and polarization, types of polarization, frequency dependence of the dielectric constant, dielectric materials, ferroelectricity, piezoelectricity.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    MODULE V OPTICAL AND MAGNETIC PRPERTIES OF MATERIALS (10 H)\n\n\n</font></b>

Optical properties basic concepts, electromagnetic radiation, light interactions with solids atomic and electronic interactions optical properties of metals, optical properties of nonmetals, refraction, reflection, absorption, transmission, applications of optical phenomena, luminescence, Materials of importance -light-emitting diodes, photoconductivity, lasers, optical fibers in communications Diamagnetism and Paramagnetism Ferromagnetism, Antiferromagnetism and Ferrimagnetism, The Influence of Temperature on Magnetic Behavior, Domains and Hysteresis, Magnetic Anisotropy, Soft Magnetic Materials, Materials of Importance-An Iron-Silicon Alloy That Is Used in Transformer Cores, Hard Magnetic Materials Magnetic Storage, Superconductivity\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    MODULE VI SUPERCONDUCTIVITY (6H)\n\n\n</font></b>

Properties of superconductors, London equations, Quantum explanation of superconductivity, Applications of superconductors. Nanomaterials: Introduction to nanotechnology, Nanowire and Nanotube, Carbon nanotubes, Single wall carbon nanotubes, Multiwall carbon nanotubes, Fabrications, Properties and applications\n\n\n

Economic, Environmental, and Societal Issues in Materials Science and Engineering introduction, economic considerations, component design, materials, manufacturing techniques, environmental and societal considerations, recycling issues in materials science and engineering, materials of importance-biodegradable and biorenewable polymers/ plastics\n\n\n
***********************************************

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 110814 Satellite Communication 3L: OT: OP 3 Credits\n\n\n</font>
</b>

1 Introduction to Satellite Communication: Principles and architecture of satellite

Communication, Brief history of Satellite systems, advantages, disadvantages, applications and frequency bands used for satellite communication.\n\n\n


2 Orbital Mechanics: Orbital equations, Kepler\'s laws, Apogee and Perigee for an elliptical orbit, evaluation of velocity, orbital period, angular velocity etc. of a satellite, concepts of Solar day and Sidereal day\n\n\n

3 Satellite sub-systems: Study of Architecture and Roles of various sub systems of a satellite system such as Telemetry, tracking, command and monitoring (TTC and M), Attitude and orbit control system (AOCS), Communication sub-system.\n\n\n

4 Typical Phenomena in Satellite Communication: Solar Eclipse on satellite, its effects, remedies for Eclipse, Sun Transit Outage phenomena, its effects and remedies, Doppler frequency shift Phenomena and expression for Doppler shift\n\n\n

5 Flux density and received signal power equations, Calculation of System noise temperature for satellite receiver, noise power calculation, C/N ratio calculations in clear air and rainy conditions\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    •No. Name of Authors/Books/Publishers\n\n\n</font></b>

Timothy Pratt Charles W. Bostian, Jeremy E. Allnutt: Satellite Communications; Wiley\n\n\n

•Tri T. Ha: Digital Satellite Communications: Tata McGraw Hill\n\n\n

Dennis Roddy: Satellite Communication: 4th Edition, McGraw Hill.\n\n\n

1 Biomedical signals and Physiological transducers: Source of biomedical signal, Origin of bioelectric signals, recording electrodes, Electrodes for ECG, EMG and EEG Physiological transducers: Pressure, Temperature, photoelectric and ultrasound Transducers. Measurement in Respiratory system: Physiology of respiratory system, Measurement of breathing mechanics Spiro meter, Respiratory therapy equipments Inhalators ventilators and Respirators, Humidifiers, Nebulizers Aspirators, Biomedical recorders: ECG, EEG and EMG.\n\n\n

 2 Patient Monitoring systems and Audiometers: Cardiac monitor, Bed-side patient monitor, measurement of heart rate, blood pressure, temperature, respiration rate, Arrhythmia monitor, Methods of monitoring fatal heart rate, Monitoring labor activity. Audiometers: Audiometers, Blood cell counters, Oximeter, Blood flow meter, cardiac output measurement, Blood gas analyz-ers.\n\n\n

3 Modern Imaging systems: Introduction, Basic principle and Block diagram of x-ray machine, x-ray Computed Tomography (CT), Magnetic resonance imaging system (NMR), ultrasonic imaging system. Eco-Cardiograph, Eco Encephalography, Ophthalmic scans, MRI. Therapeutic Equipments: Cardiac pacemakers, cardiac defibrillators, Hemodialysis machine, Surgical diathermy machine.\n\n\n

4 Patient\'s safety: Precaution, safety codes for electro medical equipment, Electric

safety analyzer, Testing of biomedical equipment, Ultrasound therapy unit. Electrotherapy Equipments, Ventilators.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    No. Name of Authors/Books/Publishers\n\n\n</font></b>

1 "Hand book of Biomedical Instrumentation", R.S. Khandpur,\n\n\n

2 "Biomedical Instruments: Theory and Design", Walter Welko- Witiz and Sid Doutsch, Wiley\n\n\n

3 "Biomedical Instrumentation and Measurements", Lesile Cromwell, Fred J. Weibell and Erich A. Pfeiffer, PHI\n\n\n

4 "Introduction to Biomedical Equipment Technology", Joseph J. Carr and John M. Brown, Pearson\n\n\n

5 "Textbook of Biomedical Instrumentation System", Shakti Chatterjee, Cengage Learning\n\n\n

</string>
<string name="eeesem8sub3">Program Elective-V</string>
<string name="PE5eee">\n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    CHOOSE ANY ONE SUBJECT:\n\n\n</font></b>
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Fiber Optic Communications [EC]</font></b>\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b>
At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>\n\n\n

Understand the principles fiber-optic communication, the components and the bandwidth advantages.\n\n\n

Understand the properties of the optical fibers and optical components.\n\n\n

Understand operation of lasers, LEDs, and detectors\n\n\n

•Analyze system performance of optical communication systems\n\n\n

•Design optical networks and understand non-linear effects in optical fibers\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 1: </font></b>\n\n\nIntroduction to vector nature of light, propagation of light, propagation of light ina cylindrical dielectric rod, Ray model, wave model.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 2:</font></b>\n\n\n Different types of optical fibers, Modal analysis of a step index fiber. Signal degradation on optical fiber due to dispersion and attenuation. Fabrication of fibers and measurement techniques like OTDR.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Optical sources - LEDs and Lasers, Photo-detectors -pin-diodes, APDs, detectorresponsivity, noise, optical receivers. Optical link design - BER calculation, quantum limit, power penalties.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\nOptical switches - coupled mode analysis of directional couplers, electroopticswitches. \n\n\n
    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 5: </font></b>\n\n\nOptical amplifiers - EDFA, Raman amplifier.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 6: </font></b>\n\n\n WDM and DWDM systems. Principles of WDM networks.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Module 7:</font></b>\n\n\n Nonlinear effects in fiber optic links. Concept of self-phase modulation, groupvelocity dispersion and solition based communication.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Text/Reference Books\n\n\n</font></b>

J. Keiser, Fibre Optic communication, McGraw-Hill, 5th Ed. 2013 (Indian Edition).\n\n\n

•T. Tamir, Integrated optics, (Topics in Applied Physics Vol.7), Springer-Verlag, 1975.\n\n\n

J. Gowar, Optical communication systems, Prentice Hall India, 1987.\n\n\n

•S.E. Miller and A.G. Chynoweth, eds., Optical fibres telecommunications, Academic Press, 1979.\n\n\n

•G. Agrawal, Nonlinear fibre optics, Academic Press, 2nd Ed. 1994.\n\n\n

•G. Agrawal, Fiber optic Communication Systems, John Wiley and sons, New York, 1997\n\n\n

•F.C. Allard, Fiber Optics Handbook for engineers and scientists, McGraw Hill, New York (1990).\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Micro and Nano-Electronics [EC]\n\n\n</font></b>
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b>
    At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>
    \n\n\n

•Analyze semiconductor devices, through numerical problems, using fundamental characteristics of semiconductor materials, such as carrier densities, transport, lifetime, generation and recombination.\n\n\n

•Understand various aspects of nano-technology and the processes involved in making nano components and material.\n\n\n

•Leverage advantages of the nano-materials and appropriate use in solving practical problems.\n\n\n

•Understand various aspects of nano-technology and theprocesses involved in making nano components and material.\n\n\n\

•Leverage advantages of the nano-materials and appropriate use in solving practical problems.\n\n\n

    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Module 1:</font></b>\n\n\n Semiconductor crystal lattice and growth of high

purity semiconductor materials Energy bands, Fermi-Dirac distribution function, and energy band diagrams Doping of semiconductors; carrier concentration in doped and intrinsic semiconductors Carrier transport phenomena - drift and diffusion current; device current equations\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 2: </font></b>\n\n\nGeneration, recombination, carrier lifetime

and mobility Semiconductor junctions p-n diodes: creation of space charge region in a p-n junction and current-voltage characteristics Metal-semiconductor contacts-Schottky and Ohmic contact LED-Application of p-n junction Basic operation principle of BJT and MOSFET transistors\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 3:</font></b>\n\n\n Introduction to nanotechnology, meso structures, Basics of Quantum Mechanics: Schrodinger equation, Density of States. Particle in a box Concepts, Degeneracy. Band Theory of Solids. Kronig-Penny Model. Brillouin Zones.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 4:</font></b>\n\n\n Shrink-down approaches: Introduction, CMOS Scaling, The nanoscale MOSFET, Finfets, Vertical MOSFETs, limits to scaling, system integration limits (interconnect issues etc.),\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 5:</font></b>\n\n\n Resonant Tunneling Diode, Coulomb dots, Quantum

blockade, Single electron transistors, Carbon nanotube electronics, Bandstructure and transport, devices, applications, 2D semiconductors and electronic devices, Graphene, atomistic simulation\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
        Text/ Reference Books:</font>
</b>
    \n\n\n

•Semiconductor Physics and Devices, Donald A. Neamen, 4th edition, McGraw Hill Higher Education, ISBN # 978-0-07-352958-5

G.W. Hanson, Fundamentals of Nanoelectronics, Pearson, 2009.\n\n\n

•W. Ranier, Nanoelectronics and Information Technology (Advanced Electronic Material and Novel Devices), Wiley-VCH, 2003.\n\n\n

•K.E. Drexler, Nanosystems, Wiley, 1992.\n\n\n

J.H. Davies, The Physics of Low-Dimensional Semiconductors, Cambridge University Press, 1998.\n\n\n

C.P. Poole, F. J. Owens, Introduction to Nanotechnology, Wiley, 2003\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Transducer &amp; Signal Conditioning\n\n\n</font></b>
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b>
At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</b>

• Understand the basics oknowledge of the principles, working and characteristics of transducers and the associated signal conditioning circuits for industrial applications.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 1: Transducers (10 hours)</font></b>\n\n\n

Introduction, classification, mechanical devices as primary detectors, basic requirements of a transducer, electrical transducers, type of transducers for measuring displacement, strain, vibration, pressure, flow, temperature, force, torque, liquid level, humidity, P. H. value, velocity (angular &amp; linear), acceleration, basic principles of resistive transducers, inductive transducers, capacitive transducers, thermoelectric transducers, piezoelectric transducers, hall effect transducers, electromechanical transducers, photoelectric transducers, digital transducers.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 2: Signal Processing Circuits (11 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

crossing detector, zero crossing detector with hysteresis, inverting and non-inverting amplifiers, voltage-follower, adder, subtractor, multiplier, divider, integrator, differentiator, voltage to current converter, current to voltage converter, phase shifter circuit, absolute-value circuit, peak detector, ac to dc converter, logarithmic converter, differential-amplifier, instrumentation amplifier, analog modulators &amp; demodulators.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 3: Data Display and Recording Systems (6 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Introduction to analog and digital display methods, analog recorders, C.R.O., magnetic tape recorders, digital input-output devices, digital frequency meter, digital voltmeter.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 4: Data Transmission and Telemetry (6 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Introduction, characteristics of frequency division multiplexing, time- division multiplexing, transmission channels and media.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 5: Data Acquisition and Conversion (7 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Introduction, signal conditioning of the inputs, single channel. DAS, Multi-channel DAS, data conversion, multiplexer, S/ H circuit, A/D converter.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Text / References:</font></b>\n\n\n

D. V. S. Murty, "Transducers and Instrumentation", Prentice-Hall of India Private Limited, 2013.\n\n\n

C.S. Rangan, G.R. Sarma and V. S.V. Mani, "Instrumentation Devices &amp; Systems", Mc Graw Hill.\n\n\n

A. K. Sawhney, "A course in Electrical &amp; Electronic Measurements &amp; Instrumentation", Dhanpat Rai &amp; Sons.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Power System Protection</font></b>\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
        Course Outcomes: At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to</font>
</b>\n\n\n

•Understand the different components of a protection system.\n\n\n

•Evaluate fault current due to different types of fault in a network.\n\n\n

Understand the protection schemes for different power system components.\n\n\n

Understand the basic principles of digital protection.\n\n\n

Understand system protection schemes, and the use of wide-area measurements.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 1: Introduction and Components of a Protection System (4 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Principles of Power System Protection, Relays, Instrument transformers, Circuit Breakers\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 2: Faults and Over-Current Protection (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Review of Fault Analysis, Sequence Networks. Introduction to Overcurrent Protection and overcurrent relay co-ordination.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 3: Equipment Protection Schemes (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Directional, Distance, Differential protection. Transformer and Generator protection. Bus bar Protection, Bus Bar arrangement schemes.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 4: Digital Protection (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Computer-aided protection, Fourier analysis and estimation of Phasors from DFT. Sampling, aliasing issues.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 5: Modeling and Simulation of Protection Schemes (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

CT/PT modeling and standards, Simulation of transients using Electro-Magnetic Transients (EMT) programs. Relay Testing.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 6: System Protection (4 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Effect of Power Swings on Distance Relaying. System Protection Schemes. Under-frequency, under- voltage and df/ dt relays, Out-of-step protection, Synchro-phasors, Phasor Measurement Units and Wide-Area Measurement Systems (WAMS). Application of WAMS for improving protection systems.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Text/References\n\n\n</font></b>

J. L. Blackburn, "Protective Relaying: Principles and Applications", Marcel Dekker, New York, 1987.\n\n\n

•Y. G.Paithankar and S. R. Bhide, "Fundamentals of power system protection, Prentice Hall, India, 2010.\n\n\n

•A. G. Phadke and J. S. Thorp, "Computer Relaying for Power Systems", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1988.\n\n\n

•A. G. Phadke and J. S. Thorp, "Synchronized Phasor Measurements and their Applications", Springer, 2008.\n\n\n

D. Reimert, "Protective Relaying for Power Generation Systems", Taylor and Francis, 2006.\n\n\n

</string>

<string name="eeesem8sub4">Program Elective-VI</string>
<string name="PE4eee">\n\n\n


    <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>CHOOSE ANY ONE SUBJECT:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Smart Grid Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b>
    At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to\n\n\n</b>

Understand thebackground and fundamental building blocks of smart grid with stringent emphasis on practical applications in the existing power system network\n\n\n

•Emphasizes on renewable energy source integration in present grids as well as in micro and nano grids as part of the course and explores its issues in operation, analysis, management, control, protection and monitoring.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 1: Introduction to Smart Grid: (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Evolution of Electric Grid, Concept, Definitions and Need for Smart Grid, Smart grid drivers, functions, opportunities, challenges and benefits.\n\n\n

Difference between conventional &amp; Smart Grid, Concept of Resilient &amp;Self-Healing Grid, Present development &amp; International policies in Smart Grid, Diverse perspectives from experts and global Smart Grid initiatives.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 2: Smart Grid Technologies (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Technology Drivers, Smart energy resources, Smart substations, Substation Automation, Feeder Automation, Transmission systems: EMS, FACTS and HVDC, Wide area monitoring, Protection and Control, Distribution Systems: DMS, Volt/Var control, Fault Detection, Isolation and service restoration, Outage management, High-Efficiency, Distribution Transformers, Phase Shifting Transformers, Plug in Hybrid Electric Vehicles (PHEV).\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 3: Smart Meters and Advanced Metering Infrastructure (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Introduction to Smart Meters, Advanced Metering infrastructure (AMI) drivers and benefits, AMI protocols, standards and initiatives,. AMI needs in the smart grid, Phasor Measurement, Unit (PMU), Intelligent Electronic Devices (IED) &amp; their application for monitoring &amp; protection.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 4: Power Quality Management in Smart Grid: (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Power Quality &amp; EMC in Smart Grid, Power Quality issues of Grid connected Renewable Energy Sources, Power Quality Conditioners for Smart Grid, Web based Power Quality monitoring, Power Quality Audit.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 5: High Performance Computing for Smart Grid Applications (8 hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Local Area Network (LAN), House Area Network (HAN), Wide Area Network (WAN), Broad band over Power line (BPL), IP based Protocols, Basics of Web Service and CLOUD Computing to make Smart Grids smarter, Cyber Security for Smart Grid\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
        Text / References:\n\n\n</font>
</b>

•Vehbi C. Giingor, Dilan Sahin, Taskin Kocak, Salih Ergiit, Concettina Buccella, Carlo Cecati, and Gerhard P. Hancke: Smart Grid Technologies- Communication Technologies and Standards IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics, Vol. 7, No. 4, November 2011\n\n\n

Xi Fang, Satyajayant Misra, Guoliang Xue, and Dejun Yang: Smart Grid - The New and Improved Power Grid- A Survey, IEEE Transaction on Smart Grids, 2011.\n\n\n

•Stuart Borlase: Smart Grid-Infrastructure, Technology and Solutions, CRC Press, 2012.\n\n\n

A Keyhani, M Marwali, "Smart power grids",.\n\n\n

ArunPhadke, "omputer Relaying for Power Systems",\n\n\n
•Nikos Hatziargyriou, "Microgrids Architecture and control",.\n\n\n

Fang Lin Luo, Hong Ye, "Renewable Energy Systems",.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Wind and Solar Energy Systems\n\n\n</font></b>
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Course Outcomes:</font></b>\n\n\n
<b>
    At the end of this course, students will demonstrate the ability to\n\n\n</b>


•Understand the energy scenario and the consequent growth of the power generation from renewable energy sources.\n\n\n

•Understand the basic physics of wind and solar power generation.\n\n\n

•Understand the power electronic interfaces for wind and solar generation.\n\n\n

Understand the issues related to the grid-integration of solar and wind energy systems.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 1: Physics of Wind Power: (5 Hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

History of wind power, Indian and Global statistics, Wind physics, Betz limit, Tip speed ratio, stall and pitch control, Wind speed statistics-probability distributions, Wind speed and power-cumulative distribution functions.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
Module 2: Wind generator topologies: (12 Hours)\n\n\n
</font></b>
Review of modem wind turbine technologies, Fixed and Variable speed wind turbines, Induction Generators, Doubly-Fed Induction Generators and their characteristics, Permanent-Magnet Synchronous Generators, Power electronics converters. Generator-Converter configurations, Converter Control.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 3: The Solar Resource: (3 Hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Introduction, solar radiation spectra, solar geometry, Earth Sun angles, observer Sun angles, solarday length, Estimation of solar energy availability.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 4: Solar photovoltaic: (8 Hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Technologies-Amorphous, monocrystalline, polycrystalline; V-I characteristics of a PV cell, PV module, array, Power Electronic Converters for Solar Systems, Maximum Power Point Tracking (MPPT) algorithms Converter Control.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 5: Network Integration Issues: (8 Hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Overview of grid code technical requirements. Fault ride-through for wind farms -real and reactive power regulation, voltage and frequency operating limits, solar PV and wind farm behavior during grid disturbances. Power quality issues. Power system interconnection experiences in the world. Hybrid and isolated operations of solar PV and wind systems.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
    Module 6: Solar thermal power generation: (3 Hours)\n\n\n</font></b>

Technologies, Parabolic trough, central receivers, parabolic dish, Fresnel, solar pond, elementary analysis.\n\n\n
<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>
        Text / References:</font>
</b>\n\n\n

•T. Ackermann, "Wind Power in Power Systems", John Wiley and Sons Ltd.,2005.\n\n\n

•G. M. Masters, "Renewable and Efficient Electric Power Systems", John Wiley and Sons, 2004.\n\n\n

•S. P. Sukhatme, "Solar Energy: Principles of Thermal Collection and Storage", McGraw Hi11,1984.\n\n\n

•H. Siegfried and R. Waddington, "Grid integration of wind energy conversion systems" John Wiley and Sons Ltd.,2006.\n\n\n
•G. N. Tiwari and M. K. Ghosal, "Renewable Energy Applications", Narosa Publications, 2004.\n\n\n

J. A. Duffie and W. A. Beckman, "Solar Engineering of Thermal Processes", John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1991.\n\n\n

</string>









<string name="eeesem8sub5">Project-II</string>
<string name="peee2">
    PROJECT
</string>



























</resources>