<resources>
    <string name="app_name">My Syllabus</string>
    <string name="navigation_open">Open Navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_close">close Navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="hint">Enter your name </string>
    <string name="text">Get Started</string>
    <string name="text2">Get All Your Syllabus on Our App!</string>
    <string name="title_activity_home">home</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_activity_aeronautical">Aeronautical</string>
    <string name="title_activity_scrolling">ScrollingActivity</string>
    <string name="Semester1ST">1ST Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester2ND">2ND Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester3RD">3RD Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester4TH">4TH Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester5th">5TH Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester6TH">6TH Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester7TH">7TH Semester</string>
    <string name="Semester8TH">8TH Semester</string>
    <string name="Aero">AERONAUTICAL</string>
    <string name="cse">CSE</string>
    <string name="ai">AI ML</string>
    <string name="eee">EEE</string>
    <string name="mechanical">MECHANICAL</string>
    <string name="mechanicalelective">MECHANICAL ELECTIVE</string>
    <string name="civil">CIVIL</string>
    <string name="sub1">Basic Electrical Engineering</string>
    <string name="bee"> \n\n\n<b> <font fgcolor='#F700FF'> MODULE 1: DC CIRCUITS (8 LECTURES)></font></b>\n \n\n

ELECTRICAL CIRCUIT ELEMENTS (R, L AND C), VOLTAGE AND CURRENT SOURCES, KIRCHHOFF CURRENT AND VOLTAGE LAWS, ANALYSIS OF SIMPLE CIRCUITS WITH DC EXCITATION. STAR-DELTA CONVERSION, NETWORK THEOREMS (SUPERPOSITION, THEVENIN, NORTON AND MAXIMUM POWER TRANSFER THEOREMS). TIME-DOMAIN ANALYSIS OF FIRST-ORDER RL AND RC CIRCUITS \n\n\n

<b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: AC CIRCUITS (8 LECTURES)</font></b> \n \n\n

REPRESENTATION OF SINUSOIDAL WAVEFORMS, PEAK, RMS AND AVERAGE VALUES (FORM FACTOR AND PEAK FACTOR), IMPEDANCE OF SERIES AND PARALLEL CIRCUIT, PHASOR REPRESENTATION, REAL POWER, REACTIVE POWER, APPARENT POWER, POWER FACTOR, POWER TRIANGLE. ANALYSIS OF SINGLE-PHASE AC CIRCUITS CONSISTING OF R, L, C, RL, RC, RLC COMBINATIONS (SERIES AND PARALLEL), RESONANCE. THREE-PHASE BALANCED CIRCUITS, VOLTAGE AND CURRENT RELATIONS IN STAR AND DELTA CONNECTIONS. \n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: MAGNETIC CIRCUITS: (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

INTRODUCTION, SERIES AND PARALLEL MAGNETIC CIRCUITS, ANALYSIS OF SERIES AND PARALLEL MAGNETIC CIRCUITS. \n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: TRANSFORMERS (6 LECTURES)</font></b> \n\n\n

MAGNETIC MATERIALS, BH CHARACTERISTICS, IDEAL AND PRACTICAL TRANSFORMER, EMF EQUATION, EQUIVALENT CIRCUIT, LOSSES IN TRANSFORMERS, REGULATION AND EFFICIENCY. AUTO-TRANSFORMER AND THREE-PHASE TRANSFORMER CONNECTIONS. \n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: ELECTRICAL MACHINES (10 LECTURES)</font></b> \n\n\n

CONSTRUCTION, WORKING, TORQUE-SPEED CHARACTERISTIC AND SPEED CONTROL OF SEPARATELY EXCITED DC MOTOR. GENERATION OF ROTATING MAGNETIC FIELDS, CONSTRUCTION AND WORKING OF A THREE-PHASE INDUCTION MOTOR, SIGNIFICANCE OF TORQUE-SLIP CHARACTERISTIC. LOSS COMPONENTS AND EFFICIENCY, STARTING AND SPEED CONTROL OF INDUCTION MOTOR. CONSTRUCTION AND WORKING OF SYNCHRONOUS GENERATORS. \n \n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6: ELECTRICAL INSTALLATIONS (6 LECTURES)</font></b> \n\n\n

COMPONENTS OF LT SWITCHGEAR: SWITCH FUSE UNIT (SFU), MCB, ELCB, MCCB, TYPES OF WIRES AND CABLES, EARTHING. TYPES OF BATTERIES, IMPORTANT CHARACTERISTICS FOR BATTERIES. ELEMENTARY CALCULATIONS FOR ENERGY CONSUMPTION, POWER FACTOR IMPROVEMENT AND BATTERY BACKUP. \n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT / REFERENCE BOOKS</font></b> \n\n\n

~D. P. KOTHARI AND I. J. NAGRATH, "BASIC ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING", TATA MCGRAW HILL, 2010. \n\n\n

~D. C. KULSHRESHTHA, "BASIC ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING", MCGRAW HILL, 2009. \n\n\n

~L. S. BOBROW, "FUNDAMENTALS OF ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING", OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS, 2011. \n\n\n

~E. HUGHES, "ELECTRICAL AND ELECTRONICS TECHNOLOGY", PEARSON, 2010. \n\n\n

~V. D. TORO, "ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING FUNDAMENTALS", PRENTICE HALL INDIA, 1989. \n\n\n

~ BASIC ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING BY FITZERALD, ET AL, TATA MCGRAW HILL \n\n\n

~FUNDAMENTALS OF ELECTRICAL ENGG. BY R. PRASAD, PHI PUBLICATION \n\n\n

~BASIC ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING BY V.K. MEHTA AND ROHIT MEHTA, S.CHAND PUBLICATION</string>
    \n\n\n


    <string name="sub2">Engineering Graphics And Design</string>
    <string name="edg">\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:1 T:0 P:4 Credit:3</font></b> \n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>TRADITIONAL ENGINEERING GRAPHICS:</font></b>\n\n\n

PRINCIPLES OF ENGINEERING GRAPHICS; ORTHOGRAPHIC PROJECTION; DESCRIPTIVE GEOMETRY; DRAWING PRINCIPLES; ISOMETRIC PROJECTION; SURFACE DEVELOPMENT; PERSPECTIVE; READING A DRAWING; SECTIONAL VIEWS; DIMENSIONING and TOLERANCES; TRUE LENGTH, ANGLE; INTERSECTION, SHORTEST DISTANCE.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>COMPUTER GRAPHICS:</font></b>\n\n\n

ENGINEERING GRAPHICS SOFTWARE; -SPATIAL TRANSFORMATIONS; ORTHOGRAPHIC PROJECTIONS; MODEL VIEWING; CO-ORDINATE SYSTEMS; MULTI-VIEW PROJECTION; EXPLODED ASSEMBLY; MODEL VIEWING; ANIMATION; SPATIAL MANIPULATION; SURFACE MODELLING; SOLID MODELLING, INTRODUCTION TO BUILDING INFORMATION MODELLING (BIM).\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>(EXCEPT THE BASIC ESSENTIAL CONCEPTS, MOST OF THE TEACHING PART CAN HAPPEN CONCURRENTLY IN THE LABORATORY)</font></b>\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: INTRODUCTION TO ENGINEERING DRAWING</font></b>\n\n\n

PRINCIPLES OF ENGINEERING GRAPHICS AND THEIR SIGNIFICANCE, USAGE OF DRAWING INSTRUMENTS, LETTERING, CONIC SECTIONS INCLUDING THE RECTANGULAR HYPERBOLA (GENERAL METHOD ONLY); CYCLOID, EPICYCLOID, HYPOCYCLOID AND INVOLUTE; SCALES - PLAIN, DIAGONAL AND VERNIER SCALES\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: ORTHOGRAPHIC PROJECTIONS</font></b>\n\n\n

PRINCIPLES OF ORTHOGRAPHIC PROJECTIONS-CONVENTIONS -PROJECTIONS OF POINTS AND LINES INCLINED TO BOTH PLANES; PROJECTIONS OF PLANES INCLINED PLANES -AUXILIARY PLANES \n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: PROJECTIONS OF REGULAR SOLIDS </font></b>\n\n\n

THOSE INCLINED TO BOTH THE PLANES- AUXILIARY VIEWS; DRAW SIMPLE ANNOTATION, DIMENSIONING AND SCALE. FLOOR PLANS THAT INCLUDE: WINDOWS, DOORS, AND FIXTURES SUCH AS WC, BATH, SINK, SHOWER, ETC.\n\n\n


  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: SECTIONS AND SECTIONAL VIEWS OF RIGHT ANGULAR SOLIDS </font></b>\n\n\n

COVERING, PRISM, CYLINDER, PYRAMID, CONE - AUXILIARY VIEWS; DEVELOPMENT OF SURFACES OF RIGHT REGULAR SOLIDS-PRISM, PYRAMID, CYLINDER AND CONE; DRAW THE SECTIONAL ORTHOGRAPHIC VIEWS OF GEOMETRICAL SOLIDS, OBJECTS FROM INDUSTRY AND DWELLINGS (FOUNDATION TO SLAB ONLY)\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: ISOMETRIC PROJECTIONS</font></b>\n\n\n

PRINCIPLES OF ISOMETRIC PROJECTION-ISOMETRIC SCALE, ISOMETRIC VIEWS, CONVENTIONS; ISOMETRIC VIEWS OF LINES, PLANES, SIMPLE AND COMPOUND SOLIDS; CONVERSION OF ISOMETRIC VIEWS TO ORTHOGRAPHIC VIEWS AND VICE-VERSA, CONVENTIONS \n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6: OVERVIEW OF COMPUTER GRAPHICS</font></b> \n\n\n

LISTING THE COMPUTER TECHNOLOGIES THAT IMPACT ON GRAPHICAL COMMUNICATION, DEMONSTRATING KNOWLEDGE OF THE THEORY OF CAD SOFTWARE [SUCH AS: THE MENU SYSTEM, TOOLBARS (STANDARD, OBJECT PROPERTIES, DRAW, MODIFY AND DIMENSION), DRAWING AREA (BACKGROUND, CROSSHAIRS, COORDINATE SYSTEM), DIALOG BOXES AND WINDOWS, SHORTCUT MENUS (BUTTON BARS), THE COMMAND LINE (WHERE APPLICABLE), THE STATUS BAR, DIFFERENT METHODS OF ZOOM AS USED IN CAD, SELECT AND ERASE OBJECTS.; ISOMETRIC VIEWS OF LINES, PLANES, SIMPLE AND COMPOUND SOLIDS] \n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 7: CUSTOMISATION and CAD DRAWING</font></b>\n\n\n

CONSISTING OF SET UP OF THE DRAWING PAGE AND THE PRINTER, INCLUDING SCALE SETTINGS, SETTING UP OF UNITS AND DRAWING LIMITS; ISO AND ANSI STANDARDS FOR COORDINATE DIMENSIONING AND TOLERANCING; ORTHOGRAPHIC CONSTRAINTS, SNAP TO OBJECTS MANUALLY AND AUTOMATICALLY; PRODUCING DRAWINGS BY USING VARIOUS COORDINATE INPUT ENTRY METHODS TO DRAW STRAIGHT LINES, APPLYING VARIOUS WAYS OF DRAWING CIRCLES. \n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 8: ANNOTATIONS, LAYERING and OTHER FUNCTIONS</font></b>\n\n\n

COVERING APPLYING DIMENSIONS TO OBJECTS, APPLYING ANNOTATIONS TO DRAWINGS; SETTING UP AND USE OF LAYERS, LAYERS TO CREATE DRAWINGS, CREATE, EDIT AND USE CUSTOMIZED LAYERS; CHANGING LINE LENGTHS THROUGH MODIFYING EXISTING LINES (EXTEND/ LENGTHEN); PRINTING DOCUMENTS TO PAPER USING THE PRINT COMMAND; ORTHOGRAPHIC PROJECTION TECHNIQUES; DRAWING SECTIONAL VIEWS OF COMPOSITE RIGHT REGULAR GEOMETRIC SOLIDS AND PROJECT THE TRUE SHAPE OF THE SECTIONED SURFACE; DRAWING ANNOTATION, COMPUTER-AIDED DESIGN (CAD) SOFTWARE MODELING OF PARTS AND ASSEMBLIES. PARAMETRIC AND NON-PARAMETRIC SOLID, SURFACE, AND WIREFRAME MODELS. PART EDITING AND TWO-DIMENSIONAL DOCUMENTATION OF MODELS. PLANAR PROJECTION THEORY, INCLUDING SKETCHING OF PERSPECTIVE, ISOMETRIC, MULTIVIEW, AUXILIARY, AND SECTION VIEWS. SPATIAL VISUALIZATION EXERCISES. DIMENSIONING GUIDELINES, TOLERANCING TECHNIQUES; DIMENSIONING AND SCALE MULTI VIEWS OF DWELLING.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 9: DEMONSTRATION OF A SIMPLE TEAM DESIGN PROJECT THAT ILLUSTRATES</font></b>\n\n\n

GEOMETRY AND TOPOLOGY OF ENGINEERED COMPONENTS: CREATION OF ENGINEERING MODELS AND THEIR PRESENTATION IN STANDARD 2D BLUEPRINT FORM AND AS 3D WIRE-FRAME AND SHADED SOLIDS; MESHED TOPOLOGIES FOR ENGINEERING ANALYSIS AND TOOL-PATH GENERATION FOR COMPONENT MANUFACTURE; GEOMETRIC DIMENSIONING AND TOLERANCING; USE OF SOLID-MODELING SOFTWARE FOR CREATING ASSOCIATIVE MODELS AT THE COMPONENT AND ASSEMBLY LEVELS. FLOOR PLANS THAT INCLUDE: WINDOWS, DOORS, AND FIXTURES SUCH AS WC, BATH, SINK, SHOWER, ETC. APPLYING COLOUR CODING ACCORDING TO BUILDING DRAWING PRACTICE; DRAWING SECTIONAL ELEVATION SHOWING FOUNDATION TO CEILING; INTRODUCTION TO BUILDING INFORMATION MODELLING (BIM).\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT/REFERENCE BOOKS:</font></b>\n\n\n

~ BHATT N.D., PANCHAL V.M. and INGLE P.R., (2014), ENGINEERING DRAWING, CHAROTAR PUBLISHING HOUSE\n\n\n

~SHAH, M.B. and RANA B.C. (2008), ENGINEERING DRAWING AND COMPUTER GRAPHICS, PEARSON EDUCATION\n\n\n

~ AGRAWAL B. and AGRAWAL C. M. (2012), ENGINEERING GRAPHICS, TMH PUBLICATION\n\n\n

~ NARAYANA, K.L. and P KANNAIAH (2008), TEXT BOOK ON ENGINEERING DRAWING, SCITECHPUBLISHERS\n\n\n

~(CORRESPONDING SET OF) CAD SOFTWARE THEORY AND USER MANUALS\n\n\n</string>


    <string name="sub3">Mathematics-I (Calculus And linear Algebra)</string>
    <string name="math">\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:3 T:1 P:0 Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n

        <b>DETAILED CONTENTS</b>\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: CALCULUS: (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EVOLUTES AND INVOLUTES; EVALUATION OF DEFINITE AND IMPROPER INTEGRALS; BETA AND GAMMA FUNCTIONS AND THEIR PROPERTIES; APPLICATIONS OF DEFINITE INTEGRALS TO EVALUATE SURFACE AREAS AND VOLUMES OF REVOLUTIONS.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: CALCULUS: (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

ROLLES THEOREM, MEAN VALUE THEOREMS, TAYLORS AND MACLAURIN THEOREMS WITH REMAINDERS; INDETERMINATE FORMS AND LHOSPITALS RULE; MAXIMA AND MINIMA.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: SEQUENCES AND SERIES: (10 LECTURES) </font></b>\n\n\nCONVERGENCE OF SEQUENCE AND SERIES, TESTS FOR CONVERGENCE; POWER SERIES, TAYLORS SERIES, SERIES FOR EXPONENTIAL, TRIGONOMETRIC AND LOGARITHM FUNCTIONS; FOURIER SERIES: HALF RANGE SINE AND COSINE SERIES, PARSEVALS THEOREM.\n\n\

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: MULTIVARIABLE CALCULUS (DIFFERENTIATION):</font></b>\n\n\n

(8 LECTURES) LIMIT, CONTINUITY AND PARTIAL DERIVATIVES, DIRECTIONAL DERIVATIVES, TOTAL DERIVATIVE; TANGENT PLANE AND NORMAL LINE; MAXIMA, MINIMA AND SADDLE POINTS; METHOD OF LAGRANGE MULTIPLIERS; GRADIENT, CURL AND DIVERGENCE.\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: MATRICES (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

INVERSE AND RANK OF A MATRIX, RANK-NULLITY THEOREM; SYSTEM OF LINEAR EQUATIONS; SYMMETRIC, SKEW-SYMMETRIC AND ORTHOGONAL MATRICES; DETERMINANTS; EIGENVALUES AND EIGENVECTORS; DIAGONALIZATION OF MATRICES; CAYLEY-HAMILTON THEOREM, AND ORTHOGONAL TRANSFORMATION.\n\n\n

  <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT/REFERENCE BOOKS</font></b>\n\n\n

~G.B. THOMAS AND R.L. FINNEY, CALCULUS AND ANALYTIC GEOMETRY, 9TH EDITION, PEARSON, REPRINT, 2002.\n\n\n

~ ERWIN KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, 9TH EDITION, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n

~VEERARAJAN T., ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS FOR FIRST YEAR, TATA MCGRAW-HILL, NEW DELHI, 2008.\n\n\n

~RAMANA B.V., HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, TATA MCGRAW HILL NEW DELHI, 11TH REPRINT, 2010.\n\n\n

~D. POOLE, LINEAR ALGEBRA: A MODERN INTRODUCTION, 2ND EDITION, BROOKS/COLE, 2005.\n\n\n

~N.P. BALI AND MANISH GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, REPRINT, 2008 \n\n\n</string>

    <string name="sub4">Physics(Electromagnetism)</string>
    <string name="phy">\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:3 T:1 P:3 Credit:5.5</font></b>\n\n\n

        <b>INTRODUCTION TO ELECTROMAGNETIC THEORY [L: 3; T: 1; P: 0 (4 CREDITS)]</b>\n\n\n

        <b>PRE-REQUISITES (IF ANY) MATHEMATICS COURSE WITH VECTOR CALCULUS DETAILED CONTENTS:</b>\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: ELECTROSTATICS IN VACUUM (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
        CALCULATION OF ELECTRIC FIELD AND ELECTROSTATIC POTENTIAL FOR A CHARGE DISTRIBUTION; DIVERGENCE AND CURL OF ELECTROSTATIC FIELD; LAPLACE AND POISSON EQUATIONS FOR ELECTROSTATIC POTENTIAL AND UNIQUENESS OF THEIR SOLUTION AND CONNECTION WITH STEADY STATE DIFFUSION AND THERMAL CONDUCTION; PRACTICAL EXAMPLES LIKE FARADY\'S CAGE AND COFFEE-RING EFFECT; BOUNDARY CONDITIONS OF ELECTRIC FIELD AND ELECTROSTATIC POTENTIAL; METHOD OF IMAGES; ENERGY OF A CHARGE DISTRIBUTION AND ITS EXPRESSION IN TERMS OF ELECTRIC FIELD.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: ELECTROSTATICS IN A LINEAR DIELECTRIC MEDIUM (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
        ELECTROSTATIC FIELD AND POTENTIAL OF A DIPOLE. BOUND CHARGES DUE TO ELECTRIC POLARIZATION; ELECTRIC DISPLACEMENT; BOUNDARY CONDITIONS ON DISPLACEMENT; SOLVING SIMPLE ELECTROSTATICS PROBLEMS IN PRESENCE OF DIELECTRICS - POINT CHARGE AT THE CENTRE OF A DIELECTRIC SPHERE, CHARGE IN FRONT OF A DIELECTRIC SLAB, DIELECTRIC SLAB AND DIELECTRIC SPHERE IN UNIFORM ELECTRIC FIELD.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: MAGNETOSTATICS (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
        BIO-SAVART LAW, DIVERGENCE AND CURL OF STATIC MAGNETIC FIELD; VECTOR POTENTIAL AND CALCULATING IT FOR A GIVEN MAGNETIC FIELD USING STOKES THEOREM; THE EQUATION FOR THE VECTOR POTENTIAL AND ITS SOLUTION FOR GIVEN CURRENT DENSITIES.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: MAGNETOSTATICS IN A LINEAR MAGNETIC MEDIUM (3 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
        MAGNETIZATION AND ASSOCIATED BOUND CURRENTS; AUXILIARY MAGNETIC FIELD; BOUNDARY CONDITIONS ON AND. SOLVING FOR MAGNETIC FIELD DUE TO SIMPLE MAGNETS LIKE A BAR MAGNET; MAGNETIC SUSCEPTIBILITY AND FERROMAGNETIC, PARAMAGNETIC AND DIAMAGNETIC MATERIALS; QUALITATIVE DISCUSSION OF MAGNETIC FIELD IN PRESENCE OF MAGNETIC MATERIALS.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: FARADAYS LAW (4 LECTURES)</font></b>
        FARADAYS LAW IN TERMS OF EMF PRODUCED BY CHANGING MAGNETIC FLUX; EQUIVALENCE OF FARADAYS LAW AND MOTIONAL EMF; LENZS LAW ;ELECTROMAGNETIC BREAKING AND ITS APPLICATIONS; DIFFERENTIAL FORM OF FARADAYS LAW EXPRESSING CURL OF ELECTRIC FIELD IN TERMS OF TIME-DERIVATIVE OF MAGNETIC FIELD AND CALCULATING ELECTRIC FIELD DUE TO CHANGING MAGNETIC FIELDS IN QUASI-STATIC APPROXIMATION; ENERGY STORED IN A MAGNETIC FIELD.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6: DISPLACEMENT CURRENT, MAGNETIC FIELD DUE TO TIME-DEPENDENT ELECTRIC FIELD AND MAXWELLS EQUATIONS (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
        CONTINUITY EQUATION FOR CURRENT DENSITIES; MODIFYING EQUATION FOR THE CURL OF MAGNETIC FIELD TO SATISFY CONTINUITY EQUATION; DISPLACE CURRENT AND MAGNETIC FIELD ARISING FROM TIME- DEPENDENT ELECTRIC FIELD; CALCULATING MAGNETIC FIELD DUE TO CHANGING ELECTRIC FIELDS IN QUASI- STATIC APPROXIMATION. MAXWELLS EQUATION IN VACUUM AND NON-CONDUCTING MEDIUM; ENERGY IN AN ELECTROMAGNETIC FIELD; FLOW OF ENERGY AND POYNTING VECTOR WITH EXAMPLES. QUALITATIVE DISCUSSION OF MOMENTUM IN ELECTROMAGNETIC FIELDS.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 7: ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVES (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
        THE WAVE EQUATION; PLANE ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVES IN VACUUM, THEIR TRANSVERSE NATURE AND POLARIZATION; RELATION BETWEEN ELECTRIC AND MAGNETIC FIELDS OF AN ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVE; ENERGY CARRIED BY ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVES AND EXAMPLES. MOMENTUM CARRIED BY ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVES AND RESULTANT PRESSURE. REFLECTION AND TRANSMISSION OF ELECTROMAGNETIC WAVES FROM A NON-CONDUCTING MEDIUM-VACUUM INTERFACE FOR NORMAL INCIDENCE.\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT BOOKS</font></b>\n\n\n

        ~DAVID GRIFFITHS, INTRODUCTION TO ELECTRODYNAMICS\n\n\n

        SUGGESTED REFERENCE BOOKS:\n\n\n

        ~HALLIDAY AND RESNICK, PHYSICS\n\n\n

        ~W. SASLOW, ELECTRICITY, MAGNETISM AND LIGHT\n\n\n

          <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> LABORATORY - INTRODUCTION TO ELECTROMAGNETIC THEORY [L:0,T:0;P:3 (1.5 CREDITS)]</font></b>\n\n\n

        CHOICE OF EXPERIMENTS FROM THE FOLLOWING:\n\n\n

        ~ EXPERIMENTS ON ELECTROMAGNETIC INDUCTION AND ELECTROMAGNETIC BREAKING;\n\n\n

        ~LC CIRCUIT AND LCR CIRCUIT;\n\n\n

        ~RESONANCE PHENOMENA IN LCR CIRCUITS;\n\n\n

        ~MAGNETIC FIELD FROM HELMHOLTZ COIL;\n\n\n

        ~MEASUREMENT OF LORENTZ FORCE IN A VACUUM TUBE</string>

    <string name="sem2sub1">Chemistry</string>
    <string name="chemistry">\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:3 T:1 P:3 Credit 5.5 </font></b>\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: ATOMIC AND MOLECULAR STRUCTURE (10 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

FAILURE OF CLASSICAL NEWTONIAN AND MAXWELL WAVE MECHANICS TO EXPLAIN PROPERTIES OF PARTICLES AT ATOMIC AND SUB-ATOMIC LEVEL; ELECTROMAGNETIC RADIATION, DUAL NATURE OF ELECTRON AND ELECTROMAGNETIC RADIATION, PLANKS THEORY, PHOTOELECTRIC EFFECT AND HEISENBERG UNCERTAINTY PRINCIPLE. FAILURE OF EARLIER THEORIES TO EXPLAIN CERTAIN PROPERTIES OF MOLECULES LIKE PARAMAGNETIC PROPERTIES. PRINCIPLES FOR COMBINATION OF ATOMIC ORBITALS TO FORM MOLECULAR ORBITALS. FORMATION OF HOMO AND HETERO DIATOMIC MOLECULES AND PLOTS OF ENERGY LEVEL DIAGRAM OF MOLECULAR ORBITALS. COORDINATION NUMBERS AND GEOMETRIES, ISOMERISM IN TRANSITIONAL METAL COMPOUNDS, CRYSTAL FIELD THEORY AND THE ENERGY LEVEL DIAGRAMS FOR TRANSITION METAL IONS AND THEIR MAGNETIC PROPERTIES.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: SPECTROSCOPIC TECHNIQUES AND APPLICATIONS (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

PRINCIPLES OF VIBRATIONAL AND ROTATIONAL SPECTROSCOPY AND SELECTION RULES FOR APPLICATION IN DIATOMIC MOLECULES. ELEMENTARY IDEA OF ELECTRONIC SPECTROSCOPY. UV-VIS SPECTROSCOPY WITH RELATED RULES AND ITS APPLICATIONS. FLUORESCENCE AND ITS APPLICATIONS IN MEDICINE. BASIC PRINCIPLE OF NUCLEAR MAGNETIC RESONANCE AND ITS APPLICATION. BASICS OF MAGNETIC RESONANCE IMAGING.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: INTERMOLECULAR FORCES AND PROPERTIES OF GASES (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

IONIC, DIPOLAR AND VAN DER WAALS INTERACTIONS. EQUATIONS OF STATE OF IDEAL AND REAL GASES, DEVIATION FROM IDEAL BEHAVIOUR. VANDER WAAL GAS EQUATION.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: USE OF FREE ENERGY IN CHEMICAL EQUILIBRIA and WATER CHEMISTRY (8 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

THERMODYNAMIC FUNCTIONS: ENERGY, ENTHALPY ENTROPY AND FREE ENERGY. EQUATIONS TO INTERRELATE THERMODYNAMIC PROPERTIES. FREE ENERGY, EMF. AND CELL POTENTIALS, THE NERNST EQUATION AND APPLICATIONS. CORROSION. USE OF FREE ENERGY CONSIDERATIONS IN METALLURGY THROUGH ELLINGHAM DIAGRAMS. SOLUBILITY EQUILIBRIA.\n\n\n

WATER CHEMISTRY, HARD AND SOFT WATER. PARAMETERS OF QUALITY OF WATER TO BE USED IN DIFFERENT INDUSTRIES AS FOR DRINKING WATER. CALCULATION OF HARDNESS OF WATER IN ALL UNITS. ESTIMATION OF HARDNESS USING EDTA AND ALKALINITY METHOD. REMOVAL OF HARDNESS BY SODA LIME AND ION EXCHANGE METHOD INCLUDING ZEOLITE METHOD\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: PERIODIC PROPERTIES (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

EFFECTIVE NUCLEAR CHARGE, PENETRATION OF ORBITALS, VARIATIONS OF S, P, D AND F ORBITAL ENERGIES OF ATOMS IN THE PERIODIC TABLE, ELECTRONIC CONFIGURATIONS, ATOMIC AND IONIC SIZES, IONIZATION ENERGIES, ELECTRON AFFINITY AND

ELECTRONEGATIVITY, POLARIZABILITY, ACID, BASE, PRINCIPLE OF HSAB THEORY, OXIDATION STATES, HYBRIDIZATION AND MOLECULAR GEOMETRIES.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6: STEREOCHEMISTRY (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

REPRESENTATIONS OF 3-D STRUCTURES, STRUCTURAL ISOMERS AND STEREOISOMERS, CONFIGURATIONS AND SYMMETRY AND CHIRALITY, ENANTIOMERS, DIASTEREOMERS, OPTICAL ACTIVITY, ABSOLUTE CONFIGURATIONS AND CONFORMATIONAL ANALYSIS.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 7: ORGANIC REACTIONS AND SYNTHESIS OF A DRUG MOLECULE (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n

INTRODUCTION TO INTERMEDIATES AND REACTIONS INVOLVING SUBSTITUTION, ADDITION, ELIMINATION, OXIDATION-REDUCTION, DIELS ELDER CYCLIZATION AND EPOXIDE RING OPENINGS REACTIONS. SYNTHESIS OF A COMMONLY USED DRUG MOLECULE LIKE ASPIRIN.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT BOOKS:</font></b>\n\n\n

~ UNIVERSITY CHEMISTRY, BY B. H. MAHAN\n\n\n

~CHEMISTRY: PRINCIPLES AND APPLICATIONS, BY M. J. SIENKO AND R. A. PLANE\n\n\n

~FUNDAMENTALS OF MOLECULAR SPECTROSCOPY, BY C. N. BANWELL\n\n\n

~ENGINEERING CHEMISTRY (NPTEL WEB-BOOK), BY B. L. TEMBE, KAMALUDDIN AND M. S. KRISHNAN\n\n\n

~PHYSICAL CHEMISTRY, BY P. W. ATKINS\n\n\n

~ ORGANIC CHEMISTRY: STRUCTURE AND FUNCTION BY K. P. C. VOLHARDT AND N. E. SCHORE, 5TH EDITION\n\n\n

~HTTP://BCS.WHFREEMAN.COM/VOLLHARDTSCHORESE /DEFAULT.ASP\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>CHEMISTRY LABORATORY CHOICE OF 10-12 EXPERIMENTS FROM THE FOLLOWING</font></b>\n\n\n

~DETERMINATION OF SURFACE TENSION AND VISCOSITY\n\n\n

~THIN LAYER CHROMATOGRAPHY\n\n\n

~ION EXCHANGE COLUMN FOR REMOVAL OF HARDNESS OF\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>WATER</font></b>\n\n\n

~DETERMINATION OF CHLORIDE CONTENT OF WATER\n\n\n

~COLLIGATIVE PROPERTIES USING FREEZING POINT DEPRESSION\n\n\n

~DETERMINATION OF THE RATE CONSTANT OF A REACTION\n\n\n

~DETERMINATION OF CELL CONSTANT AND\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>CONDUCTANCE OF SOLUTIONS</font></b>\n\n\n

~ POTENTIOMETRY-DETERMINATION OF REDOX POTENTIALS AND EMFS\n\n\n

~SYNTHESIS OF A POLYMER/DRUG\n\n\n

~SAPONIFICATION/ACID VALUE OF AN OIL\n\n\n

~CHEMICAL ANALYSIS OF A SALT\n\n\n

~LATTICE STRUCTURES AND PACKING OF SPHERES\n\n\n

~MODELS OF POTENTIAL ENERGY SURFACES\n\n\n

~CHEMICAL OSCILLATIONS- IODINE CLOCK REACTION\n\n\n

~DETERMINATION OF THE PARTITION COEFFICIENT OF A SUBSTANCE BETWEEN TWO IMMISCIBLE LIQUIDS\n\n\n

~ADSORPTION OF ACETIC ACID BY CHARCOAL\n\n\n

~ USE OF THE CAPILLARY VISCOSIMETERS TO THE\n\n\n

DEMONSTRATE OF THE ISOELECTRIC POINT AS THE PH OF MINIMUM VISCOSITY FOR GELATIN SOLS AND/OR COAGULATION OF THE WHITE PART OF EGG.\n\n\n
    </string>

    <string name="sem2sub2">Mathematics(ODE and COMPLEX VARIABLES)</string>
    <string name="mathss">
        <b>L:3 T:1 P:0 Credit:4</b>\n\n\n

       <b>DETAILED CONTENTS</b> \n\n\n


        <!-- strings.xml file -->

        <!-- Module 1 -->
        <string name="module1"><b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: MULTIVARIABLE CALCULUS (INTEGRATION):(10 LECTURES)</font></b> \n\n\n
MULTIPLE INTEGRATION: DOUBLE INTEGRALS (CARTESIAN), CHANGE OF ORDER OF INTEGRATION IN DOUBLE INTEGRALS, CHANGE OF VARIABLES (CARTESIAN TO POLAR), APPLICATIONS: AREAS AND VOLUMES, CENTER OF MASS AND GRAVITY (CONSTANT AND VARIABLE DENSITIES); TRIPLE INTEGRALS (CARTESIAN), ORTHOGONAL CURVILINEAR COORDINATES, SIMPLE APPLICATIONS INVOLVING CUBES, SPHERE AND RECTANGULAR PARALLELEPIPEDS; SCALAR LINE INTEGRALS, VECTOR LINE INTEGRALS, SCALAR SURFACE INTEGRALS, VECTOR SURFACE INTEGRALS, THEOREMS OF GREEN, GAUSS AND STOKES.</string>\n\n\n

        <!-- Module 2 -->
        <string name="module2"><b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: FIRST ORDER ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS: (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
EXACT, LINEAR AND BERNOULLIS EQUATIONS, EULERS EQUATIONS, EQUATIONS NOT OF FIRST DEGREE: EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR P, EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR Y, EQUATIONS SOLVABLE FOR X AND CLAIRAUT TYPE.</string>\n\n\n

        <!-- Module 3 -->
        <string name="module3"><b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS OF HIGHER ORDERS:(8 LECTURES)</font></b> \n\n\n
SECOND ORDER LINEAR DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS WITH VARIABLE COEFFICIENTS, METHOD OF VARIATION OF PARAMETERS, CAUCHY-EULER EQUATION; POWER SERIES SOLUTIONS; LEGENDRE POLYNOMIALS, BESSEL FUNCTIONS OF THE FIRST KIND AND THEIR PROPERTIES.</string>\n\n\n

        <!-- Module 4 -->
        <string name="module4"><b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: COMPLEX VARIABLE - DIFFERENTIATION:(8 LECTURES)</font></b> \n\n\n
DIFFERENTIATION, CAUCHY-RIEMANN EQUATIONS, ANALYTIC FUNCTIONS, HARMONIC FUNCTIONS, FINDING HARMONIC CONJUGATE; ELEMENTARY ANALYTIC FUNCTIONS (EXPONENTIAL, TRIGONOMETRIC, LOGARITHM) AND THEIR PROPERTIES; CONFORMAL MAPPINGS, MOBIUS TRANSFORMATIONS AND THEIR PROPERTIES.</string>\n\n\n

        <!-- Module 5 -->
        <string name="module5"><b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: COMPLEX VARIABLE - INTEGRATION:(8 LECTURES) </font></b>\n\n\n
CONTOUR INTEGRALS, CAUCHY-GOURSAT THEOREM (WITHOUT PROOF), CAUCHY INTEGRAL FORMULA (WITHOUT PROOF), LIOUVILLE\'S THEOREM AND MAXIMUM-MODULUS THEOREM (WITHOUT PROOF); TAYLOR\'S SERIES, ZEROS OF ANALYTIC FUNCTIONS, SINGULARITIES, LAURENTS SERIES; RESIDUES, CAUCHY RESIDUE THEOREM (WITHOUT PROOF), EVALUATION OF DEFINITE INTEGRAL INVOLVING SINE AND COSINE, EVALUATION OF CERTAIN IMPROPER INTEGRALS USING THE BROMWICH CONTOUR.</string>\n\n\n

        <!-- Suggested Text/Reference Books -->
        <string name="suggested_books"><b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT/REFERENCE BOOKS</font></b>\n\n\n
G.B. THOMAS AND R.L. FINNEY, CALCULUS AND ANALYTIC GEOMETRY, 9TH EDITION, PEARSON, REPRINT, 2002.\n\n\n
~ERWIN KREYSZIG, ADVANCED ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, 9TH EDITION, JOHN WILEY and SONS, 2006.\n\n\n
~W. E. BOYCE AND R. C. DIPRIMA, ELEMENTARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS AND BOUNDARY VALUE PROBLEMS, 9TH EDN., WILEY INDIA, 2009.\n\n\n
~S. L. ROSS, DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, 3RD ED., WILEY INDIA, 1984.\n\n\n
~E. A. CODDINGTON, AN INTRODUCTION TO ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, PRENTICE HALL INDIA, 1995.\n\n\n
~E. L. INCE, ORDINARY DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS, DOVER PUBLICATIONS, 1958.\n\n\n
J. W. BROWN AND R. V. CHURCHILL, COMPLEX VARIABLES AND APPLICATIONS, 7TH ED., MC-GRAW HILL, 2004.\n\n\n
~N.P. BALI AND MANISH GOYAL, A TEXT BOOK OF ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, LAXMI PUBLICATIONS, REPRINT, 2008.\n\n\n
~B.S. GREWAL, HIGHER ENGINEERING MATHEMATICS, KHANNA PUBLISHERS, 36TH EDITION, 2010.</string>
    </string>


    <string name="sem2sub3">Programming For Problem Solving</string>
    <string name="pps">\n\n\nL:3 T:0 P:4 Credit:5\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 1: INTRODUCTION TO PROGRAMMING (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Components of a computer system\n\n\n
- Algorithms and their representation (Flowcharts/Pseudo code)\n\n\n
- From algorithms to programs (Source code, variables, memory)\n\n\n
- Run-time environment and storage classes\n\n\n
- Syntax and logical errors in compilation\n\n\n
- Object and executable code\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 2: OPERATORS (3 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Arithmetic, relational, logical, bitwise operators\n\n\n
- Operator precedence\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 3: CONDITIONAL BRANCHING AND LOOPS (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Writing and evaluating conditionals\n\n\n
- Branching and iteration (Loops)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 4: ARRAYS (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Array declaration and initialization\n\n\n
- Bound checking arrays (1-D, 2-D)\n\n\n
- Character arrays and strings\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 5: BASIC ALGORITHMS (6 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Searching algorithms (Linear, Binary)\n\n\n
- Basic sorting algorithms (Bubble, Insertion, Selection)\n\n\n
- Finding roots of equations\n\n\n
- Notion of order of complexity through example programs\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 6: FUNCTION (4 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Introduction and writing functions\n\n\n
- Scope of variables in functions\n\n\n
- Parameter passing in functions (Call by value, Call by reference)\n\n\n
- Passing arrays to functions\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 7: RECURSION (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Recursion as a problem-solving technique\n\n\n
- Example programs: Factorial, Fibonacci series, Reverse a string, GCD, Ackerman function\n\n\n
- Quick sort or merge sort\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 8: STRUCTURE/UNION (3 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Structures and their elements\n\n\n
- Storage of structure elements\n\n\n
- Defining structures and arrays of structures\n\n\n
- Basic definition of union\n\n\n
- Comparison between structure and union with examples\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 9: POINTERS (5 LECTURES)</font></b>\n\n\n
- Idea of pointers and their definitions
- Use of pointers in self-referential structures
- Notion of linked lists
- Pointer to pointer, array, strings, function, structure\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>MODULE 10: FILE HANDLING</font></b>\n\n\n
- (To be covered if time permits or as part of the lab)\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT BOOKS:</font></b>\n\n\n

~BYRON GOTTFRIED, SCHAUMS OUTLINE OF PROGRAMMING WITH C, MCGRAW-HILL

~E. BALAGURUSWAMY, PROGRAMMING IN ANSI C, TATA MCGRAW-HILL\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED REFERENCE BOOKS</font></b>\n\n\n

~BRIAN W. KERNIGHAN AND DENNIS M. RITCHIE, THE C PROGRAMMING LANGUAGE, PRENTICE HALL OF INDIA

~ YASHWANT KANETKAR, LET US C, BPB PUBLICATION\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>THE STUDENT WILL LEARN</font></b>\n\n\n

~TO FORMULATE SIMPLE ALGORITHMS FOR ARITHMETIC AND LOGICAL PROBLEMS.\n\n\n

~TO TRANSLATE THE ALGORITHMS TO PROGRAMS (IN C LANGUAGE). ~TO TEST AND EXECUTE THE PROGRAMS AND CORRECT\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SYNTAX AND LOGICAL ERRORS.</font></b>\n\n\n

~TO IMPLEMENT CONDITIONAL BRANCHING, ITERATION AND RECURSION.\n\n\n

~TO DECOMPOSE A PROBLEM INTO FUNCTIONS AND\n\n\n

SYNTHESIZE A COMPLETE PROGRAM USING DIVIDE AND CONQUER APPROACH.\n\n\n

~TO USE ARRAYS, POINTERS AND STRUCTURES TO FORMULATE ALGORITHMS AND PROGRAMS.\n\n\n

~TO APPLY PROGRAMMING TO SOLVE MATRIX ADDITION AND MULTIPLICATION PROBLEMS AND SEARCHING AND SORTING PROBLEMS.\n\n\n

~TO APPLY PROGRAMMING TO SOLVE SIMPLE NUMERICAL METHOD PROBLEMS, NAMELY ROT FINDING OF FUNCTION, DIFFERENTIATION OF FUNCTION AND SIMPLE INTEGRATION.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> LABORATORY PROGRAMMING FOR PROBLEM SOLVING</font></b>\n\n\n

[THE LABORATORY SHOULD BE PRECEDED OR FOLLOWED BY A TUTORIAL TO EXPLAIN THE APPROACH OR ALGORITHM TO BE IMPLEMENTED FOR THE PROBLEM GIVEN.]\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 1: PROBLEM SOLVING USING COMPUTERS:\n\n\n

LAB1: FAMILIARIZATION WITH PROGRAMMING ENVIRONMENT\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 2: VARIABLE TYPES AND TYPE CONVERSIONS:\n\n\n

LAB 2: SIMPLE COMPUTATIONAL PROBLEMS USING ARITHMETIC EXPRESSIONS\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 3: BRANCHING AND LOGICAL EXPRESSIONS:\n\n\n

LAB 3: PROBLEMS INVOLVING IF-THEN-ELSE STRUCTURES\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 4: LOOPS, WHILE AND FOR LOOPS:\n\n\n

LAB 4: ITERATIVE PROBLEMS E.G., SUM OF SERIES\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 5: 1D ARRAYS: SEARCHING, SORTING:\n\n\n

LAB 5: 1D ARRAY MANIPULATION\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 6: 2D ARRAYS AND STRINGS\n\n\n

LAB 6: MATRIX PROBLEMS, STRING OPERATIONS\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 7: FUNCTIONS, CALL BY VALUE:\n\n\n

LAB 7: SIMPLE FUNCTIONS\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 8: NUMERICAL METHODS (ROOT FINDING, NUMERICAL DIFFERENTIATION, NUMERICAL INTEGRATION):\n\n\n

LAB 8: PROGRAMMING FOR SOLVING NUMERICAL METHODS PROBLEMS\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 9: RECURSION, STRUCTURE OF RECURSIVE CALLS\n\n\n

LAB 9: RECURSIVE FUNCTIONS\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 10: POINTERS, STRUCTURES AND DYNAMIC MEMORY ALLOCATION\n\n\n

        LAB 10: POINTERS AND STRUCTURES\n\n\n

TUTORIAL 11: FILE HANDLING:\n\n\n

LAB 11: FILE OPERATIONS\n\n\n</string>


    <string name="sem2sub4">Workshop Manufacturing Practices</string>
    <string name="WMP">\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> L:1 T:0 P:4 Credit:3</font></b>\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>LECTURES and VIDEOS: (10 HOURS) [L: 1; T: 0; P: 0 (1 CREDIT)]</font></b>\n\n\n

        <b>DETAILED CONTENTS:</b>

1. MANUFACTURING METHODS-CASTING, FORMING, MACHINING, JOINING, ADVANCED MANUFACTURING METHODS (3 LECTURES)\n\n\n

2. CNC MACHINING, ADDITIVE MANUFACTURING (1 LECTURE)\n\n\n

3. FITTING OPERATIONS and POWER TOOLS (1 LECTURE)\n\n\n

4. CARPENTRY (1 LECTURE)\n\n\n

5. PLASTIC MOULDING, GLASS CUTTING (1 LECTURE)\n\n\n

6. METAL CASTING (1 LECTURE)\n\n\n

7. WELDING (ARC WELDING and GAS WELDING), BRAZING, SOLDERING (2 LECTURE)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED TEXT/REFERENCE BOOKS:</font></b>\n\n\n

~HAJRA CHOUDHURY S.K., HAJRA CHOUDHURY A.K. AND NIRJHAR ROY S.K., ELEMENTS OF WORKSHOP TECHNOLOGY, VOL. I 2008 AND VOL. II 2010, MEDIA PROMOTERS AND PUBLISHERS PRIVATE LIMITED, MUMBAI.\n\n\n

~KALPAKJIAN S. AND STEVEN S. SCHMID,\n\n\n

MANUFACTURING ENGINEERING AND TECHNOLOGY, 4TH\n\n\n

EDITION, PEARSON EDUCATION INDIA EDITION, 2002. ~GOWRI P. HARIHARAN AND A. SURESH BABU,MANUFACTURING TECHNOLOGY-I PEARSON\n\n\n

EDUCATION, 2008. ~ROY A. LINDBERG, PROCESSES AND MATERIALS OF MANUFACTURE, 4TH EDITION, PRENTICE HALL INDIA, 1998.\n\n\n

~RAO P.N., MANUFACTURING TECHNOLOGY, VOL. I AND VOL. II, TATA MCGRAWHILL HOUSE, 2017.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>COURSE OUTCOMES:</font></b>\n\n\n

~UPON COMPLETION OF THIS COURSE, THE STUDENTS WILL GAIN KNOWLEDGE OF THE DIFFERENT MANUFACTURING PROCESSES WHICH ARE COMMONLY EMPLOYED IN THE INDUSTRY, TO FABRICATE COMPONENTS USING DIFFERENT MATERIALS.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> WORKSHOP PRACTICE: (60 HOURS) [L: 0; T: 0; P: 4 (2 CREDITS)]</font></b>\n\n\n

1. MACHINE SHOP (10 HOURS) AND FITTING SHOP (8 HOURS)\n\n\n

2. CARPENTRY (6 HOURS)\n\n\n

3. WELDING SHOP (8 HOURS) (ARC WELDING 4 HRS + GAS WELDING 4 HRS)\n\n\n

4. CASTING (8 HOURS) AND SMITHY (6 HOURS)\n\n\n

5. PLASTIC MOULDING and GLASS CUTTING (6 HOURS)\n\n\n

6. 3-D PRINTING OF DIFFERENT MODELS (8 HOURS)\n\n\n

EXAMINATIONS COULD INVOLVE THE ACTUAL FABRICATION OF SIMPLE COMPONENTS, UTILIZING ONE OR MORE OF THE TECHNIQUES COVERED ABOVE.\n\n\n</string>


    <string name="sem2sub5">English</string>
    <string name="eng">\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>L:2 T:0 P:2 Credit:3</font></b>\n\n\n

<b>DETAILED CONTENTS</b>\n\n\n

1.VOCABULARY BUILDING\n\n\n

A. THE CONCEPT OF WORD FORMATION\n\n\n

B. ROOT WORDS FROM FOREIGN LANGUAGES AND THEIR USE IN ENGLISH\n\n\n

C. ACQUAINTANCE WITH PREFIXES AND SUFFIXES FROM FOREIGN LANGUAGES IN ENGLISH TO FORM DERIVATIVES.\n\n\n

D. SYNONYMS, ANTONYMS, AND STANDARD ABBREVIATIONS.\n\n\n

E. AFFIXES, ACRONYMS\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>2.BASIC WRITING SKILLS</font></b>\n\n\n

A. SENTENCE STRUCTURES\n\n\n

B. USE OF PHRASES AND CLAUSES IN SENTENCES\n\n\n

C. IMPORTANCE OF PROPER PUNCTUATION\n\n\n

D. KINDS OF SENTENCES\n\n\n

E. USE OF TENSE, USE IN CONTEXT AND COHERENCE OF TENSE IN WRITING\n\n\n

F. USE OF VOICE-ACTIVE/PASSIVE IN SENTENCES\n\n\n

G. USE OF SPEECH-DIRECT AND INDIRECT SPEECH\n\n\n

H. FRAMING QUESTIONS-DIRECT, USING MODAL VERBS\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>3.IDENTIFYING COMMON ERRORS IN WRITING</font></b>\n\n\n

A. SUBJECT-VERB AGREEMENT\n\n\n

B. NOUN-PRONOUN AGREEMENT\n\n\n

C. MISPLACED MODIFIERS\n\n\n

D. ARTICLES\n\n\n

E. PREPOSITIONS\n\n\n

F. REDUNDANCIES\n\n\n

G. CLICHÉS\n\n\n

H. COMMON ENGLISH ERRORS\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>4.NATURE AND STYLE OF SENSIBLE WRITING</font></b>\n\n\n

A. DESCRIBING\n\n\n

B. DEFINING\n\n\n

C. CLASSIFYING\n\n\n

D. PROVIDING EXAMPLES OR EVIDENCE\n\n\n

E. WRITING INTRODUCTION AND CONCLUSION\n\n\n

F. ORGANISING PRINCIPLE OF PARAGRAPHS IN DOCUMENTS\n\n\n

G. ARGUMENT, DESCRIBING/ NARRATING/ PLANNING, DEFINING,CLASSIFYING\n\n\n

H. LEXICAL RESOURCES, USING SUITABLE LANGUAGE REGISTER\n\n\n

I. COHERENCE, WRITING INTRODUCTION, BODY AND CONCLUSION, TECHNIQUES FOR WRITING PRECISELY,GRAMMAR AND ACCURACY\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>5.WRITING PRACTICES</font></b>\n\n\n

A. COMPREHENSION\n\n\n

B. FORMAL LETTER WRITING/ APPLICATION/ REPORT\n\n\n

WRITING/ WRITING MINUTES OF MEETINGS\n\n\n

C. ESSAY WRITING\n\n\n

D. FORMAL EMAIL WRITING\n\n\n

E. RESUME/ CV WRITING, COVER LETTER,\n\n\n

F. STATEMENT OF PURPOSE\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>6.ORAL COMMUNICATION\n\n\n</font></b>

(THIS UNIT INVOLVES INTERACTIVE PRACTICE SESSIONS IN LANGUAGE LAB)\n\n\n

A. LISTENING COMPREHENSION\n\n\n

B. PRONUNCIATION, INTONATION, STRESS AND RHYTHM\n\n\n

C. COMMON EVERYDAY SITUATIONS: CONVERSATIONS AND DIALOGUES\n\n\n

D. COMMUNICATION AT WORKPLACE\n\n\n

E. INTERVIEWS\n\n\n

F. FORMAL PRESENTATIONS\n\n\n

G. ACQUAINTING STUDENTS WITH IPA SYMBOLS\n\n\n

H. PHONETICS (BASIC)\n\n\n

1. SOUNDS - VOWELS, CONSONANTS\n\n\n

J. CLEARING MOTHER TONGUE INFLUENCE\n\n\n

K. CLEARING REDUNDANCIES AND COMMON ERRORS RELATED TO INDIANISMS\n\n\n

L. GROUP DISCUSSION\n\n\n

M. EXPRESSING OPINIONS\n\n\n

N. COHERENCE AND FLUENCY IN SPEECH\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>7.READING SKILLS\n\n\n</font></b>

A. READING COMPREHENSION,\n\n\n

B. PARAGRAPH READING BASED ON PHONETIC SOUNDS/ INTONATION\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>   8.PROFESSIONAL SKILLS\n\n\n</font></b>

A. TEAM BUILDING\n\n\n\

B. SOFT SKILLS AND ETIQUETTES\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>9.ACQUAINTANCE WITH TECHNOLOGY-AIDED LANGUAGE LEARNING</font></b>\n\n\n

A. USE OF COMPUTER SOFTWARE (GRAMMARLY, GINGER…)\n\n\n

B. USE OF SMARTPHONE APPLICATIONS (DUOLINGO, BUSUU…)\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>10.ACTIVITIES\n\n\n</font></b>

A. NARRATIVE CHAIN\n\n\n

B. DESCRIBING/ NARRATING\n\n\n

C. WRITING ESSAYS IN RELAY\n\n\n

D. PEER/ GROUP ACTIVITIES\n\n\n

E. BRAINSTORMING VOCABULARY\n\n\n

F. CUE / FLASH CARDS FOR VOCABULARY\n\n\n

G. DEBATES\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>SUGGESTED READINGS:\n\n\n</font></b>

~PRACTICAL ENGLISH USAGE. MICHAEL SWAN. OUP. 1995.\n\n\n

~REMEDIAL ENGLISH GRAMMAR. F.T. WOOD.\n\n\n

MACMILLAN.2007\n\n\n

ON WRITING WELL. WILLIAM ZINSSER. HARPER\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>RESOURCE BOOK. 2001\n\n\n</font></b>

~STUDY WRITING. LIZ HAMP-LYONS AND BEN HEASLY. CAMBRIDGE UNIVERSITY PRESS. 2006.\n\n\n

~COMMUNICATION SKILLS. SANJAY KUMAR AND PUSHPLATA. OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS. 2011.\n\n\n\

~EXERCISES IN SPOKEN ENGLISH. PARTS. I-III. CIEFL, HYDERABAD. OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS\n\n\n</string>

    <string name="aesem3sub1">Elements Of Aeronautical Engineering</string>
    <string name="eae">\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Credit:2</font></b>\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-1.0 Aeronautics: History of Flying and the Industry</font></b>\n\n\n
1.1 Early attempts of flying\n\n\n
1.2 Major events in the development of aerial vehicle and their contributors\n\n\n
1.3 Development cycle of aircraft to the present state and future ahead\n\n\n
1.4 Development cycle of helicopter to the current state\n\n\n
1.5 Indian Aeronautical Industry\n\n\n
1.6 Aeronautical Industry\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-2.0 Aerodynamics</font></b>\n\n\n
2.1 Atmosphere and Standard Atmosphere; Pressure, Temperature and Density Altitude\n\n\n
2.2 Airfoil Nomenclatures\n\n\n
2.3 Aerodynamic forces and coefficients: lift drag and moment, Pressure coefficient\n\n\n
2.4 Speed of sound\n\n\n
2.5 Subsonic wind tunnels and supersonic wind tunnels\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-3.0 Propulsion</font></b>\n\n\n
3.1 Aircraft propulsion: Propellers, reciprocating engines, Jet engines\n\n\n
3.2 Jet engines: Working principle, TypesTurbojet, Turbofan, Turboshaft\n\n\n
3.3 Ramjet, Scramjet propulsion\n\n\n
3.4 Brief introduction of rocket propulsion\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-4.0 Aircraft Structures and Systems</font></b>\n\n\n
4.1 Various materials used in different components/parts of the aircraft, Evolution of aircraft materials with time\n\n\n
4.2 Properties of flight vehicle material, Factors impacting choice of aircraft material\n\n\n
4.3 Layout of aircraft along with various structure components including control surfaces\n\n\n
4.4 Brief introduction to various aircraft instruments and systems\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-5.0 Aircraft Performance</font></b>\n\n\n
5.1 Equation of motion, Drag polar\n\n\n
5.2 Level and un-accelerated flight: thrust and power requirements\n\n\n
5.3 Aircraft power requirements and power available (Jet and propeller propulsion)\n\n\n
5.4 Range and Endurance Phenomenon\n\n\n
5.5 Take-off and landing performance\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Books</font></b>\n\n\n

        Introduction to flight : John D. Anderson, Mary L. Bowden\n\n\n
        Flight without formula : A. C. Kermode\n\n\n
        Aircraft: Basic Science Ralph D. Bent, Michael J. Kroes\n\n\n
        Jet Propulsion: A Simple Guide to the Aerodynamic and Thermodynamic Design and Performance of Jet Engines : Nicholas Cumpsty</string>
    \n\n\n

    <string name="aesem3sub2">Fluid Mechanics and Machinery</string>
    <string name="fluid">\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-1.0 Properties of Fluids and Fluid Statics</font></b>\n\n\n
1.1 Properties of fluids\n\n\n
1.2 Fluid statics\n\n\n
1.3 Hydrostatic equation – Forces on plane and curved surfaces\n\n\n
1.4 Buoyancy – Metacentre\n\n\n
1.5 Simple and differential manometers\n\n\n
1.6 Mechanical pressure gauges and Relative equilibrium\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-2.0 Fluid Dynamics</font></b>\n\n\n
2.1 Lagrangian vs Eulerian descriptions\n\n\n
2.2 Classification of fluid flows\n\n\n
2.3 Flow Visualization – Path line – Stream line – Streak line\n\n\n
2.4 Stream and Potential functions, Flownets.\n\n\n
2.5 Governing equations: Continuity equation, Momentum equation, Energy equation – Euler’s equation – Bernoulli’s equation – Applications\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>   Unit-3.0 Flow through Pipes and Boundary Layer</font></b>
3.1 Reynold’s Experiment\n\n\n
3.2 Laminar flow through circular conduits\n\n\n
3.3 Darcy Weisbach equation – friction factor - Moody diagram - Major and minor losses\n\n\n
3.4 Hydraulic and energy gradient lines\n\n\n
3.5 Pipes in series and parallel\n\n\n
3.6 Boundary layer concepts and Types of boundary layer thickness\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit- 4.0 Dimensional Analysis and Model Studies</font></b>\n\n\n
4.1 Fundamental dimensions, Dimensional homogeneity\n\n\n
4.2 Rayleigh’s method and Buckingham Pi theorem\n\n\n
4.3 Dimensionless parameters\n\n\n
4.4 Similitude and model studies, Distorted and undistorted models\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit- 5.0 Turbines and Pumps</font></b>\n\n\n
5.1 Impact of jets, Velocity triangle\n\n\n
5.2 Classification of turbines and Working principles\n\n\n
5.3 Classification of pumps - Centrifugal pumps - Working principle\n\n\n
5.4 Velocity triangles - Work done by the impeller\n\n\n
5.5 Reciprocating pump working principle\n\n\n
5.6 Rotary pumps\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Laboratory Experiment/Practical Titles</font></b>\n\n\n
      1  Verification of Bernoulli’s theorem\n\n\n
      2  Flow through Orifice meter\n\n\n
      3  Flow through Venturi meter\n\n\n
      4  Fiction factor for flow through pipes\n\n\n
      5  Impact of jet on fixed plate\n\n\n
      6  Determination of metacentric height\n\n\n
      7  Determination of Reynolds Number\n\n\n
      8  Characteristics of Centrifugal pump\n\n\n
      9  Characteristics of Reciprocating pump\n\n\n
      10  Characteristics of Pelton wheel turbine &amp; Francis turbine\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Books</font></b>\n\n\n
       1. Fluid Mechanics: Fundamentals and Applications : Yunus A. Cengel and John M. Cimbala\n\n\n
        2. Fluid Mechanics: Frank M. White\n\n\n
        3. Introduction to Fluid Mechanics Philip J. Pritchard, Fox and McDonald\n\n\n
        4. Fluid Mechanics: Pijush K. Kundu, Ira M. Cohen and David R. Dowling\n\n\n
        5. Introduction to Fluid Mechanics and Fluid Machines:  S K Som, Gautam Biswas, and S Chakraborty\n\n\n
        6. Fluid Mechanics with Problems and Solutions, and an Aerodynamic Laboratory : Egon Krause\n\n\n
        7. Hydraulics and Fluid Mechanics:  Modi P.N. and Seth, S.M\n\n\n</string>

    <string name="aesem3sub3">Mechanics of Solids</string>
    <string name="mos">\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-1.0 Direct Stresses and Strains in Components</font></b>\n\n\n
1.1 Different types of Loads.\n\n\n
1.2 Mechanical properties of materials like Strength, Stiffness, Hardness, Toughness, Ductility, Malleability, Elasticity, Plasticity, Creep, Fatigue etc.\n\n\n
1.3 Statically Determinate and Indeterminate structures.\n\n\n
1.4 Direct Stress, Linear Strain, Hook’s Law, Stress- Strain curve of ferrous and non ferrous materials, Modulus of Elasticity, Yield, Proof, Breaking and Ultimate Stress and Factor of safety.\n\n\n
1.5 Lateral Strain and Poisson’s ratio, Relations between different Moduli.\n\n\n
1.6 Taper circular bar, Bar of Uniform strength\n\n\n
1.7 Composite bars.\n\n\n
1.8 Stresses in Bolted connections bolted joint when subjected to direct external load only\n\n\n
1.9 Temperature Stresses and Strain with and without yielding.\n\n\n
1.10 Shear Stress, Shear Strain and Shear Modulus.\n\n\n
1.11 Bulk Modulus and Volumetric Strain\n\n\n
1.12 Sudden, Gradual and Impact Loads, Strain Energy and Proof Resilience for Sudden, Gradual and Impact Loads.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-2.0 Shear Force, Bending Moment, Slope and Deflection in Beam type Components</font></b>\n\n\n
2.1 Types of Beams like Cantilever, Simply Supported and Over Hang Beams.\n\n\n
2.2 Relation between Shear Force and Bending Moment.\n\n\n
2.3 Sagging and Hogging Bending Moment and its importance.\n\n\n
2.4 Point of Contra flexure and its importance.\n\n\n
2.5 S.F and B.M Diagram for various beams under different loadings.\n\n\n
2.6 Slope and Deflection in Cantilever and Simply Supported beams using Double Integration Method, McCauley’s method, Area Moment method, Conjugate Beam method.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-3.0 Bending and Shear Stresses in Beam type Components</font></b>\n\n\n
3.1 Bending Theory, Flexural equation, Bending stress, Bending strain, Sectional Modulus\n\n\n
3.2 Neutral Axis, application of Bending theory to Statically determinate beams elements like shaft, axle, spindle , pulley arm having rectangular or circular section to find out stresses.\n\n\n
3.3 Flitched/Composite beams.\n\n\n
3.4 Shear stresses in beams\n\n\n
3.5 Beams of Uniform strength.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-4.0 Eccentric Loading</font></b>\n\n\n
4.1 Axial and eccentric load, effects of eccentricity, Field cases (Hook, clamp, Bench Vice, Frame etc).\n\n\n
4.2 Axial stress and bending stress, resultant stress intensities, resultant stress variation (Eccentricity about one axis only).\n\n\n
4.3 Limiting eccentricity, Core of section.\n\n\n
4.4 No tension condition.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-5.0 Thick and Thin Pressure Vessels</font></b>\n\n\n
5.1 Pressure Vessels.\n\n\n
5.2 Thin cylinders and spheres subjected to internal pressure; Hoop stresses, longitudinal stress and change in volume.\n\n\n
5.3 Wire bound thin Cylindrical pressure vessels.\n\n\n
5.4 Thick cylinders subjected to both internal and external pressure; Lame’s equation, Hoop stresses, Longitudinal stress and Radial stresses. Radial and Hoop stress distribution.\n\n\n
5.5 Shrink fit thick cylindrical pressure vessels.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-6.0 Torsion of Shaft</font></b>\n\n\n
6.1 Torsion/Twisting Moment, Torsional Equation, Angle of Twist, Polar Moment of Inertia, Torsional Rigidity.\n\n\n
6.2 Torsional Stress and Strain in solid and hollow shafts. Comparison between Solid and Hollow Shafts subjected to pure torsion.\n\n\n
6.3 Composite Shafts\n\n\n
6.4 Power Transmitted /Consumed for shaft, spindle and axle of solid and hollow sections subjected to Twisting Moment.\n\n\n
6.5 Shafts subjected to combined bending and torsion.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Unit-7.0 Column and Struts</font></b>\n\n\n
7.1 Column and Strut\n\n\n
7.2 Short and Long Column.\n\n\n
7.3 End Conditions of Column.\n\n\n
7.4 Effective Length of Column and Modes of Failure in column.\n\n\n
7.5 Radius of Gyration, Slenderness Ratio.\n\n\n
7.6 Euler’s Crippling Load and its application. Limitations of Euler’s theory.\n\n\n
7.7 Rankin’s load / Buckling Load and its application in screw of Screw jack, Connecting Rod.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-8.0 Principal Stresses and Strains</font></b>\n\n\n
8.1 Multi load situations and need of estimating principal stresses.\n\n\n
8.2 Definition of principal plane and principal stresses.\n\n\n
8.3 Expression for normal and tangential stress, maximum shear stress.\n\n\n
8.4 Stresses on inclined planes.\n\n\n
8.5 Position of principal planes and planes of maximum shear.\n\n\n
8.6 Graphical solution using Mohr’s circle of Stresses.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Laboratory Experiment/Practical Titles</font></b>\n\n\n

1. Perform Tension Test on Mild Steel/ Aluminium on Universal Testing machine as per IS432 (I)\n\n\n

        2. Perform Compression test on Cast Iron on
Universal Testing Machine as per IS
14858\n\n\n

        3. Perform direct Shear Test on Mild Steel
using Universal Testing Machine as per
IS 5242\n\n\n

        4. Determine Young’s Modulus of Elasticity
of different materials’ beam simply
supported at ends.\n\n\n

        5. Calculate Impact Value/Toughness of
Mild Steel and Aluminium using Izod and
Charpy Impact Test Apparatus as per IS
1757.\n\n\n

        6. Perform Brinell, Rockwell and Vicker’s
hardness test on different metals.\n\n\n


        7. Estimate Maximum Bending moment and
Shear force for simply supported and
cantilever beams under point load and
UDL using ‘Combined Shear Force and
Bending Moment’ apparatus.\n\n\n


        8. Measure flexural rigidity (EI) for beam
using ‘Slope and Deflection’ apparatus and compare it with theoretical value.\n\n\n

        9. Investigate the effect of beam length and
width on deflection of beam and compare
it with theoretical value using ‘Slope and
Deflection’ apparatus.\n\n\n

        10. Perform the torsion test on wire/ Rod of
different materials using ‘Torsion of Bar’
apparatus. (Part I) as per IS 1717\n\n\n

        11. Measure the buckling load of three
different slenderness ratio long columns
of same lengths using ‘Behaviour of
column and struts’ apparatus.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Suggested Learning Resources</font></b>\n\n\n

        1. Engineering Mechanics of Solids: Popov, E. P.\n\n\n
        2. Mechanics of Materials: Hibbeler, R. C.\n\n\n
        3. Mechanics of Materials,: Beer, F. P., Johnston, E.
R., and DeWolf, J. T.\n\n\n
        4. Advanced Mechanics of Solids : Srinath, L. S.\n\n\n
        5. Strength of Materials Vol. I and II :Timoshenko S.\n\n\n
        6. Schaum’s Outline of Theory and
Problems of Strength of Materials:
Nash William A.\n\n\n

        7. Mechanics of Materials :Timoshenko and Gere\n\n\n
        8. Strength of Materials :Rajput R.K.\n\n\n
        9. Strength of Materials:  Rattan S.S.\n\n\n
    </string>


    <string name="aesem3sub4">Thermodynamics</string>
    <string name="thermo">\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Credit:4</font></b>\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-1.0 Basic Concepts and First Law</font></b>\n\n\n

1.1 Concept of continuum, macroscopic
approach, and thermodynamic systems.\n\n\n
1.2 Property, state, path and process-quasi-static
process\n\n\n
1.3 Work, Zeroth law of thermodynamics\n\n\n
1.4 Concept of temperature and heat, internal
energy, specific heat capacities, enthalpy\n\n\n
1.5 Concept of ideal and real gases\n\n\n
1.6 First law of thermodynamics and its applications to closed and open systems\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-2.0 Second Law and Entropy</font></b>\n\n\n

2.1 Second law of thermodynamics, Kelvin
planck and clausius statements of second
law\n\n\n
2.2 Reversibility and irreversibility\n\n\n
2.3 Carnot theorem – Carnot cycle, Reversed
Carnot cycle, Efficiency\n\n\n
2.4 Thermodynamic temperature scale –
Clausius inequality, concept of entropy\n\n\n
2.5 Entropy of ideal gas, principle of increase of
entropy\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-3.0 Air Standard Cycles</font></b>\n\n\n
3.1 Otto, Diesel, Dual, Ericsson, Atkinson,
Stirling and Brayton cycles\n\n\n
3.2 Air Standard efficiency, Mean effective
pressure\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit- 4.0 Fundamentals of Vapour Power
            Cycles</font></b>\n\n\n
4.1 Properties of pure substances – solid,
liquid and vapour phases, phase rule.\n\n\n
4.2 p-v, p-T, T-v, T-s, h-s diagrams, p-v-T
surfaces\n\n\n
4.3 Thermodynamic properties of steam\n\n\n
4.4 Calculations of work done and heat
transfer in non-flow and flow processes\n\n\n
4.5 Standard Rankine cycle, Reheat and
Regeneration cycle\n\n\n
4.6 Heat rate, Specific steam consumption,
Tonne of refrigeration\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit- 5.0 Basics of Propulsion and Heat
             Transfer.</font></b>\n\n\n
5.1 Classification of jet engines, basic jet
propulsion arrangement\n\n\n

5.2 Engine station number, thrust equation\n\n\n
5.3 Specific thrust, SFC, TSFC, specific
impulse, actual cycles, isentropic
efficiencies of jet engine components,
polytropic efficiency\n\n\n
5.4 Conduction in parallel, radial and
composite wall\n\n\n
5.5 Basics of convective and radiation heat
transfer.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Laboratory Experiment/Practical
            Titles</font></b>\n\n\n

        1. Performance test on a 4-stroke engine\n\n\n
        2. Valve timing of a 4 – stroke engine and
port timing of a 2 stroke engine\n\n\n
        3. Determination of effectiveness of a
parallel flow heat exchanger\n\n\n
        4. Determination of effectiveness of a
counter flow heat exchanger\n\n\n

        5. Determination of heating value of a fuel\n\n\n
        6. Determination of specific heat of solid\n\n\n
        7. Determination of thermal conductivity of
solid.\n\n\n
        8. Determination of thermal resistance of a
composite wall\n\n\n
        9. COP test on a vapour compression
refrigeration\n\n\n
        10. COP test on a vapour compression airconditioning\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Suggested Learning Resources:</font></b>\n\n\n
        1. Thermodynamics: An
Engineering Approach:
Cengel, Y. A. and Boles, M. A\n\n\n
        2. Principles of Engineering
Thermodynamics (SI Version):
Moran, M. J., Shapiro, H. N.,
Boettner, D. D., and Bailey, M. B\n\n\n
        3. Thermodynamics Arora C.P\n\n\n
        4. Engineering Thermodynamics Nag, P. K\n\n\n
        5. Thermodynamics Holman.J.P\n\n\n
        6. Thermodynamics for
Engineers
Merala C, Pother, Craig W,
Somerton

    </string>


    <string name="aesem3sub5">Python Programming</string>
    <string name="python">\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Credit:3</font></b>\n\n\n
         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-1.0 Basics Programming Syntax,
             Conditional and Iterative Statements</font></b>\n\n\n
1.1 Procedure oriented vs. Object-Oriented
approach of programming\n\n\n
1.2 Python character set, Python tokens ,
variables, concept of Lvalue and Rvalue,
use of comments.\n\n\n
1.3 Data types: number (integer, floating
point, complex), Boolean, sequence
(string, list, tuple), none, mapping(dictionary), mutable and immutable data
types\n\n\n
1.4 Operators: arithmetic operators, relational
operators, logical operators, assignment
operator, augmented assignment
operators. Expressions, statement, type
conversion &amp; input/output: precedence of
operators, expression, evaluation of
expression.\n\n\n
1.5 Conditional statements: simple if
statement, if- else statement, if-elif-else
statement\n\n\n
1.6 Iterative statements: while loop, for
loop, range function, break and continue
statements, nested loops\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-2.0 String, List, Tuples, Set and
             Dictionary</font></b>\n\n\n
2.1 String: indexing, string operations
(concatenation, repetition, membership &amp;
slicing), traversing a string using loops,
built-in functions.\n\n\n
2.2 Lists: introduction, indexing, list
operations: concatenation, repetition,
membership &amp; slicing, traversing a list,
built- in list functions, linear search on list
of numbers and counting the frequency of
elements in a list\n\n\n
2.3 Tuples: Creating, initializing, accessing
elements, tuple assignment, performing
operations on tuples, tuple methods and
built-in functions, nested tuples\n\n\n
2.4 Set: Creating set, traversing, adding,
removing data in set, performing set
operations like join, Union intersection,
difference\n\n\n
2.5 Dictionary: accessing items in a
dictionary using keys, mutability of
dictionary: adding a new item, modifying
an existing item, built-in dictionary
functions\n\n\n


       <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Unit-3.0 Python Functions, Modules and
           Packages</font></b>\n\n\n
3.1 Functions: types of function (built- in
functions, functions defined in module,
user defined functions), creating user
defined function, arguments and
parameters, default parameters, positional
parameters, Lambda functions, returning
value, scope of a variable: global scope,
local scope \n\n\n
        3.2 Modules and Packages: Importing module
using import Regular Expressions,
Exception Handling, PyPI Python
Package Index, Pip Python package
manager, Importing Libraries and
Functions\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-4.0 Object-Oriented Programming
            (OOP)</font></b>\n\n\n
4.1 OOPs Object oriented programming
concepts and approach, Abstraction,
encapsulation, class, object, class method
vs static method in Python, class and
static variable, constructor and destructors
in python\n\n\n
4.2 Inheritance: types of inheritance: single,
multiple, multilevel, hierarchical\n\n\n
4.3 Polymorphism: Polymorphism with class
method, polymorphism with inheritance,
method overriding, overloading\n\n\n

         <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit 5: Exception and File Handling in
             Python</font></b>\n\n\n
5.1 Exception Handling: syntax errors,
exceptions, need of exception handling,
user-defined exceptions, raising
exceptions, handling exceptions, catching
exceptions, Try - except - else clause, Try
- finally clause, recovering and continuing
with finally, built-in exception classes. \n\n\n
5.2 File Handling: text file and binary file,
file types, open and close files, reading
and writing text files, reading and writing
binary files, file access modes\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>   Unit-6.0 Data Analysis with Pandas</font></b>\n\n\n
6.1 Pandas data structures: Series,
Declaration, selecting elements, assigning
values, Filtering values, operations,
mathematical functions, evaluating values,
handling missing data, creating series from
dictionaries, adding two series.\n\n\n
6.2 Data Frame: Defining, selecting elements,
assigning values, membership, deleting a
column, filtering. Index Objects: Indexing,
Re-indexing, Dropping, sorting and
ranking,Descriptive Statistics\n\n\n
6.3 Data Loading: Reading and Writing csv,
xls, text data files, Data Cleaning and
Preparation: Handling missing data,
removing duplicates, replacing values,
Vectorized String Methods, Hierarchical
Indexing, Merging and Combining, Data
aggregation and Grouping.\n\n\n


       <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Laboratory Experiment/Practical
           Titles</font></b>\n\n\n

        1. a) Download and Install IDLE.\n\n\n
b) Write and execute Python program tob) Calculate the Area of a Triangle
where its three sides a, b, c are
given. s=(a+b+c)/2, Area=square
root of s(s-a)(s-b)(s-c) (write
program without using function)\n\n\n
c) Swap Two Variables\n\n\n
d) Solve quadratic equation for real
numbers.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>    2. Write and execute Python program to </font></b>\n\n\n
        a) Check if a Number is Positive,
Negative or zero.\n\n\n
b) Check whether the given year is a
Leap Year.\n\n\n
c) Print all Prime Numbers in an
Interval.\n\n\n
d) Display the multiplication Table
based on the given input.\n\n\n
e) Print the Fibonacci sequence.\n\n\n
f) Find the Factorial of a Number.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  3. Write and execute Python program to</font></b>\n\n\n
        a) Check whether the string is
Palindrome\n\n\n
b) Reverse words in a given String in
Python\n\n\n
c) identify in a strings the name,
position and counting of vowels.\n\n\n
d) Count the Number of matching
characters in a pair of string (set)\n\n\n
e) Python program for removing i-th
character from a string\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 4. Write and execute Python program to</font></b>\n\n\n
        a) find largest number in a given list
without using max().\n\n\n
b) find the common numbers from
two lists.\n\n\n
c) create a list of even numbers and
another list of odd numbers from a
given list.\n\n\n
d) To find number of occurrences of
given number without using builtin methods.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  5. Write and execute Python program to </font></b>\n\n\n
        a) find the index of an item of a
tuple.\n\n\n
b) find the length of a tuple.\n\n\n
c) to reverse a tuple.\n\n\n
d) Write a Python program to sort a
list of tuple by its float element.
Sample data: [("item1", "12.20"),
("item2", "15.10"), ("item3", "24.5")]
Expected Output: [("item3", "24.5"),
("item2", "15.10"), ("item1", "12.20")]\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 6. Write and execute Python program to</font></b>\n\n\n
        a) create an intersection of sets.\n\n\n
b) create a union of sets.\n\n\n
c) create set difference.\n\n\n
d) check if two given sets have no
elements in common.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>    7. Write and execute Python program to</font></b>\n\n\n
        a) Write a Python script to concatenate
two dictionaries to create a new one\n\n\n
b) Write a Python script to merge two
Python dictionaries.\n\n\n
c) Write a Python program to combine
two dictionary adding values for
common keys.
d1 = {"a" : 100, "b": 200, "c" :300}
d2 = {"a": 300, "b": 200, "d":400}
Sample output: d({"a": 400, "b": 400,
"d": 400, "c": 300})\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  8. Write and execute Python program to</font></b>\n\n\n
        a) Write a Python function for
reversing a string and call it.\n\n\n
b) Write a Python function for
calculating compound interest and
call it.\n\n\n
c) Write a Python function for
calculating the factorial of a number
and call it to calculate !n/(!r)*!(n-r))
where symbol “! “ stands for
factorial.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  9. Write program using OOP approach to –</font></b>\n\n\n
a) create an instance of a specified
class and display the namespace of
the said instance\n\n\n

b) create a Python class named Student
with two attributes: student_id,
student_name. Add a new attribute:
student_class. Create a function to display all attributes and their
values in the Student class.\n\n\n

c) Create a Python class named
Student with two instances
student1, student2 and assign values
to the instances attributes. Print all
the attributes of the student1,
student2 instances\n\n\n

d) Write programs to demonstrate use
of following types of inheritance:\n\n

i. Single inheritance\n\n

ii. Multiple inheritance\n\n

iii. Multilevel inheritance\n\n\n

e) Demonstrate use of polymorphism
with following situations:\n\n\

i. Polymorphism in operator\n\n

ii. Polymorphism in user defined
method\n\n

iii. Polymorphism in built-in
function\n\n

iv. Polymorphism with class
method\n\n

v. Polymorphism with method
overriding\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 10. a) Using exception handling feature
such as try…except, try finallywrite minimum three programs to
handle following types of
            exceptions.</font></b>\n\n\
i. TypeError\n
ii. NameError\n
iii. IndexError\n
iv. KeyError\n
v. ValueErrorn\n
vi. IOError\n
vii. ZeroDivisionError\n\n
b) Write Python program to
demonstrate file operations.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>11 Working with a Series using Pandas</font></b>\n\n\n
a) Create a series using list and
dictionary. 10b. Create a series
using NumPy functions
inPandas.\n\n\n
b) Print the index and values of
series.\n\n
c) Print the first and last few rows
from theseries.\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> 12 Working with Data Frame Rows</font></b>\n\n\n
a) Slicing Data Frame
using loc and iloc.11b.
Filter multiple rows
using isin.\n\n\n
b) Select first n rows and last n rows\n\n
c) Select rows randomly n rows and fractionsof rows (use df.
sample method)\n\n\n
d) Count the number of rows
with eachunique value of
variables\n\n\n
e) Select nlargest and nsmallest
values.11g. Order/sort the rows\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>13 Merge and combine data</font></b>\n\n
a) Perform the append, concat
and combinefirst operations
on Data Frames.\n\n\n
b) Apply different types of merge
on data. 12c. Use a query
method to filter Data Frame\n\n\n
c) with multiple conditions.\n\n\n


        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Suggested Learning Resources:</font></b>\n\n\n

        1 Introduction to Computing
and Problem-Solving using Python:
E. Balagurusamy\n\n\n

2
Core Python Applications
Programming:
Wesley J. Chun\n\n\n

      3 Python Cookbook
David Beazley, Brian
Jones.,\n\n\n

       4 Python Data Analytics :Fabio Nelli\n\n\n

        5 Python for Data Analysis: Data
Wrangling with Pandas, Numpy,
and IPython:
Wes McKinney \n\n\n</string>


    <string name="aesem3sub6">Engineering Mathematics-III</string>
    <string name="math3">\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Credit:2</font></b>\n\n\n
        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-1.0 Probability and Statistics</font></b>\n\n\n
1.1 Variance and Standard Deviation,
Covariance.\n\n\n
1.2 Correlation, Regression.\n\n\n
1.3 Discrete Distribution: Binomial, Poisson’s.\n\n\n
1.4 Continuous Distribution: Normal
Distribution.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-2.0 Statistical Computation and Quality
            Control</font></b>\n\n\n
2.1 Frequency distribution\n\n\n
2.2 Graphical representation of Frequency
distribution\n\n\n
2.3 Types of Frequency Curves\n\n\n
2.4 Standard error of estimate\n\n\n
2.5 Statistical Quality Control\n\n\n
2.6 Technique of Quality Control\n\n\n
2.7 Control charts for variables and attributes\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Unit-3.0 Test of Significance</font></b>
3.1 Null and Alternative Hypotheses\n\n\n
3.2 Type I and Type II Errors,\n\n\n
3.3 Student’s t-Test: Two-Tailed and OneTailed Tests\n\n\n
3.4 F- Test.\n\n\n
3.5 𝜒2 chi square Test for the goodness of fit. \n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>  Unit-4.0 Graph Theory and Fuzzy Set Theory</font></b>\n\n\n
4.1 Planer, weighted, and Isomorphic
graphs.\n\n\n
4.2 Paths, Cycles, and connectivity\n\n\n
4.3 shortest path in a weighted graph.\n\n\n
4.4 Eulerian paths and circuits,
Hamiltonian paths and circuits.\n\n\n
4.5 Fuzzy Set and its operations.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'> Unit-5.0 Optimization Techniques</font></b>\n\n\n
5.1 Formulation of Linear Programming
Problem (LPP).\n\n\n
5.2 Solution concept of LPP using
Graphical method and Simplex method.\n\n\n
5.3 Big ‘M’ Method, Duality.\n\n\n
5.4 Transportation Problems.\n\n\n
5.5 Assignment Problems (AP):
Mathematical Formulation.\n\n\n

        <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Suggested Learning Resources:</font></b>\n\n\n
        1. Advanced Engineering
Mathematics:
Krezig, Ervin\n\n
        2. Understanding Engineering
Mathematics:
John Bird\n\n\n
        3. Probability for Statistics and
Machine Learning:
Anirban Das Gupta\n\n\n
        4. Probability and Computing
Randomized Algorithms and
Probabilistic Analysis:
Michael
Mitzenmacher and
Eli Upfal\n\n\n

      5.  An Introduction to Statistical
Learning with Applications in
R:
Gareth James,
Daniela Witten,
Trevor Hastie Robert
and Tibshirani\n\n\n

        6. Python for Probability,
Statistics, and Machine
Learning:  José Unpingco\n\n\n

        7. Operations Research :Prem Kumar Gupta
and Dr. D. S.Hira\n\n\n

        8. Operations Research: Theory,
Methods and Applications
S. D.
Sharma, Himanshu
Sharma\n\n\n

        9. SCHAUMS Outline of Graph
Theory:
V. K. Balakrishnan \n\n\n

        10. Fuzzy Sets, Fuzzy Logic and
Their Applications 2020:
        Michael Voskoglou\n\n\n</string>


    <string name="aesem3sub7">Indian Constitution</string>
    <string name="IC">\n\n\n
            <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Credit:1</font></b>\n\n\n
            <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-1.0 Constitution and Preamble</font></b>\n\n\n
1.1 Meaning of the constitution of India.\n\n\n
1.2 Historical perspective of the Constitution of
India.\n\n\n
1.3 Salient features and characteristics of the
Constitution of India.\n\n\n
1.4 Preamble to the Constitution of India.\n\n\n

              <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-2.0 Fundamental Rights and Directive
                  Principles</font></b>\n\n\n
2.1 Fundamental Rights under Part-III.\n\n\n\
2.2 Fundamental duties and their significance.\n\n\n
2.3 Relevance of Directive Principles of State
Policy under part-IV.\n\n\n

            <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Unit-3.0 Governance and Amendments</font></b>\n\n\n
3.1 Amendment of the Constitutional Powers
and Procedure\n\n\n
3.2 Major Constitutional Amendment
procedure - 42nd, 44th, 74th, 76th, 86th and
91st\n\n\n


            <b><font fgcolor='#F700FF'>Suggested Learning Resources:</font></b>\n\n\n

            1 The Constitution of India P.M.Bakshi\n\n\n

            2 Introduction to Indian Constitution D.D.Basu\n\n\n

            3 Introduction to Constitution of India B. K. Sharma\n\n\n

            4 The Constitution of India B.L. Fadia\n\n\n

            5 The Constitutional Law of India Durga Das Basu\n\n\n



    </string>


</resources>